Ephesians  4 : 1 - 32

4 Therefore I, the prisoner in the Lord, appeal to you to walk worthily of the calling with which you were called, ^2 with all humility[*] and mildness, with patience, putting up with one another in love, ^3 earnestly endeavoring to maintain the oneness of the spirit in the uniting bond of peace. ^4 One body there is, and one spirit, just as you were called to the one hope of your calling; ^5 one Lord, one faith, one baptism; ^6 one God and Father of all, who is over all and through all and in all.

^7 Now undeserved kindness was given to each one of us according to how the Christ measured out the free gift. ^8 For it says: “When he ascended on high he carried away captives; he gave gifts in men.” ^9 Now what does the expression “he ascended” mean but that he also descended into the lower regions, that is, the earth? ^10 The very one who descended is also the one who ascended far above all the heavens, so that he might give fullness to all things.

^11 And he gave some as apostles, some as prophets, some as evangelizers,[*] some as shepherds and teachers, ^12 with a view to the readjustment[*] of the holy ones, for ministerial work, to build up the body of the Christ, ^13 until we all attain to the oneness[*] of the faith and of the accurate knowledge of the Son of God, to being a full-grown[*] man, attaining the measure of stature that belongs to the fullness of the Christ. ^14 So we should no longer be children, tossed about as by waves and carried here and there by every wind of teaching by means of the trickery of men, by means of cunning in deceptive schemes. ^15 But speaking the truth, let us by love grow up in all things into him who is the head, Christ. ^16 From him all the body is harmoniously joined together and made to cooperate through every joint that gives what is needed. When each respective member functions properly, this contributes to the growth of the body as it builds itself up in love.

^17 So this is what I say and bear witness to in the Lord, that you should no longer go on walking just as the nations also walk, in the futility[*] of their minds. ^18 They are in darkness mentally and alienated from the life that belongs to God, because of the ignorance that is in them, because of the insensitivity[*] of their hearts. ^19 Having gone past all moral sense, they gave themselves over to brazen conduct[*] to practice every sort of uncleanness with greediness.

^20 But you did not learn the Christ to be like this, ^21 if, indeed, you heard him and were taught by means of him, just as truth is in Jesus. ^22 You were taught to put away the old personality that conforms to your former course of conduct and that is being corrupted according to its deceptive desires. ^23 And you should continue to be made new in your dominant mental attitude,[*] ^24 and should put on the new personality that was created according to God’s will in true righteousness and loyalty.

^25 Therefore, now that you have put away deceit, each one of you speak truth with his neighbor, because we are members belonging to one another. ^26 Be wrathful, but do not sin; do not let the sun set while you are still angry; ^27 do not give the Devil an opportunity.[*] ^28 Let the one who steals steal no more; rather, let him do hard work, doing good work with his hands, so that he may have something to share with someone in need. ^29 Let a rotten word not come out of your mouth, but only what is good for building up as the need may be, to impart what is beneficial to the hearers. ^30 Also, do not be grieving[*] God’s holy spirit, with which you have been sealed for a day of releasing by ransom.

^31 Put away from yourselves every kind of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath, screaming, and abusive speech, as well as everything injurious. ^32 But become kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving one another just as God also by Christ freely forgave you.

^ Eph. 4:2 Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ Eph. 4:11 Or “proclaimers of the good news.”

^ Eph. 4:12 Or “training.”

^ Eph. 4:13 Or “unity.”

^ Eph. 4:13 Or “mature.”

^ Eph. 4:17 Or “emptiness; vanity.”

^ Eph. 4:18 Lit., “dulling.”

^ Eph. 4:19 Or “shameless conduct.” Greek, a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

^ Eph. 4:23 Or “in the force actuating your mind.” Lit., “to the spirit of your mind.”

^ Eph. 4:27 Or “neither allow place for the Devil.”

^ Eph. 4:30 Or “cause sorrow to.”

Philippians  1 : 1 - 30

TO THE PHILIPPIANS

1 Paul and Timothy, slaves of Christ Jesus, to all the holy ones in union with Christ Jesus who are in Phi·lipʹpi, along with overseers and ministerial servants:

^2 May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

^3 I thank my God always when I remember you ^4 in every supplication of mine for all of you. I offer each supplication with joy, ^5 because of the contribution you have made to[*] the good news from the first day until this moment. ^6 For I am confident of this very thing, that the one who started a good work in you will bring it to completion until the day of Christ Jesus. ^7 It is only right for me to think this regarding all of you, since I have you in my heart, you who are sharers with me in the undeserved kindness both in my prison bonds and in the defending and legally establishing of the good news.

^8 For God is my witness of how I am longing for all of you with such tender affection as Christ Jesus has. ^9 And this is what I continue praying, that your love may abound still more and more with accurate knowledge and full discernment; ^10 that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ; ^11 and that you may be filled with righteous fruit, which is through Jesus Christ, to God’s glory and praise.

^12 Now I want you to know, brothers, that my situation has actually turned out for the advancement of the good news, ^13 so that my prison bonds for the sake of Christ have become public knowledge among all the Prae·toʹri·an Guard and all the rest. ^14 Now most of the brothers in the Lord have gained confidence because of my prison bonds, and they are showing all the more courage to speak the word of God fearlessly.

^15 True, some are preaching the Christ out of envy and rivalry, but others out of goodwill. ^16 The latter are proclaiming the Christ out of love, for they know that I have been appointed to defend the good news; ^17 but the former do it out of contentiousness, not with a pure motive, for they are intending to create trouble for me in my prison bonds. ^18 With what result? Only that in every way, whether in pretense or in truth, Christ is being proclaimed, and I rejoice over this. In fact, I will also keep on rejoicing, ^19 for I know that this will result in my salvation through your supplication and with the support of the spirit of Jesus Christ. ^20 This is in harmony with my eager expectation and hope that I will not be ashamed in any respect, but that with all freeness of speech Christ will now, as always before, be magnified by means of my body, whether through life or through death.

^21 For in my case, to live is Christ and to die is gain. ^22 Now if I am to live on in the flesh, this is a fruitage of my work; yet what I would choose, I do not make known. ^23 I am torn between these two things, for I do desire the releasing and the being with Christ, which is, to be sure, far better. ^24 However, it is more necessary for me to remain in the flesh for your sakes. ^25 So, being confident of this, I know I will remain and continue with all of you for your advancement and your joy in the faith, ^26 so that your exultation may overflow in Christ Jesus because of me when I am again present with you.

^27 Only behave[*] in a manner worthy of the good news about the Christ, so that whether I come and see you or I am absent, I may hear about you and learn that you are standing firm in one spirit, with one soul,[*] striving side by side for the faith of the good news, ^28 and in no way being frightened by your opponents. This very thing is a proof of destruction for them, but of salvation for you; and this is from God. ^29 For you have been given the privilege in behalf of Christ, not only to put your faith in him but also to suffer in his behalf. ^30 For you are facing the same struggle that you saw me face, which you now hear that I am still facing.

^ Phil. 1:5 Or “because of your participation in furthering.”

^ Phil. 1:27 Or “carry on as citizens.”

^ Phil. 1:27 Or “with one accord.”

Philippians  2 : 1 - 30

2 If, then, there is any encouragement in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any spiritual fellowship,[*] if any tender affection and compassion, ^2 make my joy full by being of the same mind and having the same love, being completely united,[*] having the one thought in mind. ^3 Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility[*] consider others superior to you, ^4 as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

^5 Keep this mental attitude in you that was also in Christ Jesus, ^6 who, although he was existing in God’s form, did not even consider the idea of trying to be equal to God. ^7 No, but he emptied himself and took a slave’s form and became human.[*] ^8 More than that, when he came as a man,[*] he humbled himself and became obedient to the point of death, yes, death on a torture stake.[*] ^9 For this very reason, God exalted him to a superior position and kindly gave him the name that is above every other name, ^10 so that in the name of Jesus every knee should bend—of those in heaven and those on earth and those under the ground— ^11 and every tongue should openly acknowledge that Jesus Christ is Lord to the glory of God the Father.

^12 Consequently, my beloved ones, just as you have always obeyed, not only during my presence but now much more readily during my absence, keep working out your own salvation with fear and trembling. ^13 For God is the one who for the sake of his good pleasure energizes you, giving you both the desire and the power to act. ^14 Keep doing all things free from murmuring and arguments, ^15 so that you may come to be blameless and innocent, children of God without a blemish in the midst of a crooked and twisted generation, among whom you are shining as illuminators in the world, ^16 keeping a tight grip on the word of life. Then I may have reason for rejoicing in Christ’s day, knowing that I did not run in vain or work hard in vain. ^17 However, even if I am being poured out like a drink offering on the sacrifice and the holy service[*] to which your faith has led you, I am glad and I rejoice with all of you. ^18 In the same way, you also should be glad and rejoice with me.

^19 Now I am hoping in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you shortly, so that I may be encouraged when I receive news about you. ^20 For I have no one else of a disposition like his who will genuinely care for your concerns. ^21 For all the others are seeking their own interests, not those of Jesus Christ. ^22 But you know the proof he gave of himself, that like a child with a father he slaved with me to advance the good news. ^23 Therefore, he is the one I am hoping to send just as soon as I see how things turn out for me. ^24 Indeed, I am confident in the Lord that I myself will also come soon.

^25 But for now I consider it necessary to send to you E·paph·ro·diʹtus, my brother and fellow worker and fellow soldier, and your envoy and personal servant for my need, ^26 since he is longing to see all of you and is depressed because you heard he had fallen sick. ^27 Indeed, he did fall sick nearly to the point of death; but God had mercy on him, in fact, not only on him but also on me, so that I should not have one grief after another. ^28 Therefore, I am sending him with the greatest urgency, so that when you see him you may again rejoice and I may also be less anxious. ^29 So give him the customary welcome in the Lord with all joy, and keep holding men of that sort dear, ^30 because he nearly died on account of the work of Christ,[*] risking his life[*] in order to make up for your not being here to render personal service to me.

^ Phil. 2:1 Lit., “any sharing of spirit.”

^ Phil. 2:2 Or “being joined together in soul.”

^ Phil. 2:3 Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ Phil. 2:7 Lit., “came to be in the likeness of men.”

^ Phil. 2:8 Lit., “when he was found in appearance as a man.”

^ Phil. 2:8 See Glossary.

^ Phil. 2:17 Or “the public service.”

^ Phil. 2:30 Or possibly, “of the Lord’s work.”

^ Phil. 2:30 Or “exposing his soul to danger.”

Philippians  3 : 1 - 21

3 Finally, my brothers, continue rejoicing in the Lord. It is not troublesome for me to write the same things to you, and it is for your safety.

^2 Look out for the dogs; look out for those who cause injury; look out for those who mutilate the flesh. ^3 For we are those with the real circumcision, we who are rendering sacred service by God’s spirit and boasting in Christ Jesus and who do not base our confidence in the flesh, ^4 though I, if anyone, do have grounds for confidence in the flesh.

If any other man thinks he has grounds for confidence in the flesh, I have more: ^5 circumcised the eighth day, of the nation of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew born from Hebrews; regarding law, a Pharisee; ^6 regarding zeal, persecuting the congregation; regarding righteousness based on law, one who proved himself blameless. ^7 Yet, the things that were gains to me, I have considered loss[*] on account of the Christ. ^8 What is more, I do indeed also consider all things to be loss on account of the excelling value of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord. For his sake I have taken the loss of all things and I consider them as a lot of refuse,[*] that I may gain Christ ^9 and be found in union with him, not because of my own righteousness from following the Law, but because of the righteousness that is through faith in Christ, the righteousness from God based on faith. ^10 My aim is to know him and the power of his resurrection and to share in his sufferings, submitting myself to a death like his, ^11 to see if at all possible I may attain to the earlier resurrection from the dead.

^12 Not that I have already received it or am already made perfect, but I am pressing on to see if I may also lay hold on that for which Christ Jesus selected me.[*] ^13 Brothers, I do not yet consider myself as having taken hold of it; but one thing is certain: Forgetting the things behind and stretching forward to the things ahead, ^14 I am pressing on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God by means of Christ Jesus. ^15 Therefore, let those of us who are mature be of this mental attitude, and if you are mentally inclined otherwise in any respect, God will reveal the above attitude to you. ^16 At any rate, to the extent we have made progress, let us go on walking orderly in this same course.

^17 Unitedly become imitators of me, brothers, and keep your eye on those who are walking in a way that is in harmony with the example we set for you. ^18 For there are many—I used to mention them often but now I mention them also with weeping—who are walking as enemies of the torture stake[*] of the Christ. ^19 Their end is destruction, and their god is their belly, and their glory is really their shame, and they have their minds on earthly things. ^20 But our citizenship exists in the heavens, and we are eagerly waiting for a savior from there, the Lord Jesus Christ, ^21 who will transform our humble body to be like[*] his glorious body by his great power that enables him to subject all things to himself.

^ Phil. 3:7 Or possibly, “have willingly abandoned.”

^ Phil. 3:8 Or “garbage; rubbish.”

^ Phil. 3:12 Lit., “laid hold on me.”

^ Phil. 3:18 See Glossary.

^ Phil. 3:21 Lit., “to be conformed to.”

Philippians  4 : 1 - 23

4 Consequently, my brothers whom I love and long for, my joy and crown, stand firm in this way in the Lord, my beloved ones.

^2 I urge Eu·oʹdi·a and I urge Synʹty·che to be of the same mind in the Lord. ^3 Yes, I request you also, as a true fellow worker,[*] to keep assisting these women who have striven[*] side by side with me for the good news, along with Clement as well as the rest of my fellow workers, whose names are in the book of life.

^4 Always rejoice in the Lord. Again I will say, Rejoice! ^5 Let your reasonableness become known to all men. The Lord is near. ^6 Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; ^7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers[*] by means of Christ Jesus.

^8 Finally, brothers, whatever things are true, whatever things are of serious concern, whatever things are righteous, whatever things are chaste,[*] whatever things are lovable, whatever things are well-spoken-of, whatever things are virtuous, and whatever things are praiseworthy, continue considering[*] these things. ^9 The things that you learned as well as accepted and heard and saw in connection with me, practice these, and the God of peace will be with you.

^10 I rejoice greatly in the Lord that now at last you have renewed your concern for me. Though you were concerned about me, you lacked opportunity to show it. ^11 Not that I am saying this because I am in need, for I have learned to be self-sufficient[*] regardless of my circumstances. ^12 I know how to be low on provisions and how to have an abundance. In everything and in all circumstances I have learned the secret of both how to be full and how to hunger, both how to have an abundance and how to do without. ^13 For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.

^14 Nevertheless, you did well to share with me in my tribulation. ^15 In fact, you Phi·lipʹpi·ans also know that after you first learned the good news, when I departed from Mac·e·doʹni·a, not a congregation shared with me in the matter of giving and receiving, except you alone; ^16 for while I was in Thes·sa·lo·niʹca, you sent something to me for my need not just once but twice. ^17 Not that I am looking for a gift, but I want the fruitage that brings more credit to your account. ^18 However, I have everything I need and even more. I am fully supplied, now that I have received from E·paph·ro·diʹtus what you sent, a sweet fragrance, an acceptable sacrifice, well-pleasing to God. ^19 In turn my God will fully supply all your need according to his riches in glory by means of Christ Jesus. ^20 Now to our God and Father be the glory forever and ever. Amen.

^21 Give my greetings to every holy one in union with Christ Jesus. The brothers who are with me send you their greetings. ^22 All the holy ones, but especially those of the household of Caesar, send you their greetings.

^23 The undeserved kindness of the Lord Jesus Christ be with the spirit you show.

^ Phil. 4:3 Lit., “genuine yokefellow.”

^ Phil. 4:3 Or “who have struggled hard.”

^ Phil. 4:7 Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

^ Phil. 4:8 Or “pure.”

^ Phil. 4:8 Or “thinking about; meditating on.”

^ Phil. 4:11 Or “content.”

Colossians  1 : 1 - 29

TO THE COLOSSIANS

1 Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through God’s will, and Timothy our brother, ^2 to the holy ones and faithful brothers in union with Christ at Co·losʹsae:

May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father.

^3 We always thank God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, when we pray for you, ^4 since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus and the love you have for all the holy ones ^5 because of the hope that is being reserved for you in the heavens. You previously heard about this hope through the message of truth of the good news ^6 that has come to you. Just as the good news is bearing fruit and increasing in all the world, so it is also doing among you from the day you heard and accurately knew the undeserved kindness of God in truth. ^7 That is what you have learned from our beloved fellow slave Epʹa·phras, who is a faithful minister of the Christ on our behalf. ^8 He also made known to us your love in a spiritual way.[*]

^9 That is also why from the day we heard of it, we have never stopped praying for you and asking that you may be filled with the accurate knowledge of his will in all wisdom and spiritual comprehension, ^10 so as to walk worthily of Jehovah[*] in order to please him fully as you go on bearing fruit in every good work and increasing in the accurate knowledge of God; ^11 and may you be strengthened with all power according to his glorious might so that you may endure fully with patience and joy, ^12 as you thank the Father, who made you qualify to share in the inheritance of the holy ones in the light.

^13 He rescued us from the authority of the darkness and transferred us into the kingdom of his beloved Son, ^14 by means of whom we have our release by ransom, the forgiveness of our sins. ^15 He is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of all creation; ^16 because by means of him all other things were created in the heavens and on the earth, the things visible and the things invisible, whether they are thrones or lordships or governments or authorities. All other things have been created through him and for him. ^17 Also, he is before all other things, and by means of him all other things were made to exist, ^18 and he is the head of the body, the congregation. He is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead, so that he might become the one who is first in all things; ^19 because God was pleased to have all fullness to dwell in him, ^20 and through him to reconcile to himself all other things by making peace through the blood he shed on the torture stake,[*] whether the things on the earth or the things in the heavens.

^21 Indeed, you who were once alienated and enemies because your minds were on the works that were wicked, ^22 he has now reconciled by means of that one’s fleshly body through his death, in order to present you holy and unblemished and open to no accusation before him— ^23 provided, of course, that you continue in the faith, established on the foundation and steadfast, not being shifted away from the hope of that good news that you heard and that was preached in all creation under heaven. Of this good news I, Paul, became a minister.

^24 I am now rejoicing in my sufferings for your sake, and I am undergoing the tribulations of the Christ that are yet lacking in my flesh in behalf of his body, which is the congregation. ^25 I became a minister of this congregation in accord with the stewardship from God that was given to me in your behalf to preach the word of God fully, ^26 the sacred secret that was hidden from the past systems of things[*] and from the past generations. But now it has been revealed to his holy ones, ^27 to whom God has been pleased to make known among the nations the glorious riches of this sacred secret, which is Christ in union with you, the hope of his glory. ^28 He is the one we are proclaiming, admonishing everyone and teaching everyone in all wisdom, so that we may present every person complete in union with Christ. ^29 To this end I am indeed working hard, exerting myself with his strength that is operating powerfully within me.

^ Col. 1:8 Lit., “in spirit.”

^ Col. 1:10 See App. A5.

^ Col. 1:20 See Glossary.

^ Col. 1:26 Or “past ages.” See Glossary.

Colossians  2 : 1 - 23

2 For I want you to realize how great a struggle I am having in your behalf and in behalf of those at La·o·di·ceʹa and in behalf of all those who have not personally seen me.[*] ^2 This is so that their hearts may be comforted and that they may be harmoniously joined together in love and may have all the riches that result from the full assurance of their understanding, in order to gain an accurate knowledge of the sacred secret of God, namely, Christ. ^3 Carefully concealed in him are all the treasures of wisdom and of knowledge. ^4 I am saying this so that no one may delude you with persuasive arguments. ^5 Though I am absent in body, I am with you in spirit, rejoicing to see your good order and the firmness of your faith in Christ.

^6 Therefore, just as you have accepted Christ Jesus the Lord, go on walking in union with him, ^7 being rooted and built up in him and being stabilized in the faith, just as you were taught, and overflowing with thanksgiving.

^8 Look out that no one takes you captive[*] by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ; ^9 because it is in him that all the fullness of the divine quality dwells bodily. ^10 So you have acquired a fullness by means of him, the one who is the head of all government and authority. ^11 By your relationship with him, you were also circumcised with a circumcision performed without hands by stripping off the fleshly body, by the circumcision that belongs to the Christ. ^12 For you were buried with him in his baptism, and by your relationship with him you were also raised up together through your faith in the powerful work of God, who raised him up from the dead.

^13 Furthermore, though you were dead in your trespasses and in the uncircumcised state of your flesh, God made you alive together with him. He kindly forgave us all our trespasses ^14 and erased[*] the handwritten document that consisted of decrees and was in opposition to us. He has taken it out of the way by nailing it to the torture stake.[*] ^15 He has stripped the governments and the authorities bare and has publicly exhibited them as conquered, leading them in a triumphal procession by means of it.[*]

^16 Therefore, do not let anyone judge you about what you eat and drink or about the observance of a festival or of the new moon or of a sabbath. ^17 Those things are a shadow of the things to come, but the reality belongs to the Christ. ^18 Let no man deprive you of the prize who takes delight in a false humility and a form of worship of the angels, “taking his stand on”[*] the things he has seen. He is actually puffed up without proper cause by his fleshly frame of mind, ^19 and he is not holding fast to the head, to the one through whom the whole body is supplied and harmoniously joined together by means of its joints and ligaments and made to grow with the growth that is from God.

^20 If you died together with Christ with respect to the elementary things of the world, why do you live as if still part of the world by further subjecting yourselves to the decrees: ^21 “Do not handle, nor taste, nor touch,” ^22 referring to things that all perish with their use, according to the commands and teachings of men? ^23 Although those things have an appearance of wisdom in a self-imposed form of worship and a false humility, a harsh treatment of the body, they are of no value in combating the satisfying of the flesh.

^ Col. 2:1 Lit., “not seen my face in the flesh.”

^ Col. 2:8 Or “carries you off as his prey.”

^ Col. 2:14 Or “blotted out.”

^ Col. 2:14 See Glossary.

^ Col. 2:15 Or possibly, “him.”

^ Col. 2:18 Quoted from pagan mystery (initiation) rites.

Colossians  4 : 1 - 18

4 You masters, treat your slaves in a righteous and fair way, knowing that you also have a Master in heaven.

^2 Persevere in prayer, remaining awake in it with thanksgiving. ^3 At the same time, pray also for us, that God may open a door for the word so that we can declare the sacred secret about the Christ, for which I am in prison bonds, ^4 and that I may proclaim it as clearly as I ought to.

^5 Go on walking in wisdom toward those on the outside, making the best use of your time.[*] ^6 Let your words always be gracious, seasoned with salt, so that you will know how you should answer each person.

^7 Tychʹi·cus, my beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow slave in the Lord, will tell you all the news about me. ^8 I am sending him to you so that you will know how we are and that he may comfort your hearts. ^9 He is coming along with O·nesʹi·mus, my faithful and beloved brother, who is from among you; they will tell you all the things happening here.

^10 Ar·is·tarʹchus, my fellow captive, sends you his greetings, and so does Mark, the cousin of Barʹna·bas (concerning whom you received instructions to welcome him if he comes to you), ^11 and Jesus who is called Justus, who are of those circumcised. Only these are my fellow workers for the Kingdom of God, and they have become a source of great comfort[*] to me. ^12 Epʹa·phras, a slave of Christ Jesus who is from among you, sends you his greetings. He is always exerting himself in your behalf in his prayers, so that you may finally stand complete and with firm conviction in all the will of God. ^13 For I bear him witness that he makes great efforts in your behalf and in behalf of those in La·o·di·ceʹa and Hi·e·rapʹo·lis.

^14 Luke, the beloved physician, sends you his greetings, and so does Deʹmas. ^15 Give my greetings to the brothers in La·o·di·ceʹa and to Nymʹpha and to the congregation at her house. ^16 And when this letter has been read among you, arrange for it also to be read in the congregation of the La·o·di·ceʹans and for you also to read the one from La·o·di·ceʹa. ^17 Also, tell Ar·chipʹpus: “Pay attention to the ministry that you accepted in the Lord, in order to fulfill it.”

^18 Here is my greeting, Paul’s, in my own hand. Keep my prison bonds in mind. The undeserved kindness be with you.

^ Col. 4:5 Lit., “buying out the appointed time.”

^ Col. 4:11 Or “a strengthening aid.”

1 Thessalonians  1 : 1 - 10

THE FIRST TO THE THESSALONIANS

1 Paul, Sil·vaʹnus,[*] and Timothy, to the congregation of the Thes·sa·loʹni·ans in union with God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ:

May you have undeserved kindness and peace.

^2 We always thank God when we mention all of you in our prayers, ^3 for we continually remember your faithful work, your loving labor, and your endurance because of your hope in our Lord Jesus Christ in the presence of our God and Father. ^4 For we know, brothers loved by God, his choosing of you, ^5 because the good news we preach did not come to you with speech alone but also with power and with holy spirit and with strong conviction, just as you know what sort of men we became among you for your sakes. ^6 And you became imitators of us and of the Lord, seeing that you accepted the word under much tribulation with joy of holy spirit, ^7 so that you became an example to all the believers in Mac·e·doʹni·a and in A·chaʹia.

^8 The fact is, not only has the word of Jehovah[*] sounded out from you in Mac·e·doʹni·a and A·chaʹia but your faith in God has spread abroad in every place, so that we do not need to say anything. ^9 For they themselves keep reporting about our first contact with you and how you turned to God from your idols to slave for a living and true God, ^10 and to wait for his Son from the heavens, whom he raised up from the dead, namely, Jesus, who rescues us from the wrath that is coming.

^ 1 Thess. 1:1 Also called Silas.

^ 1 Thess. 1:8 See App. A5.

1 Thessalonians  2 : 1 - 20

2 You yourselves surely know, brothers, that our visit to you has not been without results. ^2 For although we had first suffered and been insolently treated in Phi·lipʹpi, as you know, we mustered up boldness[*] by means of our God to tell you the good news of God in the face of much opposition.[*] ^3 For the exhortation we give does not spring from error or from uncleanness or with deceit, ^4 but just as we have been approved by God to be entrusted with the good news, so we speak to please, not men, but God, who examines our hearts.

^5 In fact, you know that we never used flattering speech or put on any false front with greedy motives; God is witness! ^6 Nor have we been seeking glory from men, either from you or from others, though we could be an expensive burden as apostles of Christ. ^7 On the contrary, we became gentle in your midst, as when a nursing mother tenderly cares for[*] her own children. ^8 So having tender affection for you, we were determined[*] to impart to you, not only the good news of God but also our very selves,[*] because you became so beloved to us.

^9 Surely you remember, brothers, our labor and toil. We were working night and day, so that we would not put an expensive burden on any one of you, when we preached the good news of God to you. ^10 You are witnesses, God is also, of how loyal and righteous and blameless we behaved toward you believers. ^11 You well know that we kept exhorting and consoling you and bearing witness to each one of you, just as a father does his children, ^12 so that you would go on walking worthily of God, who is calling you to his Kingdom and glory.

^13 Indeed, that is why we also thank God unceasingly, because when you received God’s word, which you heard from us, you accepted it not as the word of men but, just as it truthfully is, as the word of God, which is also at work in you believers. ^14 For you, brothers, became imitators of the congregations of God in union with Christ Jesus that are in Ju·deʹa, because you suffered at the hands of your own countrymen the same things that they also are suffering at the hands of the Jews, ^15 who even killed the Lord Jesus and the prophets and persecuted us. Furthermore, they are not pleasing God, but are against the interests of all men, ^16 as they try to prevent us from speaking to people of the nations so that these might be saved. In this way they always fill up the measure of their sins. But his wrath has at last come upon them.

^17 But when we were separated from[*] you, brothers, for just a short time (in person, not in our hearts), because of our strong desire, we made every effort to see you in person.[*] ^18 For this reason we wanted to come to you, yes I, Paul, tried not just once but twice; yet Satan cut across our path. ^19 For what is our hope or joy or crown of exultation before our Lord Jesus at his presence? Is it not in fact you? ^20 You certainly are our glory and joy.

^ 1 Thess. 2:2 Or “courage.”

^ 1 Thess. 2:2 Or possibly, “amid much struggling.”

^ 1 Thess. 2:7 Or “cherishes.”

^ 1 Thess. 2:8 Lit., “well-pleased.”

^ 1 Thess. 2:8 Or “souls.”

^ 1 Thess. 2:17 Or “bereaved of.”

^ 1 Thess. 2:17 Lit., “to see your face.”

2 Thessalonians  1 : 1 - 12

THE SECOND TO THE THESSALONIANS

1 Paul, Sil·vaʹnus,[*] and Timothy, to the congregation of the Thes·sa·loʹni·ans in union with God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ:

^2 May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

^3 We are obligated always to give thanks to God for you, brothers. This is fitting, because your faith is growing exceedingly and the love of each and every one of you is increasing toward one another. ^4 As a result we ourselves take pride in you among the congregations of God because of your endurance and faith in all your persecutions and the hardships[*] that you are suffering.[*] ^5 This is a proof of the righteous judgment of God, leading to your being counted worthy of the Kingdom of God, for which you are indeed suffering.

^6 This takes into account that it is righteous on God’s part to repay tribulation to those who make tribulation for you. ^7 But you who suffer tribulation will be given relief along with us at the revelation of the Lord Jesus from heaven with his powerful angels ^8 in a flaming fire, as he brings vengeance on those who do not know God and those who do not obey the good news about our Lord Jesus. ^9 These very ones will undergo the judicial punishment of everlasting destruction from before the Lord and from the glory of his strength, ^10 at the time when he comes to be glorified in connection with his holy ones and to be regarded in that day with wonder among all those who exercised faith, because the witness we gave met with faith among you.

^11 To that very end we always pray for you, that our God may count you worthy of his calling and with his power perform completely all the good that he pleases and every work of faith. ^12 This is so that the name of our Lord Jesus may be glorified in you and you in union with him, according to the undeserved kindness of our God and of the Lord Jesus Christ.

^ 2 Thess. 1:1 Also called Silas.

^ 2 Thess. 1:4 Or “tribulations.”

^ 2 Thess. 1:4 Or “enduring.”

2 Thessalonians  3 : 1 - 18

3 Finally, brothers, carry on prayer for us, that the word of Jehovah[*] may keep spreading rapidly and being glorified, just as it is with you, ^2 and that we may be rescued from harmful and wicked men, for faith is not a possession of all people. ^3 But the Lord is faithful, and he will strengthen you and protect you from the wicked one. ^4 Moreover, we have confidence in the Lord regarding you, that you are carrying out and will go on carrying out our instructions. ^5 May the Lord continue to guide your hearts successfully to the love of God and to the endurance for the Christ.

^6 Now we are giving you instructions, brothers, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, to withdraw from every brother who is walking disorderly and not according to the tradition[*] that you[*] received from us. ^7 For you yourselves know how you should imitate us, because we did not behave in a disorderly way among you, ^8 nor did we eat anyone’s food free.[*] On the contrary, by labor and toil we were working night and day so as not to impose an expensive burden on any one of you. ^9 Not that we do not have authority, but we wanted to offer ourselves as an example for you to imitate. ^10 In fact, when we were with you, we used to give you this order: “If anyone does not want to work, neither let him eat.” ^11 For we hear that some are walking disorderly among you, not working at all, but meddling with what does not concern them. ^12 To such people we give the order and exhortation in the Lord Jesus Christ that they should work quietly and eat food they themselves earn.

^13 For your part, brothers, do not give up in doing good. ^14 But if anyone is not obedient to our word through this letter, keep this one marked and stop associating with him, so that he may become ashamed. ^15 And yet do not consider him an enemy, but continue admonishing him as a brother.

^16 Now may the Lord of peace himself give you peace constantly in every way. May the Lord be with all of you.

^17 Here is my greeting, Paul’s, in my own hand, which is a sign in every letter; this is the way I write.

^18 The undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus Christ be with all of you.

^ 2 Thess. 3:1 See App. A5.

^ 2 Thess. 3:6 Or “instruction.”

^ 2 Thess. 3:6 Or possibly, “they.”

^ 2 Thess. 3:8 Or “without paying.”

1 Timothy  5 : 1 - 25

5 Do not severely criticize an older man. On the contrary, appeal to him as a father, to younger men as brothers, ^2 to older women as mothers, to younger women as sisters, with all chasteness.

^3 Give consideration to[*] widows who are truly widows.[*] ^4 But if any widow has children or grandchildren, let these learn first to practice godly devotion in their own household and to repay their parents and grandparents what is due them, for this is acceptable in God’s sight. ^5 Now the woman who is truly a widow and left destitute has put her hope in God and continues in supplications and prayers night and day. ^6 But the one who gives herself to sensual gratification is dead though she is living. ^7 So keep on giving these instructions,[*] so that they may be irreprehensible. ^8 Certainly if anyone does not provide for those who are his own, and especially for those who are members of his household, he has disowned the faith and is worse than a person without faith.

^9 A widow is to be put on the list if she is not less than 60 years old, was the wife of one husband, ^10 having a reputation for fine works, if she raised children, if she practiced hospitality, if she washed the feet of holy ones, if she assisted the afflicted, if she devoted herself to every good work.

^11 On the other hand, do not put younger widows on the list, for when their sexual desires come between them and the Christ, they want to marry. ^12 And they will incur judgment because they have abandoned their first expression of faith.[*] ^13 At the same time they also learn to be unoccupied, going around from one house to another; yes, not only unoccupied but also gossipers and meddlers in other people’s affairs, talking about things they should not. ^14 Therefore, I desire the younger widows to marry, to bear children, to manage a household, to give no opportunity to the opposer to criticize. ^15 In fact, some have already been turned aside to follow Satan. ^16 If any believing woman has relatives who are widows, let her assist them so that the congregation is not burdened. Then it can assist those who are truly widows.[*]

^17 Let the elders who preside in a fine way be considered worthy of double honor, especially those who work hard in speaking and teaching. ^18 For the scripture says, “You must not muzzle a bull when it is threshing out the grain,” also, “The worker is worthy of his wages.” ^19 Do not accept an accusation against an older man[*] except on the evidence of two or three witnesses. ^20 Reprove before all onlookers those who practice sin, as a warning to the rest.[*] ^21 I solemnly charge you before God and Christ Jesus and the chosen angels to observe these instructions without any prejudice or partiality.

^22 Never lay your hands hastily on any man;[*] neither become a sharer in the sins of others; keep yourself chaste.

^23 Do not drink water any longer,[*] but take a little wine for the sake of your stomach and your frequent cases of sickness.

^24 The sins of some men are publicly known, leading directly to judgment, but those of other men become evident later. ^25 In the same way also, the fine works are publicly known and those that are otherwise cannot be kept hidden.

^ 1 Tim. 5:3 Lit., “Honor.”

^ 1 Tim. 5:3 Or “widows who are truly in need”; that is, with no one to support them.

^ 1 Tim. 5:7 Or “commands.”

^ 1 Tim. 5:12 Or “their previous promise.”

^ 1 Tim. 5:16 Or “widows who are truly in need”; that is, with no one to support them.

^ 1 Tim. 5:19 Or “an elder.”

^ 1 Tim. 5:20 Lit., “that the rest may have fear.”

^ 1 Tim. 5:22 That is, do not appoint any man hastily.

^ 1 Tim. 5:23 Or “Stop drinking just water.”

2 Timothy  1 : 1 - 18

THE SECOND TO TIMOTHY

1 Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by God’s will according to the promise of the life that is through Christ Jesus, ^2 to Timothy, a beloved child:

May you have undeserved kindness, mercy, and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.

^3 I am grateful to God, to whom I am rendering sacred service as my forefathers did, and with a clean conscience, never ceasing to remember you in my supplications night and day. ^4 As I remember your tears, I am longing to see you, so that I may get filled with joy. ^5 For I recall your unhypocritical faith, which dwelled first in your grandmother Loʹis and your mother Euʹnice, but which I am confident is also in you.

^6 For this reason I remind you to stir up like a fire the gift of God that is in you through the laying of my hands on you. ^7 For God did not give us a spirit of cowardice, but one of power and of love and of soundness of mind. ^8 So do not become ashamed either of the witness about our Lord or of me, a prisoner for his sake, but take your part in suffering adversity for the good news by relying on the power of God. ^9 He saved us and called us with a holy calling, not because of our works, but because of his own purpose and undeserved kindness. This was given to us in connection with Christ Jesus before times long ago, ^10 but now it has been made clearly evident through the manifestation of our Savior, Christ Jesus, who has abolished death and has shed light on life and incorruption through the good news, ^11 for which I was appointed a preacher and an apostle and a teacher.

^12 This is why I am also suffering these things, but I am not ashamed. For I know the One whom I have believed, and I am confident that he is able to guard what I have laid up in trust with him until that day. ^13 Keep holding to the standard[*] of wholesome[*] words that you heard from me with the faith and love that result from union with Christ Jesus. ^14 Guard this fine trust by means of the holy spirit, which is dwelling in us.

^15 You know this, that all the men in the province of Asia have turned away from me, including Phy·gelʹus and Her·mogʹe·nes. ^16 May the Lord grant mercy to the household of On·e·siphʹo·rus, for he often refreshed me, and he did not become ashamed of my prison chains. ^17 On the contrary, when he was in Rome, he diligently looked for me and found me. ^18 May the Lord grant him to find mercy from Jehovah[*] in that day. And you well know all the services he rendered in Ephʹe·sus.

^ 2 Tim. 1:13 Or “outline.”

^ 2 Tim. 1:13 Or “healthful; beneficial.”

^ 2 Tim. 1:18 See App. A5.

2 Timothy  3 : 1 - 17

3 But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here. ^2 For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal, ^3 having no natural affection, not open to any agreement, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, without love of goodness, ^4 betrayers, headstrong, puffed up with pride, lovers of pleasures rather than lovers of God, ^5 having an appearance of godliness but proving false to its power; and from these turn away. ^6 From among these arise men who slyly work their way into households and captivate weak women loaded down with sins, led by various desires, ^7 always learning and yet never able to come to an accurate knowledge of truth.

^8 Now in the way that Janʹnes and Jamʹbres opposed Moses, so these also go on opposing the truth. Such men are completely corrupted in mind, disapproved as regards the faith. ^9 Nevertheless, they will make no further progress, for their folly[*] will be very plain to all, as it was with those two men. ^10 But you have closely followed my teaching, my course of life, my purpose, my faith, my patience, my love, my endurance, ^11 the persecutions and sufferings such as I experienced in Antioch, in I·coʹni·um, in Lysʹtra. I endured these persecutions, and the Lord rescued me from them all. ^12 In fact, all those desiring to live with godly devotion in association with Christ Jesus will also be persecuted. ^13 But wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.

^14 You, however, continue in the things that you learned and were persuaded to believe, knowing from whom you learned them ^15 and that from infancy you have known the holy writings, which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus. ^16 All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,[*] for disciplining in righteousness, ^17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

^ 2 Tim. 3:9 Or “foolishness.”

^ 2 Tim. 3:16 Or “correcting.”

Titus  3 : 1 - 15

3 Continue reminding them to be in subjection and to be obedient to governments and authorities, to be ready for every good work, ^2 to speak injuriously of no one, not to be quarrelsome, but to be reasonable, displaying all mildness toward all men. ^3 For we too were once senseless, disobedient, led astray, being slaves to various desires and pleasures, carrying on in badness and envy, detestable, hating one another.

^4 However, when the kindness of our Savior, God, and his love for mankind were manifested ^5 (not because of any righteous works we had done, but because of his own mercy), he saved us by means of the bath that brought us to life and by making us new by holy spirit. ^6 He poured this spirit out richly[*] on us through Jesus Christ our Savior, ^7 so that after being declared righteous through the undeserved kindness of that one, we might become heirs according to a hope of everlasting life.

^8 These words are trustworthy, and I want you to keep stressing these matters, so that those who have believed God may keep their minds focused on maintaining fine works. These things are fine and beneficial to men.

^9 But have nothing to do with foolish arguments and genealogies and disputes and fights over the Law, for they are unprofitable and futile. ^10 As for a man who promotes a sect, reject him after a first and a second admonition,[*] ^11 knowing that such a man has deviated from the way and is sinning and is self-condemned.

^12 When I send Arʹte·mas or Tychʹi·cus to you, do your utmost to come to me at Ni·copʹo·lis, for that is where I have decided to spend the winter. ^13 Carefully supply Zeʹnas, who is versed in the Law, and A·polʹlos so that they may lack nothing for their trip. ^14 But let our people also learn to maintain fine works so as to help in cases of urgent need, so that they may not be unproductive.[*]

^15 All those with me send you their greetings. Give my greetings to those who have affection for us in the faith.

May the undeserved kindness be with all of you.

^ Titus 3:6 Or “generously.”

^ Titus 3:10 Or “warning.”

^ Titus 3:14 Lit., “unfruitful.”

Hebrews  2 : 1 - 18

2 That is why it is necessary for us to pay more than the usual attention to the things we have heard, so that we never drift away. ^2 For if the word spoken through angels proved to be sure, and every transgression and disobedient act received a punishment in harmony with justice, ^3 how will we escape if we have neglected so great a salvation? For it began to be spoken through our Lord and was verified for us by those who heard him, ^4 while God joined in bearing witness with signs and wonders[*] and various powerful works and with the holy spirit distributed according to his will.

^5 For it is not to angels that he has subjected the inhabited earth to come, about which we are speaking. ^6 But in one place a certain witness said: “What is man that you keep him in mind, or a son of man that you take care of him? ^7 You made him a little lower than angels; you crowned him with glory and honor, and appointed him over the works of your hands. ^8 All things you subjected under his feet.” By subjecting all things to him, God left nothing that is not subject to him. Now, though, we do not yet see all things in subjection to him. ^9 But we do see Jesus, who was made a little lower than angels, now crowned with glory and honor for having suffered death, so that by God’s undeserved kindness he might taste death for everyone.

^10 For it was fitting that the one for whom and through whom all things exist, in bringing many sons to glory, should make the Chief Agent of their salvation perfect through sufferings. ^11 For both the one who is sanctifying and those who are being sanctified all stem from one, and for this reason he is not ashamed to call them brothers, ^12 as he says: “I will declare your name to my brothers; in the midst of the congregation I will praise you with song.” ^13 And again: “I will put my trust in him.” And again: “Look! I and the young children, whom Jehovah[*] gave me.”

^14 Therefore, since the “young children” are sharers of blood and flesh, he also similarly shared in the same things, so that through his death he might bring to nothing the one having the means to cause death, that is, the Devil, ^15 and that he might set free[*] all those who were held in slavery all their lives by their fear of death. ^16 For it is not really angels he is assisting, but he is assisting Abraham’s offspring.[*] ^17 Consequently, he had to become like his “brothers” in all respects, so that he could become a merciful and faithful high priest in things relating to God, in order to offer a propitiatory sacrifice[*] for the sins of the people. ^18 Since he himself has suffered when being put to the test, he is able to come to the aid of those who are being put to the test.

^ Heb. 2:4 Or “portents.”

^ Heb. 2:13 See App. A5.

^ Heb. 2:15 Or “emancipate.”

^ Heb. 2:16 Lit., “seed.”

^ Heb. 2:17 Or “to offer an atoning sacrifice; to make atonement.”

Hebrews  4 : 1 - 16

4 Therefore, since a promise of entering into his rest remains, let us be on guard[*] for fear someone among you seems to fall short of it. ^2 For we have also had the good news declared to us, just as they had; but the word that they heard did not benefit them, because they were not united by faith with those who listened. ^3 For we who have exercised faith do enter into the rest, just as he has said: “So I swore in my anger, ‘They will not enter into my rest,’” although his works were finished from the founding of the world. ^4 For in one place he has said of the seventh day as follows: “And God rested on the seventh day from all his works,” ^5 and here again he says: “They will not enter into my rest.”

^6 Therefore, since it remains for some to enter into it, and those to whom the good news was first declared did not enter in because of disobedience, ^7 he again marks off a certain day by saying long afterward in David’s psalm, “Today”; just as it has been said above, “Today if you listen to his voice, do not harden your hearts.” ^8 For if Joshua had led them into a place of rest, God would not afterward have spoken of another day. ^9 So there remains a sabbath-rest for the people of God. ^10 For the man who has entered into God’s rest has also rested from his own works, just as God did from his own.

^11 Let us therefore do our utmost to enter into that rest, so that no one may fall into the same pattern of disobedience. ^12 For the word of God is alive and exerts power and is sharper than any two-edged sword and pierces even to the dividing of soul[*] and spirit,[*] and of joints from the marrow, and is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart. ^13 And there is not a creation that is hidden from his sight, but all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes of the one to whom we must give an account.

^14 Therefore, since we have a great high priest who has passed through the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold on to our public declaration of him. ^15 For we do not have a high priest who cannot sympathize with our weaknesses, but we have one who has been tested in all respects as we have, but without sin. ^16 Let us, then, approach the throne of undeserved kindness with freeness of speech, so that we may receive mercy and find undeserved kindness to help us at the right time.

^ Heb. 4:1 Lit., “be in fear.”

^ Heb. 4:12 See Glossary.

^ Heb. 4:12 See Glossary.

Hebrews  6 : 1 - 20

6 Therefore, now that we have moved beyond the primary doctrine about the Christ, let us press on to maturity, not laying a foundation again, namely, repentance from dead works and faith in God, ^2 the teaching on baptisms and the laying on of the hands, the resurrection of the dead and everlasting judgment. ^3 And this we will do, if God indeed permits.

^4 For as regards those who were once enlightened and who have tasted the heavenly free gift and who have become partakers of holy spirit ^5 and who have tasted the fine word of God and powers of the coming system of things,[*] ^6 but have fallen away, it is impossible to revive them again to repentance, because they nail the Son of God to the stake again for themselves and expose him to public shame. ^7 For the ground receives a blessing from God when it drinks in the rain that frequently falls on it and then produces vegetation useful to those for whom it is cultivated. ^8 But if it produces thorns and thistles, it is rejected and is near to being cursed, and in the end it will be burned.

^9 But in your case, beloved ones, we are convinced of better things, things related to salvation, even though we are speaking in this way. ^10 For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones. ^11 But we desire each one of you to show the same industriousness so as to have the full assurance of the hope down to the end, ^12 so that you may not become sluggish, but be imitators of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises.

^13 For when God made his promise to Abraham, since he could not swear by anyone greater, he swore by himself, ^14 saying: “I will surely bless you and I will surely multiply you.” ^15 So after Abraham had shown patience, he obtained this promise. ^16 For men swear by someone greater, and their oath is the end of every dispute, since it is a legal guarantee to them. ^17 In this same way, when God decided to demonstrate more clearly to the heirs of the promise the unchangeableness of his purpose,[*] he guaranteed it[*] with an oath, ^18 in order that through two unchangeable things in which it is impossible for God to lie, we who have fled to the refuge may have strong encouragement to take firm hold of the hope set before us. ^19 We have this hope as an anchor for the soul,[*] both sure and firm, and it enters in within the curtain, ^20 where a forerunner has entered in our behalf, Jesus, who has become a high priest in the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek forever.

^ Heb. 6:5 Or “the coming age.” See Glossary.

^ Heb. 6:17 Or “counsel.”

^ Heb. 6:17 Or “stepped in.” Lit., “mediated.”

^ Heb. 6:19 Or “for our lives.”

Hebrews  7 : 1 - 28

7 For this Mel·chizʹe·dek, king of Saʹlem, priest of the Most High God, met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings and blessed him, ^2 and Abraham gave[*] him a tenth of everything. First, his name is translated “King of Righteousness,” and then also king of Saʹlem, that is, “King of Peace.” ^3 In being fatherless, motherless, without genealogy, having neither a beginning of days nor an end of life, but being made like the Son of God, he remains a priest for all time.[*]

^4 See how great this man was to whom Abraham, the family head,[*] gave a tenth out of the best spoils. ^5 True, according to the Law, those of the sons of Leʹvi who receive their priestly office have a commandment to collect tithes from the people, that is, from their brothers, even though these are descendants[*] of Abraham. ^6 But this man who did not trace his genealogy from them took tithes from Abraham and blessed the one who had the promises. ^7 Now it is undeniable that the lesser one is blessed by the greater. ^8 And in the one case, it is men who are dying who receive tithes, but in the other case, it is someone of whom witness is given that he lives. ^9 And it could be said that even Leʹvi, who receives tithes, has paid tithes through Abraham, ^10 for he was still a future descendant[*] of his forefather when Mel·chizʹe·dek met him.

^11 If, then, perfection was attainable through the Levitical priesthood (for it was a feature of the Law that was given to the people), what further need would there be for another priest to arise who is said to be in the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek and not in the manner of Aaron? ^12 For since the priesthood is being changed, it becomes necessary to change the Law as well. ^13 For the man about whom these things are said came from another tribe, from which no one has officiated at the altar. ^14 For it is clear that our Lord has descended from Judah, yet Moses said nothing about priests coming from that tribe.

^15 And this becomes even clearer when another priest arises who is like Mel·chizʹe·dek, ^16 who has become such, not by the legal requirement that depends on fleshly descent, but by the power of an indestructible life. ^17 For it is said in witness of him: “You are a priest forever in the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek.”

^18 So, then, the former commandment is set aside because it is weak and ineffective. ^19 For the Law made nothing perfect, but the introduction of a better hope did, through which we are drawing near to God. ^20 Also, inasmuch as this was not done without an oath being sworn ^21 (for, indeed, there are men who have become priests without a sworn oath, but this one has become so through an oath sworn respecting him by the One who said: “Jehovah[*] has sworn, and he will not change his mind,[*] ‘You are a priest forever’”), ^22 Jesus has accordingly become the guarantee[*] of a better covenant. ^23 Furthermore, many had to become priests in succession because death prevented them from continuing as such, ^24 but because he continues alive forever, his priesthood has no successors. ^25 So he is able also to save completely those who are approaching God through him, because he is always alive to plead for them.

^26 For it is fitting for us to have such a high priest who is loyal, innocent, undefiled, separated from the sinners, and exalted above the heavens. ^27 Unlike those high priests, he does not need to offer up sacrifices daily, first for his own sins and then for those of the people, because he did this once for all time when he offered himself up. ^28 For the Law appoints as high priests men who have weaknesses, but the word of the oath sworn after the Law appoints a Son, who has been made perfect forever.

^ Heb. 7:2 Lit., “apportioned.”

^ Heb. 7:3 Or “perpetually.”

^ Heb. 7:4 Or “the patriarch.”

^ Heb. 7:5 Lit., “have come out of the loins.”

^ Heb. 7:10 Lit., “in the loins.”

^ Heb. 7:21 See App. A5.

^ Heb. 7:21 Or “will feel no regret.”

^ Heb. 7:22 Or “the one given in pledge.”

Hebrews  9 : 1 - 28

9 For its part, the former covenant used to have legal requirements for sacred service and its holy place on earth. ^2 For a first tent compartment was constructed, in which were the lampstand and the table and the display of the loaves of presentation;[*] and it is called the Holy Place. ^3 But behind the second curtain was the tent compartment called the Most Holy. ^4 This had a golden censer and the ark of the covenant completely overlaid with gold, in which were the golden jar containing the manna and Aaron’s rod that budded and the tablets of the covenant; ^5 and above it were the glorious cherubs overshadowing the propitiatory cover.[*] But now is not the time to speak of these things in detail.

^6 After these things were constructed this way, the priests enter the first tent compartment regularly to perform the sacred services; ^7 but the high priest enters alone into the second compartment once a year, not without blood, which he offers for himself and for the sins that the people committed in ignorance. ^8 Thus the holy spirit makes it clear that the way into the holy place had not yet been revealed while the first tent was standing. ^9 This tent is an illustration for the present time, and according to this arrangement, both gifts and sacrifices are offered. However, these are not able to make the conscience of the man doing sacred service perfect. ^10 They have to do only with foods and drinks and various ceremonial washings.[*] They were legal requirements concerning the body and were imposed until the appointed time to set things straight.

^11 However, when Christ came as a high priest of the good things that have already taken place, he passed through the greater and more perfect tent not made with hands, that is, not of this creation. ^12 He entered into the holy place, not with the blood of goats and of young bulls, but with his own blood, once for all time, and obtained an everlasting deliverance[*] for us. ^13 For if the blood of goats and of bulls and the ashes of a heifer[*] sprinkled on those who have been defiled sanctifies for the cleansing of the flesh, ^14 how much more will the blood of the Christ, who through an everlasting spirit offered himself without blemish to God, cleanse our consciences from dead works so that we may render sacred service to the living God?

^15 That is why he is a mediator of a new covenant, in order that because a death has occurred for their release by ransom from the transgressions under the former covenant, those who have been called may receive the promise of the everlasting inheritance. ^16 For where there is a covenant, the death of the human covenanter needs to be established, ^17 because a covenant is valid at death, since it is not in force as long as the human covenanter is living. ^18 Consequently, neither was the former covenant put into effect[*] without blood. ^19 For when Moses had spoken every commandment of the Law to all the people, he took the blood of the young bulls and of the goats, with water, scarlet wool, and hyssop, and sprinkled the book[*] and all the people, ^20 saying: “This is the blood of the covenant that God has commanded you to keep.” ^21 He likewise sprinkled the tent and all the vessels of the holy service[*] with the blood. ^22 Yes, according to the Law nearly all things are cleansed with blood, and unless blood is poured out no forgiveness takes place.

^23 Therefore, it was necessary for the typical representations of the things in the heavens to be cleansed by these means, but the heavenly things require far better sacrifices. ^24 For Christ did not enter into a holy place made with hands, which is a copy of the reality, but into heaven itself, so that he now appears before[*] God on our behalf. ^25 This was not done to offer himself often, as when the high priest enters into the holy place from year to year with blood that is not his own. ^26 Otherwise, he would have to suffer often from the founding of the world. But now he has manifested himself once for all time at the conclusion of the systems of things[*] to do away with sin through the sacrifice of himself. ^27 And just as it is reserved for men to die once for all time, but after this to receive a judgment, ^28 so also the Christ was offered once for all time to bear the sins of many; and the second time that he appears it will be apart from sin,[*] and he will be seen by those earnestly looking for him for their salvation.

^ Heb. 9:2 Or “the showbread.”

^ Heb. 9:5 Or “the place of atonement.”

^ Heb. 9:10 Lit., “various baptisms.”

^ Heb. 9:12 Lit., “ransoming; redemption.”

^ Heb. 9:13 Or “young cow.”

^ Heb. 9:18 Lit., “inaugurated.”

^ Heb. 9:19 Or “scroll.”

^ Heb. 9:21 Or “the public service.”

^ Heb. 9:24 Lit., “before the face of.”

^ Heb. 9:26 Or “the ages.” See Glossary.

^ Heb. 9:28 Or “it will not be to deal with sin.”

Hebrews  11 : 1 - 40

11 Faith is the assured expectation of what is hoped for, the evident demonstration[*] of realities that are not seen. ^2 For by means of it, the men of ancient times[*] had witness borne to them.

^3 By faith we perceive that the systems of things[*] were put in order by God’s word, so that what is seen has come into existence from things that are not visible.

^4 By faith Abel offered God a sacrifice of greater worth than that of Cain, and through that faith he received the witness that he was righteous, for God approved[*] his gifts, and although he died, he still speaks through his faith.

^5 By faith Eʹnoch was transferred so as not to see death, and he was nowhere to be found because God had transferred him; for before he was transferred he received the witness that he had pleased God well. ^6 Moreover, without faith it is impossible to please God well, for whoever approaches God must believe that he is[*] and that he becomes the rewarder of those earnestly seeking him.

^7 By faith Noah, after receiving divine warning of things not yet seen, showed godly fear and constructed an ark for the saving of his household; and through this faith he condemned the world, and he became an heir of the righteousness that results from faith.

^8 By faith Abraham, when he was called, obeyed by going out to a place he was to receive as an inheritance; he went out, although not knowing where he was going. ^9 By faith he lived as a foreigner in the land of the promise as in a foreign land, living in tents with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the very same promise. ^10 For he was awaiting the city having real foundations, whose designer[*] and builder is God.

^11 By faith also Sarah received power to conceive offspring,[*] even when she was past the age, since she considered Him faithful[*] who made the promise. ^12 For this reason, from one man who was as good as dead, there were born children, as many as the stars of heaven in number and as innumerable as the sands by the seaside.

^13 In faith all of these died, although they did not receive the fulfillment of the promises; but they saw them from a distance and welcomed them and publicly declared that they were strangers and temporary residents in the land. ^14 For those who speak in such a way make it evident that they are earnestly seeking a place of their own. ^15 And yet, if they had kept remembering the place from which they had departed, they would have had opportunity to return. ^16 But now they are reaching out for a better place, that is, one belonging to heaven. Therefore, God is not ashamed of them, to be called on as their God, for he has prepared a city for them.

^17 By faith Abraham, when he was tested, as good as offered up Isaac—the man who had gladly received the promises attempted to offer up his only-begotten son— ^18 although it had been said to him: “What will be called your offspring[*] will be through Isaac.” ^19 But he reasoned that God was able to raise him up even from the dead, and he did receive him from there in an illustrative way.

^20 By faith also Isaac blessed Jacob and Eʹsau concerning things to come.

^21 By faith Jacob, when about to die, blessed each of the sons of Joseph and worshipped while leaning on the top of his staff.

^22 By faith Joseph, nearing his end, spoke of the exodus of the sons of Israel, and he gave instructions[*] concerning his bones.[*]

^23 By faith Moses was hid by his parents for three months after his birth, because they saw that the young child was beautiful and they did not fear the order of the king. ^24 By faith Moses, when grown up, refused to be called the son of Pharʹaoh’s daughter, ^25 choosing to be mistreated with the people of God rather than to have the temporary enjoyment of sin, ^26 because he considered the reproach of the Christ to be riches greater than the treasures of Egypt, for he looked intently toward the payment of the reward. ^27 By faith he left Egypt, but not fearing the anger of the king, for he continued steadfast as seeing the One who is invisible. ^28 By faith he observed the Passover and the splashing of the blood, so that the destroyer might not harm[*] their firstborn.

^29 By faith they passed through the Red Sea as on dry land, but when the Egyptians attempted it, they were swallowed up.

^30 By faith the walls of Jerʹi·cho fell down after the people had marched around them for seven days. ^31 By faith Raʹhab the prostitute did not perish with those who acted disobediently, because she received the spies in a peaceable way.

^32 And what more will I say? For time will fail me if I go on to relate about Gidʹe·on, Baʹrak, Samson, Jephʹthah, David, as well as Samuel and the other prophets. ^33 Through faith they defeated kingdoms, brought about righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions, ^34 quenched the force of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, from a weak state were made powerful, became mighty in war, routed invading armies. ^35 Women received their dead by resurrection, but other men were tortured because they would not accept release by some ransom, in order that they might attain a better resurrection. ^36 Yes, others received their trial by mockings and scourgings, indeed, more than that, by chains and prisons. ^37 They were stoned, they were tried, they were sawn in two,[*] they were slaughtered by the sword, they went about in sheepskins, in goatskins, while they were in need, in tribulation, mistreated; ^38 and the world was not worthy of them. They wandered about in deserts and mountains and caves and dens of the earth.

^39 And yet all of these, although they received a favorable witness because of their faith, did not obtain the fulfillment of the promise, ^40 because God had foreseen something better for us, so that they might not be made perfect apart from us.

^ Heb. 11:1 Or “convincing evidence.”

^ Heb. 11:2 Or “our ancestors.”

^ Heb. 11:3 Or “the ages.” See Glossary.

^ Heb. 11:4 Or “bore witness by acknowledging.”

^ Heb. 11:6 Or “exists.”

^ Heb. 11:10 Or “architect.”

^ Heb. 11:11 Lit., “seed.”

^ Heb. 11:11 Or “trustworthy.”

^ Heb. 11:18 Lit., “seed.”

^ Heb. 11:22 Or “a command.”

^ Heb. 11:22 Or “burial.”

^ Heb. 11:28 Lit., “touch.”

^ Heb. 11:37 Or “sawn apart.”

James  2 : 1 - 26

2 My brothers, you are not holding to the faith of our glorious Lord Jesus Christ while showing favoritism, are you? ^2 For if a man with gold rings on his fingers and in splendid clothing comes into your meeting, but a poor man in filthy clothing also enters, ^3 do you look with favor on the one wearing the splendid clothing and say, “You take this seat here in a fine place,” and do you say to the poor one, “You keep standing” or, “Take that seat there under my footstool”? ^4 If so, do you not have class distinctions among yourselves, and have you not become judges rendering wicked decisions?

^5 Listen, my beloved brothers. Did not God choose those who are poor from the world’s standpoint to be rich in faith and heirs of the Kingdom, which he promised to those who love him? ^6 But you have dishonored the poor. Is it not the rich who oppress you and drag you before law courts? ^7 Do they not blaspheme the fine name by which you were called? ^8 If, now, you carry out the royal[*] law according to the scripture, “You must love your neighbor as yourself,” you are doing quite well. ^9 But if you continue showing favoritism, you are committing sin, and you are convicted[*] by the law as transgressors.

^10 For if anyone obeys all the Law but makes a false step in one point, he has become an offender against all of it. ^11 For the one who said, “You must not commit adultery,” also said, “You must not murder.” If, now, you do not commit adultery but you do murder, you have become a transgressor of law. ^12 Keep on speaking and behaving in such a way as those do who are going to be judged by the law of a free people.[*] ^13 For the one who does not practice mercy will have his judgment without mercy. Mercy triumphs over judgment.

^14 Of what benefit is it, my brothers, if someone says he has faith but he does not have works? That faith cannot save him, can it? ^15 If any brothers or sisters are lacking clothing[*] and enough food for the day, ^16 yet one of you says to them, “Go in peace; keep warm and well fed,” but you do not give them what they need for their body, of what benefit is it? ^17 So, too, faith by itself, without works, is dead.

^18 Nevertheless, someone will say: “You have faith, and I have works. Show me your faith without the works, and I will show you my faith by my works.” ^19 You believe that there is one God, do you? You are doing quite well. And yet the demons believe and shudder. ^20 But do you care to know, O empty man, that faith without works is useless? ^21 Was not Abraham our father declared righteous by works after he offered up Isaac his son on the altar? ^22 You see that his faith was active along with his works and his faith was perfected by his works, ^23 and the scripture was fulfilled that says: “Abraham put faith in Jehovah,[*] and it was counted to him as righteousness,” and he came to be called Jehovah’s[*] friend.

^24 You see that a man is to be declared righteous by works and not by faith alone. ^25 In the same manner, was not Raʹhab the prostitute also declared righteous by works after she received the messengers hospitably and sent them out by another way? ^26 Indeed, just as the body without spirit[*] is dead, so also faith without works is dead.

^ Jas. 2:8 Or “kingly.”

^ Jas. 2:9 Or “reproved.”

^ Jas. 2:12 Lit., “law of freedom.”

^ Jas. 2:15 Lit., “are naked.”

^ Jas. 2:23 See App. A5.

^ Jas. 2:23 See App. A5.

^ Jas. 2:26 Or “breath.”

James  4 : 1 - 17

4 What is the source of the wars and fights among you? Do they not originate from your fleshly desires that carry on a conflict within you?[*] ^2 You desire, and yet you do not have. You go on murdering and coveting, and yet you are not able to obtain. You go on fighting and waging war. You do not have because of your not asking. ^3 When you do ask, you do not receive because you are asking for a wrong purpose, so that you may spend it on your fleshly desires.

^4 Adulteresses,[*] do you not know that friendship with the world is enmity with God? Whoever, therefore, wants to be a friend of the world is making himself an enemy of God. ^5 Or do you think that for no reason the scripture says: “The spirit that has taken up residence within us keeps enviously longing”? ^6 However, the undeserved kindness that He gives is greater. So it says: “God opposes the haughty ones, but he gives undeserved kindness to the humble ones.”

^7 Therefore, subject yourselves to God; but oppose the Devil, and he will flee from you. ^8 Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones. ^9 Give way to misery and mourn and weep. Let your laughter be turned into mourning, and your joy into despair. ^10 Humble yourselves in the eyes of Jehovah,[*] and he will exalt you.

^11 Stop speaking against one another, brothers. Whoever speaks against a brother or judges his brother speaks against law and judges law. Now if you judge law, you are not a doer of law but a judge. ^12 There is only one who is Lawgiver and Judge, the one who is able to save and to destroy. But you, who are you to be judging your neighbor?

^13 Come, now, you who say: “Today or tomorrow we will travel to this city and will spend a year there, and we will do business and make some profit,” ^14 whereas you do not know what your life will be like tomorrow. For you are a mist that appears for a little while and then disappears. ^15 Instead, you should say: “If Jehovah[*] wills, we will live and do this or that.” ^16 But now you take pride in your arrogant boasting. All such boasting is wicked. ^17 Therefore, if someone knows how to do what is right and yet does not do it, it is a sin for him.

^ Jas. 4:1 Lit., “in your members.”

^ Jas. 4:4 Or “You unfaithful ones.”

^ Jas. 4:10 See App. A5.

^ Jas. 4:15 See App. A5.

1 Peter  1 : 1 - 25

THE FIRST OF PETER

1 Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the temporary residents scattered about in Ponʹtus, Ga·laʹti·a, Cap·pa·doʹci·a, Asia, and Bi·thynʹi·a, to those chosen ^2 according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, with sanctification by the spirit, for the purpose of being obedient and sprinkled with the blood of Jesus Christ:

May undeserved kindness and peace be increased to you.

^3 Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, for according to his great mercy he gave us a new birth to a living hope through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead, ^4 to an incorruptible and undefiled and unfading inheritance. It is reserved in the heavens for you, ^5 who are being safeguarded by God’s power through faith for a salvation ready to be revealed in the last period of time. ^6 Because of this you are greatly rejoicing, though for a short time, if it must be, you have been distressed by various trials, ^7 in order that the tested quality of your faith, of much greater value than gold that perishes despite its being tested[*] by fire, may be found a cause for praise and glory and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ. ^8 Though you never saw him, you love him. Though you do not see him now, yet you exercise faith in him and are greatly rejoicing with an indescribable and glorious joy, ^9 as you attain the goal of your faith, your salvation.[*]

^10 Concerning this salvation, the prophets who prophesied about the undeserved kindness meant for you made a diligent inquiry and a careful search. ^11 They kept on investigating what particular time or what season the spirit within them was indicating concerning Christ as it testified beforehand about the sufferings meant for Christ and about the glory that would follow. ^12 It was revealed to them that they were ministering, not to themselves, but to you, regarding what has now been announced to you by those who declared the good news to you with holy spirit sent from heaven. Into these very things, angels are desiring to peer.

^13 So brace up your minds for activity; keep your senses completely; set your hope on the undeserved kindness that will be brought to you at the revelation of Jesus Christ. ^14 As obedient children, stop being molded by[*] the desires you formerly had in your ignorance, ^15 but like the Holy One who called you, become holy yourselves in all your conduct, ^16 for it is written: “You must be holy, because I am holy.”

^17 And if you are calling on the Father who judges impartially according to each one’s work, conduct yourselves with fear during the time of your temporary residence. ^18 For you know that it was not with corruptible things, with silver or gold, that you were set free[*] from your futile way of life handed down to you by your forefathers.[*] ^19 But it was with precious blood, like that of an unblemished and spotless lamb, that of Christ. ^20 True, he was foreknown before the founding of the world, but he was made manifest at the end of the times for your sake. ^21 Through him you are believers in God, the one who raised him up from the dead and gave him glory, so that your faith and hope might be in God.

^22 Now that you have purified yourselves[*] by your obedience to the truth with unhypocritical brotherly affection as the result, love one another intensely from the heart. ^23 For you have been given a new birth, not by corruptible, but by incorruptible seed,[*] through the word of the living and enduring God. ^24 For “all flesh is[*] like grass, and all its glory is like a blossom of the field; the grass withers, and the flower falls off, ^25 but the saying[*] of Jehovah[*] endures forever.” And this “saying”[*] is the good news that was declared to you.

^ 1 Pet. 1:7 Or “refined.”

^ 1 Pet. 1:9 Or “the salvation of your souls.”

^ 1 Pet. 1:14 Or “fashioned after.”

^ 1 Pet. 1:18 Lit., “you were ransomed; you were redeemed.”

^ 1 Pet. 1:18 Or “by tradition.”

^ 1 Pet. 1:22 Or “your souls.”

^ 1 Pet. 1:23 That is, seed capable of reproducing, or bearing fruit.

^ 1 Pet. 1:24 Or “all humans are.”

^ 1 Pet. 1:25 Or “word.”

^ 1 Pet. 1:25 See App. A5.

^ 1 Pet. 1:25 Or “word.”

1 Peter  3 : 1 - 22

3 In the same way, you wives, be in subjection to your husbands, so that if any are not obedient to the word, they may be won without a word through the conduct of their wives, ^2 because of having been eyewitnesses of your chaste conduct together with deep respect. ^3 Do not let your adornment be external—the braiding of hair and the wearing of gold ornaments or fine clothing— ^4 but let it be the secret person of the heart in the incorruptible adornment of the quiet and mild spirit, which is of great value in the eyes of God. ^5 For this is how the holy women of the past who hoped in God used to adorn themselves, subjecting themselves to their husbands, ^6 just as Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord. And you have become her children, provided you continue doing good and do not give in to fear.

^7 You husbands, in the same way, continue dwelling with them according to knowledge.[*] Assign them honor as to a weaker vessel, the feminine one, since they are also heirs with you of the undeserved favor of life, in order for your prayers not to be hindered.

^8 Finally, all of you have unity of mind,[*] fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility. ^9 Do not pay back injury for injury or insult for insult. Instead, repay with a blessing, for you were called to this course, so that you might inherit a blessing.

^10 For “whoever would love life and see good days must guard his tongue from bad and his lips from speaking deception. ^11 Let him turn away from what is bad and do what is good; let him seek peace and pursue it. ^12 For the eyes of Jehovah[*] are on the righteous, and his ears listen to their supplication, but the face of Jehovah[*] is against those doing bad things.”

^13 Indeed, who will harm you if you become zealous for what is good? ^14 But even if you should suffer for the sake of righteousness, you are happy. However, do not fear what they fear,[*] nor be disturbed. ^15 But sanctify the Christ as Lord in your hearts, always ready to make a defense before everyone who demands of you a reason for the hope you have, but doing so with a mild temper and deep respect.

^16 Maintain a good conscience, so that in whatever way you are spoken against, those who speak against you may be put to shame because of your good conduct as followers of Christ. ^17 For it is better to suffer because you are doing good, if it is God’s will to allow it, than because you are doing evil. ^18 For Christ died once for all time for sins, a righteous person for unrighteous ones, in order to lead you to God. He was put to death in the flesh but made alive in the spirit. ^19 And in this state he went and preached to the spirits in prison, ^20 who had formerly been disobedient when God was patiently waiting[*] in Noah’s day, while the ark was being constructed, in which a few people, that is, eight souls,[*] were carried safely through the water.

^21 Baptism, which corresponds to this, is also now saving you (not by the removing of the filth of the flesh, but by the request to God for a good conscience), through the resurrection of Jesus Christ. ^22 He is at God’s right hand, for he went to heaven, and angels and authorities and powers were made subject to him.

^ 1 Pet. 3:7 Or “showing them consideration; understanding them.”

^ 1 Pet. 3:8 Or “think in agreement.”

^ 1 Pet. 3:12 See App. A5.

^ 1 Pet. 3:12 See App. A5.

^ 1 Pet. 3:14 Or possibly, “do not fear their threats.”

^ 1 Pet. 3:20 Lit., “the patience of God was waiting.”

^ 1 Pet. 3:20 Or “persons.”

1 Peter  4 : 1 - 19

4 Since Christ suffered in the flesh, you too arm yourselves with the same mental disposition;[*] because the person who has suffered in the flesh has desisted from sins, ^2 so that he may live the remainder of his time in the flesh, no more for the desires of men, but for God’s will. ^3 For the time that has passed by is sufficient for you to have done the will of the nations when you carried on in acts of brazen conduct,[*] unbridled passions, overdrinking, wild parties,[*] drinking bouts, and lawless idolatries. ^4 They are puzzled that you do not continue running with them in the same decadent course of debauchery, so they speak abusively of you. ^5 But these people will render an account to the one who is ready to judge those living and those dead. ^6 In fact, this is why the good news was declared also to the dead, so that although they are judged in the flesh from the standpoint of men, they might live in harmony with the spirit from God’s standpoint.

^7 But the end of all things has drawn close. Therefore, be sound in mind, and be vigilant[*] with a view to prayers. ^8 Above all things, have intense love for one another, because love covers a multitude of sins. ^9 Be hospitable to one another without grumbling. ^10 To the extent that each one has received a gift, use it in ministering to one another as fine stewards of God’s undeserved kindness that is expressed in various ways. ^11 If anyone speaks, let him do so as speaking pronouncements from God; if anyone ministers, let him do so as depending on the strength that God supplies; so that in all things God may be glorified through Jesus Christ. The glory and the might are his forever and ever. Amen.

^12 Beloved ones, do not be surprised about the fiery trials that you are experiencing, as though something strange were happening to you. ^13 On the contrary, go on rejoicing over the extent to which you are sharers in the sufferings of the Christ, so that you may rejoice and be overjoyed also during the revelation of his glory. ^14 If you are being reproached[*] for the name of Christ, you are happy, because the spirit of glory, yes, the spirit of God, is resting upon you.

^15 However, let none of you suffer as a murderer or a thief or a wrongdoer or a busybody in other people’s matters. ^16 But if anyone suffers as a Christian, let him not feel ashamed, but let him keep on glorifying God while bearing this name. ^17 For it is the appointed time for the judgment to start with the house of God. Now if it starts first with us, what will the outcome be for those who are not obedient to the good news of God? ^18 “And if the righteous man is being saved with difficulty, what will happen to the ungodly man and the sinner?” ^19 So, then, let those who are suffering in harmony with the will of God keep on entrusting[*] themselves[*] to a faithful Creator while they are doing good.

^ 1 Pet. 4:1 Or “resolve; determination.”

^ 1 Pet. 4:3 Or “acts of shameless conduct.” Plural of the Greek a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

^ 1 Pet. 4:3 Or “revelries.”

^ 1 Pet. 4:7 Or “alert; awake.”

^ 1 Pet. 4:14 Or “insulted.”

^ 1 Pet. 4:19 Or “commending.”

^ 1 Pet. 4:19 Or “their souls.”

1 John  2 : 1 - 29

2 My little children, I am writing you these things so that you may not commit a sin. And yet, if anyone does commit a sin, we have a helper[*] with the Father, Jesus Christ, a righteous one. ^2 And he is a propitiatory sacrifice[*] for our sins, yet not for ours only but also for the whole world’s. ^3 And by this we realize that we have come to know him, namely, if we continue observing his commandments. ^4 The one who says, “I have come to know him,” and yet does not observe his commandments is a liar, and the truth is not in this person. ^5 But whoever does observe his word, in this person the love of God has truly been made perfect. By this we know that we are in union with him. ^6 The one who says he remains in union with him is himself under obligation to go on walking just as that one walked.

^7 Beloved ones, I am writing you, not a new commandment, but an old commandment that you have had from the beginning. This old commandment is the word that you heard. ^8 Again, I am writing you a new commandment, which is true in his case and in yours, because the darkness is passing away and the true light is already shining.

^9 The one who says that he is in the light and yet hates his brother is still in the darkness. ^10 The one who loves his brother remains in the light, and in him there is no cause for stumbling. ^11 But the one who hates his brother is in the darkness and is walking in the darkness, and he does not know where he is going, because the darkness has blinded his eyes.

^12 I am writing you, little children, because your sins have been forgiven you for the sake of his name. ^13 I am writing you, fathers, because you have come to know him who is from the beginning. I am writing you, young men, because you have conquered the wicked one. I write you, young children, because you have come to know the Father. ^14 I write you, fathers, because you have come to know him who is from the beginning. I write you, young men, because you are strong and the word of God remains in you and you have conquered the wicked one.

^15 Do not love either the world or the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him; ^16 because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life[*]—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world. ^17 Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but the one who does the will of God remains forever.

^18 Young children, it is the last hour, and just as you have heard that the antichrist is coming, even now many antichrists have appeared, from which fact we know that it is the last hour. ^19 They went out from us, but they were not of our sort;[*] for if they had been of our sort, they would have remained with us. But they went out so that it might be shown that not all are of our sort. ^20 And you have an anointing from the holy one, and all of you have knowledge. ^21 I write you, not because you do not know the truth, but because you know it, and because no lie originates with the truth.

^22 Who is the liar but the one who denies that Jesus is the Christ? This is the antichrist, the one who denies the Father and the Son. ^23 Everyone who denies the Son does not have the Father either. But whoever acknowledges the Son has the Father also. ^24 As for you, what you have heard from the beginning must remain in you. If what you have heard from the beginning remains in you, you will also remain in union with the Son and in union with the Father. ^25 Furthermore, this is what he himself promised us—the life everlasting.

^26 I write you these things about those who are trying to mislead you. ^27 And as for you, the anointing that you received from him remains in you, and you do not need anyone to be teaching you; but the anointing from him is teaching you about all things and is true and is no lie. Just as it has taught you, remain in union with him. ^28 So now, little children, remain in union with him, so that when he is made manifest we may have freeness of speech and not shrink away from him in shame at his presence. ^29 If you know that he is righteous, you also know that everyone who practices righteousness has been born from him.

^ 1 John 2:1 Or “an advocate.”

^ 1 John 2:2 Or “an atoning sacrifice; a means of appeasement.”

^ 1 John 2:16 Or “the bragging about one’s possessions.”

^ 1 John 2:19 Or “they did not belong to us.”

1 John  3 : 1 - 24

3 See what sort of love the Father has given us, that we should be called children of God! And that is what we are. That is why the world does not know us, because it has not come to know him. ^2 Beloved ones, we are now children of God, but it has not yet been made manifest what we will be. We do know that when he is made manifest we will be like him, because we will see him just as he is. ^3 And everyone who has this hope in him purifies himself, just as that one is pure.

^4 Everyone who practices sin is also practicing lawlessness, and sin is lawlessness. ^5 You know, too, that he was made manifest to take away our sins, and there is no sin in him. ^6 Everyone remaining in union with him does not practice sin; no one who practices sin has either seen him or come to know him. ^7 Little children, let no one mislead you; the one who practices righteousness is righteous, just as that one is righteous. ^8 The one who practices sin originates with the Devil, because the Devil has been sinning from the beginning.[*] For this purpose the Son of God was made manifest, to break up[*] the works of the Devil.

^9 Everyone who has been born from God does not practice sin, for His seed[*] remains in such one, and he cannot practice sin, for he has been born from God. ^10 The children of God and the children of the Devil are evident by this fact: Whoever does not practice righteousness does not originate with God, nor does the one who does not love his brother. ^11 For this is the message that you have heard from the beginning, that we should love one another; ^12 not like Cain, who originated with the wicked one and slaughtered his brother. And for what reason did he slaughter him? Because his own works were wicked, but those of his brother were righteous.

^13 Do not be surprised, brothers, that the world hates you. ^14 We know that we have passed over from death to life, because we love the brothers. The one who does not love remains in death. ^15 Everyone who hates his brother is a murderer,[*] and you know that no murderer has everlasting life remaining in him. ^16 By this we have come to know love, because that one surrendered his life[*] for us, and we are under obligation to surrender our lives[*] for our brothers. ^17 But whoever has the material possessions of this world and sees his brother in need and yet refuses to show him compassion, in what way does the love of God remain in him? ^18 Little children, we should love, not in word or with the tongue, but in deed and truth.

^19 By this we will know that we originate with the truth, and we will assure[*] our hearts before him ^20 regarding whatever our hearts may condemn us in, because God is greater than our hearts and knows all things. ^21 Beloved ones, if our hearts do not condemn us, we have freeness of speech toward God; ^22 and whatever we ask we receive from him, because we are observing his commandments and doing what is pleasing in his eyes. ^23 Indeed, this is his commandment: that we have faith in the name of his Son Jesus Christ and love one another, just as he gave us a commandment. ^24 Moreover, the one who observes his commandments remains in union with him, and he in union with such one. And by the spirit that he gave us, we know that he remains in union with us.

^ 1 John 3:8 Or “from when he began.”

^ 1 John 3:8 Or “destroy.”

^ 1 John 3:9 That is, seed capable of reproducing, or bearing fruit.

^ 1 John 3:15 Or “manslayer.”

^ 1 John 3:16 Or “soul.”

^ 1 John 3:16 Or “souls.”

^ 1 John 3:19 Or “persuade; convince.”

1 John  4 : 1 - 21

4 Beloved ones, do not believe every inspired statement,[*] but test the inspired statements[*] to see whether they originate with God, for many false prophets have gone out into the world.

^2 This is how you know that the inspired statement is from God: Every inspired statement that acknowledges Jesus Christ as having come in the flesh originates with God. ^3 But every inspired statement that does not acknowledge Jesus does not originate with God. Furthermore, this is the antichrist’s inspired statement that you have heard was coming, and now it is already in the world.

^4 You originate with God, little children, and you have conquered them, because the one who is in union with you is greater than the one who is in union with the world. ^5 They originate with the world; that is why they speak what originates with the world and the world listens to them. ^6 We originate with God. Whoever comes to know God listens to us; whoever does not originate with God does not listen to us. By this we distinguish the inspired statement of truth from the inspired statement of error.

^7 Beloved ones, let us continue loving one another, because love is from God, and everyone who loves has been born from God and knows God. ^8 Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love. ^9 By this the love of God was revealed in our case, that God sent his only-begotten Son into the world so that we might gain life through him. ^10 The love is in this respect, not that we have loved God, but that he loved us and sent his Son as a propitiatory sacrifice[*] for our sins.

^11 Beloved ones, if this is how God loved us, then we are also under obligation to love one another. ^12 No one has seen God at any time. If we continue loving one another, God remains in us and his love is made perfect in us. ^13 By this we know that we are remaining in union with him and he in union with us, because he has given his spirit to us. ^14 In addition, we ourselves have seen and are bearing witness that the Father has sent his Son as savior of the world. ^15 Whoever acknowledges that Jesus is God’s Son, God remains in union with such one and he in union with God. ^16 And we have come to know and believe the love that God has for us.

God is love, and the one who remains in love remains in union with God and God remains in union with him. ^17 In this way love has been made perfect in us, so that we may have freeness of speech[*] in the day of judgment, because just as that one is, so are we ourselves in this world. ^18 There is no fear in love, but perfect love casts[*] fear out, because fear restrains us. Indeed, the one who is fearful has not been made perfect in love. ^19 We love, because he first loved us.

^20 If anyone says, “I love God,” and yet is hating his brother, he is a liar. For the one who does not love his brother, whom he has seen, cannot love God, whom he has not seen. ^21 And we have this commandment from him, that whoever loves God must also love his brother.

^ 1 John 4:1 Lit., “every spirit.”

^ 1 John 4:1 Lit., “the spirits.”

^ 1 John 4:10 Or “an atoning sacrifice; a means of appeasement.”

^ 1 John 4:17 Or “have confidence.”

^ 1 John 4:18 Or “drives.”

1 John  5 : 1 - 21

5 Everyone who believes that Jesus is the Christ has been born from God, and everyone who loves the one who caused to be born loves him who has been born from that one. ^2 By this we know that we love the children of God, when we love God and carry out his commandments. ^3 For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome, ^4 because everyone who[*] has been born from God conquers the world. And this is the conquest that has conquered the world, our faith.

^5 Who can conquer the world? Is it not the one who has faith that Jesus is the Son of God? ^6 This is the one who came by means of water and blood, Jesus Christ, not with the water only, but with the water and with the blood. And the spirit is bearing witness, because the spirit is the truth. ^7 For there are three witness bearers: ^8 the spirit and the water and the blood; and the three are in agreement.

^9 If we accept the witness of men, the witness of God is greater. Because this is the witness God gives, the witness that he has given about his Son. ^10 The person putting his faith in the Son of God has the witness within himself. The person not having faith in God has made him a liar, because he has not put his faith in the witness given by God concerning his Son. ^11 And this is the witness, that God gave us everlasting life, and this life is in his Son. ^12 The one who has the Son has this life; the one who does not have the Son of God does not have this life.

^13 I write you these things so that you may know that you have life everlasting, you who put your faith in the name of the Son of God. ^14 And this is the confidence[*] that we have toward him, that no matter what we ask according to his will, he hears us. ^15 And if we know that he hears us concerning whatever we are asking, we know that we are to have the things we ask for, since we have asked them of him.

^16 If anyone catches sight of his brother committing a sin that does not incur death, he will ask, and God will give life to him, yes, to those not committing sin that incurs death. There is a sin that does incur death. It is concerning that sin that I do not tell him to make request. ^17 All unrighteousness is sin, and yet there is a sin that does not incur death.

^18 We know that everyone who has been born from God does not practice sin, but the one born from God[*] watches him, and the wicked one cannot take hold of him.[*] ^19 We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one. ^20 But we know that the Son of God has come, and he has given us insight[*] so that we may gain the knowledge of the one who is true. And we are in union with the one who is true, by means of his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God and life everlasting. ^21 Little children, guard yourselves from idols.

^ 1 John 5:4 Lit., “everything that.”

^ 1 John 5:14 Or “freeness of speech.”

^ 1 John 5:18 That is, Jesus Christ, the Son of God.

^ 1 John 5:18 Or “does not fasten his hold on him.”

^ 1 John 5:20 Lit., “mental perception; intellectual capacity.”

Jude 1 - 25

THE LETTER OF JUDE

^1 Jude, a slave of Jesus Christ, but a brother of James, to the called ones who are loved by God the Father and preserved for Jesus Christ:

^2 May mercy and peace and love be increased to you.

^3 Beloved ones, although I was making every effort to write you about the salvation we hold in common, I found it necessary to write you to urge you to put up a hard fight for the faith that was once for all time delivered to the holy ones. ^4 My reason is that certain men have slipped in among you who were long ago appointed to this judgment by the Scriptures; they are ungodly men who turn the undeserved kindness of our God into an excuse for brazen conduct[*] and who prove false to our only owner[*] and Lord, Jesus Christ.

^5 Although you are fully aware of all of this, I want to remind you that Jehovah,[*] having saved a people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed those not showing faith. ^6 And the angels who did not keep their original position but forsook their own proper dwelling place, he has reserved with eternal bonds in dense darkness for the judgment of the great day. ^7 In the same manner, Sodʹom and Go·morʹrah and the cities around them also gave themselves over to gross sexual immorality[*] and pursued unnatural fleshly desires; they are placed before us as a warning example by undergoing the judicial punishment of everlasting fire.

^8 Despite this, these men too are indulging in dreams, defiling the flesh, despising authority, and speaking abusively of glorious ones. ^9 But when Miʹcha·el the archangel had a difference with the Devil and was disputing about Moses’ body, he did not dare to bring a judgment against him in abusive terms, but said: “May Jehovah[*] rebuke you.” ^10 But these men are speaking abusively about all the things they really do not understand. And in all the things that they do understand by instinct like unreasoning animals, they go on corrupting themselves.

^11 Too bad for them, for they have followed the path of Cain and have rushed into the erroneous course of Baʹlaam for reward, and they have perished in the rebellious talk of Korʹah! ^12 These are the rocks hidden below water at your love feasts while they feast with you, shepherds who feed themselves without fear; waterless clouds carried here and there by the wind; fruitless trees in late autumn, having died twice[*] and having been uprooted; ^13 wild waves of the sea that cast up the foam of their own shame; stars with no set course, for which the blackest darkness stands reserved forever.

^14 Yes, the seventh one in line from Adam, Eʹnoch, also prophesied about them when he said: “Look! Jehovah[*] came with his holy myriads[*] ^15 to execute judgment against all, and to convict all the ungodly concerning all their ungodly deeds that they did in an ungodly way, and concerning all the shocking things that ungodly sinners spoke against him.”

^16 These men are murmurers, complainers about their lot in life, following their own desires, and their mouths make grandiose boasts, while they are flattering others[*] for their own benefit.

^17 As for you, beloved ones, call to mind the sayings that have been previously spoken[*] by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ, ^18 how they used to say to you: “In the last time there will be ridiculers, following their own desires for ungodly things.” ^19 These are the ones who cause divisions, animalistic men,[*] not having spirituality.[*] ^20 But you, beloved ones, build yourselves up on your most holy faith, and pray with holy spirit, ^21 in order to keep yourselves in God’s love, while you await the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ with everlasting life in view. ^22 Also, continue showing mercy to some who have doubts; ^23 save them by snatching them out of the fire. But continue showing mercy to others, doing so with fear, while you hate even the garment that has been stained by the flesh.

^24 Now to the one who is able to guard you from stumbling and to make you stand unblemished in the sight of his glory[*] with great joy, ^25 to the only God our Savior through Jesus Christ our Lord, be glory, majesty, might, and authority for all past eternity and now and into all eternity. Amen.

^ Jude 4 Or “shameless conduct.” Greek, a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

^ Jude 4 Or “master.”

^ Jude 5 See App. A5.

^ Jude 7 See Glossary.

^ Jude 9 See App. A5.

^ Jude 12 Or “being completely dead.”

^ Jude 14 See App. A5.

^ Jude 14 Or “tens of thousands.”

^ Jude 16 Or “admiring personalities.”

^ Jude 17 Or “the things foretold.”

^ Jude 19 Or “physical men.”

^ Jude 19 Lit., “the spirit.”

^ Jude 24 Or “in his glorious presence.”

Revelation  1 : 1 - 20

A REVELATION TO JOHN

1 A revelation[*] by Jesus Christ, which God gave him, to show his slaves the things that must shortly take place. And he sent his angel and presented it in signs through him to his slave John, ^2 who bore witness to the word God gave and to the witness Jesus Christ gave, yes, to all the things he saw. ^3 Happy is the one who reads aloud and those who hear the words of this prophecy and who observe the things written in it, for the appointed time is near.

^4 John to the seven congregations that are in the province of Asia:

May you have undeserved kindness and peace from “the One who is and who was and who is coming,” and from the seven spirits that are before his throne, ^5 and from Jesus Christ, “the Faithful Witness,” “the firstborn from the dead,” and “the Ruler of the kings of the earth.”

To him who loves us and who set us free from our sins by means of his own blood— ^6 and he made us to be a kingdom, priests to his God and Father—yes, to him be the glory and the might forever. Amen.

^7 Look! He is coming with the clouds, and every eye will see him, and those who pierced him; and all the tribes of the earth will beat themselves in grief because of him. Yes, Amen.

^8 “I am the Alʹpha and the O·meʹga,”[*] says Jehovah[*] God, “the One who is and who was and who is coming, the Almighty.”

^9 I John, your brother and a sharer with you in the tribulation and kingdom and endurance in association with Jesus, was on the island called Patʹmos for speaking about God and bearing witness concerning Jesus. ^10 By inspiration I came to be in the Lord’s day, and I heard behind me a strong voice like that of a trumpet, ^11 saying: “What you see, write in a scroll and send it to the seven congregations: in Ephʹe·sus, in Smyrʹna, in Perʹga·mum, in Thy·a·tiʹra, in Sarʹdis, in Philadelphia, and in La·o·di·ceʹa.”

^12 I turned to see who was speaking with me, and when I turned, I saw seven golden lampstands, ^13 and in the midst of the lampstands someone like a son of man, clothed in a garment that reached down to the feet and wearing a golden sash around his chest. ^14 Moreover, his head and his hair were white as white wool, as snow, and his eyes were like a fiery flame, ^15 and his feet were like fine copper when glowing in a furnace, and his voice was like the sound of many waters. ^16 And he had in his right hand seven stars, and out of his mouth a sharp, long, two-edged sword was protruding, and his countenance[*] was like the sun when it shines at its brightest. ^17 When I saw him, I fell as dead at his feet.

And he laid his right hand on me and said: “Do not be afraid. I am the First and the Last, ^18 and the living one, and I became dead, but look! I am living forever and ever, and I have the keys of death and of the Grave.[*] ^19 So write down the things you saw, and the things that are, and the things that will take place after these. ^20 As for the sacred secret of the seven stars that you saw in my right hand and of the seven golden lampstands: The seven stars mean the angels of the seven congregations, and the seven lampstands mean the seven congregations.

^ Rev. 1:1 Or “A disclosure; An uncovering.”

^ Rev. 1:8 Or “the A and the Z.” Alpha and Omega are the first and last letters of the Greek alphabet.

^ Rev. 1:8 See App. A5.

^ Rev. 1:16 Or “face.”

^ Rev. 1:18 Or “Hades,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Revelation  2 : 1 - 29

2 “To the angel of the congregation in Ephʹe·sus write: These are the things that he says who holds the seven stars in his right hand and walks among the seven golden lampstands: ^2 ‘I know your deeds, and your labor and endurance, and that you cannot tolerate bad men, and that you put to the test those who say they are apostles, but they are not, and you found them to be liars. ^3 You are also showing endurance, and you have persevered for the sake of my name and have not grown weary. ^4 Nevertheless, I hold this against you, that you have left the love you had at first.

^5 “‘Therefore remember from where you have fallen, and repent and do the deeds you did at first. If you do not, I will come to you, and I will remove your lampstand from its place, unless you repent. ^6 Still, you do have this in your favor: that you hate the deeds of the sect of Nic·o·laʹus, which I also hate. ^7 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations: To the one who conquers I will grant to eat of the tree of life, which is in the paradise of God.’

^8 “And to the angel of the congregation in Smyrʹna write: These are the things that he says, ‘the First and the Last,’ who became dead and came to life again: ^9 ‘I know your tribulation and poverty—but you are rich—and the blasphemy by those who call themselves Jews and really are not, but they are a synagogue of Satan. ^10 Do not be afraid of the things you are about to suffer. Look! The Devil will keep on throwing some of you into prison so that you may be fully put to the test, and you will have tribulation for ten days. Prove yourself faithful even to death, and I will give you the crown of life. ^11 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations: The one who conquers will by no means be harmed by the second death.’

^12 “To the angel of the congregation in Perʹga·mum write: These are the things that he says who has the sharp, long, two-edged sword: ^13 ‘I know where you are dwelling, that is, where the throne of Satan is; and yet you keep holding fast to my name, and you did not deny your faith in me even in the days of Anʹti·pas, my faithful witness, who was killed by your side, where Satan is dwelling.

^14 “‘Nevertheless, I have a few things against you, that you have there those adhering to the teaching of Baʹlaam, who taught Baʹlak to put a stumbling block before the sons of Israel, to eat things sacrificed to idols and to commit sexual immorality.[*] ^15 In the same way, you also have those adhering to the teaching of the sect of Nic·o·laʹus. ^16 So repent. If you do not, I am coming to you quickly, and I will war against them with the long sword of my mouth.

^17 “‘Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations: To the one who conquers I will give some of the hidden manna, and I will give him a white pebble, and written on the pebble is a new name that no one knows except the one receiving it.’

^18 “To the angel of the congregation in Thy·a·tiʹra write: These are the things that the Son of God says, the one who has eyes like a fiery flame and whose feet are like fine copper: ^19 ‘I know your deeds, and your love and faith and ministry and endurance, and that your deeds of late are more than those you did at first.

^20 “‘Nevertheless, I do hold this against you, that you tolerate that woman Jezʹe·bel, who calls herself a prophetess, and she teaches and misleads my slaves to commit sexual immorality[*] and to eat things sacrificed to idols. ^21 And I gave her time to repent, but she is not willing to repent of her sexual immorality.[*] ^22 Look! I am about to throw her into a sickbed, and those committing adultery with her into great tribulation, unless they repent of her deeds. ^23 And I will kill her children with deadly plague, so that all the congregations will know that I am the one who searches the innermost thoughts[*] and hearts, and I will give to you individually according to your deeds.

^24 “‘However, I say to the rest of you who are in Thy·a·tiʹra, all those who do not follow this teaching, those who did not get to know the so-called “deep things of Satan”: I am not putting on you any other burden. ^25 Just the same, hold fast to what you have until I come. ^26 And to the one who conquers and observes my deeds down to the end, I will give authority over the nations, ^27 and he will shepherd the people with an iron rod so that they will be broken to pieces like clay vessels, just as I have received from my Father. ^28 And I will give him the morning star. ^29 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’

^ Rev. 2:14 See Glossary.

^ Rev. 2:20 See Glossary.

^ Rev. 2:21 Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 2:23 Or “the deepest emotions.” Lit., “kidneys.”

Revelation  3 : 1 - 22

3 “To the angel of the congregation in Sarʹdis write: These are the things that he says who has the seven spirits of God and the seven stars: ‘I know your deeds, that you have the name[*] that you are alive, but you are dead. ^2 Become watchful, and strengthen the things remaining that were ready to die, for I have not found your works fully performed[*] before my God. ^3 Therefore, continue mindful of[*] how you have received and how you heard, and go on keeping it, and repent. Certainly unless you wake up, I will come as a thief, and you will not know at all at what hour I will come upon you.

^4 “‘Nevertheless, you do have a few individuals[*] in Sarʹdis who did not defile their garments, and they will walk with me in white ones, because they are worthy. ^5 The one who conquers will thus be dressed in white garments, and I will by no means blot out[*] his name from the book of life, but I will acknowledge his name before my Father and before his angels. ^6 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’

^7 “To the angel of the congregation in Philadelphia write: These are the things he says who is holy, who is true, who has the key of David, who opens so that no one will shut and shuts so that no one opens: ^8 ‘I know your deeds—look! I have set before you an opened door, which no one can shut. And I know that you have a little power, and you kept my word and did not prove false to my name. ^9 Look! I will make those from the synagogue of Satan who say they are Jews yet are not, but are lying—look! I will make them come and bow[*] before your feet and make them know that I have loved you. ^10 Because you kept the word about my endurance,[*] I will also keep you from the hour of test, which is to come upon the entire inhabited earth, to put to the test those dwelling on the earth. ^11 I am coming quickly. Keep holding fast to what you have, so that no one may take your crown.

^12 “‘The one who conquers—I will make him a pillar in the temple of my God, and he will by no means go out from it anymore, and I will write upon him the name of my God and the name of the city of my God, the New Jerusalem that descends out of heaven from my God, and my own new name. ^13 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’

^14 “To the angel of the congregation in La·o·di·ceʹa write: These are the things that the Amen says, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation by God: ^15 ‘I know your deeds, that you are neither cold nor hot. I wish you were cold or else hot. ^16 So because you are lukewarm and neither hot nor cold, I am going to vomit you out of my mouth. ^17 Because you say, “I am rich and have acquired riches and do not need anything at all,” but you do not know that you are miserable and pitiful and poor and blind and naked, ^18 I advise you to buy from me gold refined by fire so that you may become rich, and white garments so that you may become dressed and that the shame of your nakedness may not be exposed, and eyesalve to rub in your eyes so that you may see.

^19 “‘All those for whom I have affection, I reprove and discipline. So be zealous and repent. ^20 Look! I am standing at the door and knocking. If anyone hears my voice and opens the door, I will come into his house and take the evening meal with him and he with me. ^21 To the one who conquers I will grant to sit down with me on my throne, just as I conquered and sat down with my Father on his throne. ^22 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’”

^ Rev. 3:1 Or “reputation.”

^ Rev. 3:2 Or “complete.”

^ Rev. 3:3 Or “remember.”

^ Rev. 3:4 Lit., “a few names.”

^ Rev. 3:5 Or “erase.”

^ Rev. 3:9 Or “do obeisance.”

^ Rev. 3:10 Or possibly, “followed the example of my endurance.”

Revelation  4 : 1 - 11

4 After this I saw, and look! an opened door in heaven, and the first voice that I heard speaking with me was like a trumpet, saying: “Come up here, and I will show you the things that must take place.” ^2 After this I immediately came to be in the power of the spirit, and look! a throne was in its position in heaven, and someone was seated on the throne. ^3 And the One seated had the appearance of a jasper stone and a sardius stone,[*] and all around the throne was a rainbow like an emerald in appearance.

^4 All around the throne were 24 thrones, and on these thrones I saw seated 24 elders dressed in white garments, and on their heads golden crowns. ^5 From the throne were coming lightning and voices and thunders; and there were seven lamps of fire burning before the throne, and these mean the seven spirits of God. ^6 Before the throne was something resembling a glassy sea, like crystal.

In the midst of the throne[*] and around the throne were four living creatures that were full of eyes in front and behind. ^7 The first living creature was like a lion, and the second living creature was like a young bull, and the third living creature had a face like a man’s, and the fourth living creature was like a flying eagle. ^8 As for the four living creatures, each one of them had six wings; they were full of eyes all around and underneath. And continuously, day and night, they say: “Holy, holy, holy is Jehovah[*] God, the Almighty, who was and who is and who is coming.”

^9 Whenever the living creatures give glory and honor and thanksgiving to the One seated on the throne, the One who lives forever and ever, ^10 the 24 elders fall down before the One seated on the throne and worship the One who lives forever and ever, and they cast their crowns before the throne, saying: ^11 “You are worthy, Jehovah[*] our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

^ Rev. 4:3 Or “a precious red-colored stone.”

^ Rev. 4:6 Or “In the middle with the throne.”

^ Rev. 4:8 See App. A5.

^ Rev. 4:11 See App. A5.

Revelation  5 : 1 - 14

5 And I saw in the right hand of the One seated on the throne a scroll written on both sides,[*] sealed tight with seven seals. ^2 And I saw a strong angel proclaiming with a loud voice: “Who is worthy to open the scroll and break its seals?” ^3 But no one in heaven or on earth or underneath the earth was able to open the scroll or to look into it. ^4 I gave way to a great deal of weeping because no one was found worthy to open the scroll or to look into it. ^5 But one of the elders said to me: “Stop weeping. Look! The Lion of the tribe of Judah, the root of David, has conquered so as to open the scroll and its seven seals.”

^6 And I saw standing in the midst[*] of the throne and of the four living creatures and in the midst of the elders a lamb that seemed to have been slaughtered, having seven horns and seven eyes, and the eyes mean the seven spirits of God that have been sent out into the whole earth. ^7 At once he came forward and took it out of the right hand of the One seated on the throne. ^8 When he took the scroll, the four living creatures and the 24 elders fell down before the Lamb, and each one had a harp and golden bowls that were full of incense. (The incense means the prayers of the holy ones.) ^9 And they sing a new song, saying: “You are worthy to take the scroll and open its seals, for you were slaughtered and with your blood you bought people for God out of every tribe and tongue[*] and people and nation, ^10 and you made them to be a kingdom and priests to our God, and they are to rule as kings over the earth.”

^11 And I saw, and I heard a voice of many angels around the throne and the living creatures and the elders, and the number of them was myriads of myriads[*] and thousands of thousands, ^12 and they were saying with a loud voice: “The Lamb who was slaughtered is worthy to receive the power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.”

^13 And I heard every creature in heaven and on earth and underneath the earth and on the sea, and all the things in them, saying: “To the One sitting on the throne and to the Lamb be the blessing and the honor and the glory and the might forever and ever.” ^14 The four living creatures were saying: “Amen!” and the elders fell down and worshipped.

^ Rev. 5:1 Lit., “inside and on the back.”

^ Rev. 5:6 Or “at the center.”

^ Rev. 5:9 Or “language.”

^ Rev. 5:11 Or “tens of thousands times tens of thousands.”

Revelation  6 : 1 - 17

6 And I saw when the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures say with a voice like thunder: “Come!” ^2 And I saw, and look! a white horse, and the one seated on it had a bow; and a crown was given him, and he went out conquering and to complete his conquest.

^3 When he opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature say: “Come!” ^4 Another came out, a fiery-colored horse, and it was granted to the one seated on it to take peace away from the earth so that they should slaughter one another, and he was given a great sword.

^5 When he opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature say: “Come!” And I saw, and look! a black horse, and the one seated on it had a pair of scales in his hand. ^6 I heard what sounded like a voice in the midst of the four living creatures say: “A quart[*] of wheat for a de·narʹi·us[*] and three quarts of barley for a de·narʹi·us; and do not harm the olive oil and the wine.”

^7 When he opened the fourth seal, I heard the voice of the fourth living creature say: “Come!” ^8 And I saw, and look! a pale horse, and the one seated on it had the name Death. And the Grave[*] was closely following him. And authority was given them over the fourth part of the earth, to kill with a long sword and with food shortage and with deadly plague and by the wild beasts of the earth.

^9 When he opened the fifth seal, I saw underneath the altar the souls[*] of those slaughtered because of the word of God and because of the witness they had given. ^10 They shouted with a loud voice, saying: “Until when, Sovereign Lord, holy and true, are you refraining from judging and avenging our blood on those who dwell on the earth?” ^11 And a white robe was given to each of them, and they were told to rest a little while longer, until the number was filled of their fellow slaves and their brothers who were about to be killed as they had been.

^12 And I saw when he opened the sixth seal, and a great earthquake occurred; and the sun became black as sackcloth made of hair,[*] and the entire moon became as blood, ^13 and the stars of heaven fell to the earth as when a fig tree shaken by a high wind drops its unripe figs. ^14 And the heaven departed as a scroll that is being rolled up, and every mountain and every island was removed from its place. ^15 Then the kings of the earth, the high officials, the military commanders, the rich, the strong, every slave, and every free person hid in the caves and among the rocks of the mountains. ^16 And they keep saying to the mountains and to the rocks: “Fall over us and hide us from the face of the One seated on the throne and from the wrath of the Lamb, ^17 because the great day of their wrath has come, and who is able to stand?”

^ Rev. 6:6 See App. B14.

^ Rev. 6:6 A Roman silver coin that equaled a day’s wage. See App. B14.

^ Rev. 6:8 Or “Hades,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 6:9 Evidently referring to their lifeblood poured out at the altar. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 6:12 Probably goat hair.

Revelation  7 : 1 - 17

7 After this I saw four angels standing on the four corners of the earth, holding tight the four winds of the earth, so that no wind could blow on the earth or on the sea or on any tree. ^2 And I saw another angel ascending from the sunrise,[*] having a seal of the living God; and he called with a loud voice to the four angels to whom it was granted to harm the earth and the sea, ^3 saying: “Do not harm the earth or the sea or the trees, until after we have sealed the slaves of our God in their foreheads.”

^4 And I heard the number of those who were sealed, 144,000, sealed out of every tribe of the sons of Israel:

^5 Out of the tribe of Judah 12,000 sealed;

out of the tribe of Reuʹben 12,000;

out of the tribe of Gad 12,000;

^6 out of the tribe of Ashʹer 12,000;

out of the tribe of Naphʹta·li 12,000;

out of the tribe of Ma·nasʹseh 12,000;

^7 out of the tribe of Simʹe·on 12,000;

out of the tribe of Leʹvi 12,000;

out of the tribe of Isʹsa·char 12,000;

^8 out of the tribe of Zebʹu·lun 12,000;

out of the tribe of Joseph 12,000;

out of the tribe of Benjamin 12,000 sealed.

^9 After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,[*] standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands. ^10 And they keep shouting with a loud voice, saying: “Salvation we owe to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb.”

^11 All the angels were standing around the throne and the elders and the four living creatures, and they fell facedown before the throne and worshipped God, ^12 saying: “Amen! Let the praise and the glory and the wisdom and the thanksgiving and the honor and the power and the strength be to our God forever and ever. Amen.”

^13 In response one of the elders said to me: “These who are dressed in the white robes, who are they and where did they come from?” ^14 So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb. ^15 That is why they are before the throne of God, and they are rendering him sacred service day and night in his temple; and the One seated on the throne will spread his tent over them. ^16 They will hunger no more nor thirst anymore, neither will the sun beat down on them nor any scorching heat, ^17 because the Lamb, who is in the midst[*] of the throne, will shepherd them and will guide them to springs[*] of waters of life. And God will wipe out every tear from their eyes.”

^ Rev. 7:2 Or “east.”

^ Rev. 7:9 Or “languages.”

^ Rev. 7:17 Or “at the center.”

^ Rev. 7:17 Or “fountains.”

Revelation  8 : 1 - 13

8 When he opened the seventh seal, there was silence in heaven for about half an hour. ^2 And I saw the seven angels who stand before God, and seven trumpets were given to them.

^3 Another angel, holding a golden incense vessel,[*] arrived and stood at the altar, and a large quantity of incense was given him to offer it with the prayers of all the holy ones on the golden altar that was before the throne. ^4 The smoke of the incense from the hand of the angel ascended with the prayers of the holy ones before God. ^5 But right away the angel took the incense vessel, and he filled it with some of the fire of the altar and hurled it to the earth. And there were thunders and voices and flashes of lightning and an earthquake. ^6 And the seven angels with the seven trumpets prepared to blow them.

^7 The first one blew his trumpet. And there was hail and fire mingled with blood, and it was hurled to the earth; and a third of the earth was burned up, and a third of the trees were burned up, and all the green vegetation was burned up.

^8 The second angel blew his trumpet. And something like a great mountain burning with fire was hurled into the sea. And a third of the sea became blood; ^9 and a third of the living creatures[*] in the sea died, and a third of the ships were wrecked.

^10 The third angel blew his trumpet. And a great star burning like a lamp fell from heaven, and it fell on a third of the rivers and on the springs[*] of waters. ^11 The name of the star is Wormwood. And a third of the waters turned into wormwood, and many of the people died from the waters, because these had been made bitter.

^12 The fourth angel blew his trumpet. And a third of the sun was struck and a third of the moon and a third of the stars, in order that a third of them might be darkened and the day might not have light for a third of it, and the night likewise.

^13 And I saw, and I heard an eagle flying in midheaven say with a loud voice: “Woe, woe, woe to those dwelling on the earth because of the rest of the trumpet blasts of the three angels who are about to blow their trumpets!”

^ Rev. 8:3 Or “burner.”

^ Rev. 8:9 Or “creatures that have souls.”

^ Rev. 8:10 Or “fountains.”

Revelation  9 : 1 - 21

9 The fifth angel blew his trumpet. And I saw a star that had fallen from heaven to the earth, and the key to the shaft[*] of the abyss was given to him. ^2 He opened the shaft[*] of the abyss, and smoke ascended out of the shaft[*] like the smoke of a great furnace, and the sun was darkened, also the air, by the smoke of the shaft.[*] ^3 And locusts came out of the smoke onto the earth, and authority was given to them, the same authority that the scorpions of the earth have. ^4 They were told not to harm the vegetation of the earth or any green plant or any tree, but only those people who do not have the seal of God on their foreheads.

^5 And it was granted the locusts, not to kill them, but to torment them five months, and their torment was like torment by a scorpion when it strikes a person. ^6 In those days people will seek death but will by no means find it, and they will long to die, but death will flee from them.

^7 And in appearance the locusts resembled horses prepared for battle; on their heads were what seemed to be crowns of gold, and their faces were like human faces, ^8 but they had hair like women’s hair. And their teeth were like those of lions, ^9 and they had breastplates like iron breastplates. And the sound of their wings was like the sound of horse-drawn chariots rushing into battle. ^10 Also, they have tails with stingers like scorpions, and in their tails is their authority to hurt the people for five months. ^11 They have over them a king, the angel of the abyss. In Hebrew his name is A·badʹdon,[*] but in Greek he has the name A·polʹlyon.[*]

^12 The one woe is past. Look! Two more woes are coming after these things.

^13 The sixth angel blew his trumpet. And I heard one voice from the horns of the golden altar that is before God ^14 say to the sixth angel who had the trumpet: “Untie the four angels who are bound at the great river Eu·phraʹtes.” ^15 And the four angels who have been prepared for the hour and day and month and year were untied to kill a third of the people.

^16 The number of the armies of cavalry was two myriads of myriads;[*] I heard the number of them. ^17 And this is how I saw the horses in the vision and those seated on them: They had fire-red and hyacinth-blue and sulfur-yellow breastplates, and the heads of the horses were like the heads of lions, and fire and smoke and sulfur came out of their mouths. ^18 A third of the people were killed by these three plagues, by the fire and the smoke and the sulfur that came out of their mouths. ^19 For the authority of the horses is in their mouths and in their tails, for their tails are like serpents and have heads, and with these they inflict harm.

^20 But the rest of the people who were not killed by these plagues did not repent of the works of their hands; they did not stop worshipping the demons and the idols of gold and silver and copper and stone and wood, which can neither see nor hear nor walk. ^21 And they did not repent of their murders nor of their spiritistic practices nor of their sexual immorality[*] nor of their thefts.

^ Rev. 9:1 Or “pit.”

^ Rev. 9:2 Or “pit.”

^ Rev. 9:2 Or “pit.”

^ Rev. 9:2 Or “pit.”

^ Rev. 9:11 Meaning “Destruction.”

^ Rev. 9:11 Meaning “Destroyer.”

^ Rev. 9:16 Or “20,000 times 10,000,” that is, 200,000,000.

^ Rev. 9:21 Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Revelation  10 : 1 - 11

10 And I saw another strong angel descending from heaven, arrayed[*] with a cloud, and a rainbow was on his head, and his face was like the sun, and his legs[*] were like pillars of fire, ^2 and he had in his hand a little scroll that had been unrolled. And he set his right foot on the sea, but his left one on the earth, ^3 and he cried out with a loud voice just as when a lion roars. And when he cried out, the voices of the seven thunders spoke.

^4 Now when the seven thunders spoke, I was about to write, but I heard a voice out of heaven say: “Seal up the things the seven thunders spoke, and do not write them down.” ^5 The angel whom I saw standing on the sea and on the earth raised his right hand to heaven, ^6 and he swore by the One who lives forever and ever, who created the heaven and the things in it and the earth and the things in it and the sea and the things in it: “There will be no delay any longer. ^7 But in the days when the seventh angel is about to blow his trumpet, the sacred secret that God declared as good news to his own slaves the prophets is indeed brought to a finish.”

^8 And I heard the voice out of heaven speaking again with me and saying: “Go, take the opened scroll that is in the hand of the angel who is standing on the sea and on the earth.” ^9 I went to the angel and told him to give me the little scroll. He said to me: “Take it and eat it up, and it will make your stomach bitter, but in your mouth it will be sweet like honey.” ^10 I took the little scroll out of the hand of the angel and ate it, and in my mouth it was sweet like honey, but when I had eaten it, my stomach was made bitter. ^11 And they said to me: “You must prophesy again about peoples and nations and tongues[*] and many kings.”

^ Rev. 10:1 Or “wrapped.”

^ Rev. 10:1 Lit., “feet.”

^ Rev. 10:11 Or “languages.”

Revelation  11 : 1 - 19

11 And a reed like a rod[*] was given to me as he said: “Get up and measure the temple sanctuary of God and the altar and those worshipping in it. ^2 But as for the courtyard that is outside the temple sanctuary, leave it out and do not measure it, because it has been given to the nations, and they will trample the holy city underfoot for 42 months. ^3 I will cause my two witnesses to prophesy for 1,260 days dressed in sackcloth.” ^4 These are symbolized by the two olive trees and the two lampstands and are standing before the Lord of the earth.

^5 If anyone wants to harm them, fire comes out of their mouths and consumes their enemies. If anyone should want to harm them, this is how he must be killed. ^6 These have the authority to shut up the sky[*] so that no rain may fall during the days of their prophesying, and they have authority over the waters to turn them into blood and to strike the earth with every sort of plague as often as they wish.

^7 When they have finished their witnessing, the wild beast that ascends out of the abyss will wage war with them and conquer them and kill them. ^8 And their corpses will be on the main street of the great city that is in a spiritual sense called Sodʹom and Egypt, where their Lord was also executed on the stake. ^9 And those of the peoples and tribes and tongues[*] and nations will look at their corpses for three and a half days, and they do not allow their corpses to be laid in a tomb. ^10 And those dwelling on the earth rejoice over them and celebrate, and they will send gifts to one another, because these two prophets tormented those dwelling on the earth.

^11 After the three and a half days, spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood on their feet, and great fear fell upon those who saw them. ^12 And they heard a loud voice from heaven say to them: “Come up here.” And they went up into heaven in the cloud, and their enemies saw them.[*] ^13 In that hour there was a great earthquake, and a tenth of the city fell; and 7,000 persons were killed by the earthquake, and the rest became frightened and gave glory to the God of heaven.

^14 The second woe is past. Look! The third woe is coming quickly.

^15 The seventh angel blew his trumpet. And there were loud voices in heaven, saying: “The kingdom of the world has become the Kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ, and he will rule as king forever and ever.”

^16 And the 24 elders who were seated before God on their thrones fell upon their faces and worshipped God, ^17 saying: “We thank you, Jehovah[*] God, the Almighty, the one who is and who was, because you have taken your great power and begun ruling as king. ^18 But the nations became wrathful, and your own wrath came, and the appointed time came for the dead to be judged and to reward your slaves the prophets and the holy ones and those fearing your name, the small and the great, and to bring to ruin those ruining[*] the earth.”

^19 And the temple sanctuary of God in heaven was opened, and the ark of his covenant was seen in his temple sanctuary. And there were flashes of lightning and voices and thunders and an earthquake and a great hail.

^ Rev. 11:1 Or “a measuring rod.”

^ Rev. 11:6 Or “heaven.”

^ Rev. 11:9 Or “languages.”

^ Rev. 11:12 Or “were looking on.”

^ Rev. 11:17 See App. A5.

^ Rev. 11:18 Or “to destroy those who are destroying.”

Revelation  13 : 1 - 18

13 And it[*] stood still on the sand of the sea.

And I saw a wild beast ascending out of the sea, with ten horns and seven heads, and on its horns ten diadems,[*] but on its heads blasphemous names. ^2 Now the wild beast that I saw was like a leopard, but its feet were like those of a bear, and its mouth was like a lion’s mouth. And the dragon gave to the beast its power and its throne and great authority.

^3 I saw that one of its heads seemed to have been fatally wounded, but its mortal wound had been healed, and all the earth followed the wild beast with admiration. ^4 And they worshipped the dragon because it gave the authority to the wild beast, and they worshipped the wild beast with the words: “Who is like the wild beast, and who can do battle with it?” ^5 It was given a mouth speaking great things and blasphemies, and it was given authority to act for 42 months. ^6 And it opened its mouth in blasphemies against God to blaspheme his name and his dwelling place, even those residing in heaven. ^7 It was permitted to wage war with the holy ones and conquer them, and it was given authority over every tribe and people and tongue[*] and nation. ^8 And all those who dwell on the earth will worship it. From the founding of the world, not one of their names has been written in the scroll of life of the Lamb who was slaughtered.

^9 If anyone has an ear, let him hear. ^10 If anyone is meant for captivity, he will go into captivity. If anyone will kill with the sword,[*] he must be killed with the sword. This is where it calls for endurance and faith on the part of the holy ones.

^11 Then I saw another wild beast ascending out of the earth, and it had two horns like a lamb, but it began speaking like a dragon. ^12 It exercises all the authority of the first wild beast in its sight. And it makes the earth and its inhabitants worship the first wild beast, whose mortal wound was healed. ^13 And it performs great signs, even making fire come down out of heaven to the earth in the sight of mankind.

^14 It misleads those who dwell on the earth, because of the signs that it was permitted to perform in the sight of the wild beast, while it tells those who dwell on the earth to make an image to the wild beast that had the sword-stroke and yet revived. ^15 And it was permitted to give breath[*] to the image of the wild beast, so that the image of the wild beast should both speak and cause to be killed all those who refuse to worship the image of the wild beast.

^16 It puts under compulsion all people—the small and the great, the rich and the poor, the free and the slaves—that these should be marked on their right hand or on their forehead, ^17 and that nobody can buy or sell except a person having the mark, the name of the wild beast or the number of its name. ^18 This is where it calls for wisdom: Let the one who has insight calculate the number of the wild beast, for it is a man’s number,[*] and its number is 666.

^ Rev. 13:1 That is, the dragon.

^ Rev. 13:1 Or “royal headbands.”

^ Rev. 13:7 Or “language.”

^ Rev. 13:10 Or possibly, “If anyone is to be killed with the sword.”

^ Rev. 13:15 Or “spirit.”

^ Rev. 13:18 Or “a human number.”

Revelation  14 : 1 - 20

14 Then I saw, and look! the Lamb standing on Mount Zion, and with him 144,000 who have his name and the name of his Father written on their foreheads. ^2 I heard a sound coming out of heaven like the sound of many waters and like the sound of loud thunder; and the sound that I heard was like singers who accompany themselves by playing on their harps. ^3 And they are singing what seems to be a new song before the throne and before the four living creatures and the elders, and no one was able to master that song except the 144,000, who have been bought from the earth. ^4 These are the ones who did not defile themselves with women; in fact, they are virgins. These are the ones who keep following the Lamb no matter where he goes. These were bought from among mankind as firstfruits to God and to the Lamb, ^5 and no deceit was found in their mouths; they are without blemish.

^6 And I saw another angel flying in midheaven,[*] and he had everlasting good news to declare to those who dwell on the earth, to every nation and tribe and tongue[*] and people. ^7 He was saying in a loud voice: “Fear God and give him glory, because the hour of judgment by him has arrived, so worship the One who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and the springs[*] of water.”

^8 Another, a second angel, followed, saying: “She has fallen! Babylon the Great has fallen, she who made all the nations drink of the wine of the passion[*] of her sexual immorality!”[*]

^9 Another angel, a third, followed them, saying in a loud voice: “If anyone worships the wild beast and its image and receives a mark on his forehead or on his hand, ^10 he will also drink of the wine of the anger of God that is poured out undiluted into the cup of His wrath, and he will be tormented with fire and sulfur in the sight of the holy angels and in the sight of the Lamb. ^11 And the smoke of their torment ascends forever and ever, and day and night they have no rest, those who worship the wild beast and its image and whoever receives the mark of its name. ^12 Here is where it calls for endurance on the part of the holy ones, those who keep the commandments of God and hold fast to the faith of Jesus.”

^13 And I heard a voice out of heaven say, “Write: Happy are the dead who die in union with the Lord from this time onward. Yes, says the spirit, let them rest from their labors, for the things they did go right[*] with them.”

^14 Then I saw, and look! a white cloud, and seated on the cloud was someone like a son of man, with a golden crown on his head and a sharp sickle in his hand.

^15 Another angel emerged from the temple sanctuary, calling with a loud voice to the one seated on the cloud: “Put your sickle in and reap, because the hour has come to reap, for the harvest of the earth is fully ripe.” ^16 And the one seated on the cloud thrust his sickle into the earth, and the earth was reaped.

^17 And still another angel emerged from the temple sanctuary that is in heaven, and he also had a sharp sickle.

^18 And still another angel emerged from the altar, and he had authority over the fire. And he called out with a loud voice to the one who had the sharp sickle, saying: “Put your sharp sickle in and gather the clusters of the vine of the earth, for its grapes have become ripe.” ^19 The angel thrust his sickle into the earth and gathered the vine of the earth, and he hurled it into the great winepress of God’s anger. ^20 The winepress was trodden outside the city, and blood came out of the winepress as high up as the bridles of the horses for a distance of 1,600 stadia.[*]

^ Rev. 14:6 Or “in midair; overhead.”

^ Rev. 14:6 Or “language.”

^ Rev. 14:7 Or “fountains.”

^ Rev. 14:8 Or “anger.”

^ Rev. 14:8 Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 14:13 Or “along.”

^ Rev. 14:20 About 296 km (184 mi). A stadium equaled 185 m (606.95 ft). See App. B14.

Revelation  15 : 1 - 8

15 And I saw in heaven another sign, great and wonderful, seven angels with seven plagues. These are the last ones, because by means of them the anger of God is brought to a finish.

^2 And I saw something like a sea of glass mingled with fire, and those who are victorious over the wild beast and its image and the number of its name were standing by the sea of glass, holding harps of God. ^3 They were singing the song of Moses the slave of God and the song of the Lamb, saying:

“Great and wonderful are your works, Jehovah[*] God, the Almighty. Righteous and true are your ways, King of eternity. ^4 Who will not really fear you, Jehovah,[*] and glorify your name, for you alone are loyal? For all the nations will come and worship before you, because your righteous decrees have been revealed.”

^5 After this I saw, and the sanctuary of the tent of the witness was opened in heaven, ^6 and the seven angels with the seven plagues emerged from the sanctuary, clothed with clean, bright linen and with golden sashes wrapped around their chests. ^7 One of the four living creatures gave the seven angels seven golden bowls that were full of the anger of God, who lives forever and ever. ^8 And the sanctuary became filled with smoke because of the glory of God and because of his power, and no one was able to enter the sanctuary until the seven plagues of the seven angels were finished.

^ Rev. 15:3 See App. A5.

^ Rev. 15:4 See App. A5.

Revelation  17 : 1 - 18

17 One of the seven angels who had the seven bowls came and said to me: “Come, I will show you the judgment on the great prostitute who sits on many waters, ^2 with whom the kings of the earth committed sexual immorality,[*] and earth’s inhabitants were made drunk with the wine of her sexual immorality.”[*]

^3 And he carried me away in the power of the spirit into a wilderness. And I saw a woman sitting on a scarlet-colored wild beast that was full of blasphemous names and that had seven heads and ten horns. ^4 The woman was clothed in purple and scarlet, and she was adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls, and she had in her hand a golden cup that was full of disgusting things and the unclean things of her sexual immorality.[*] ^5 On her forehead was written a name, a mystery: “Babylon the Great, the mother of the prostitutes and of the disgusting things of the earth.” ^6 And I saw that the woman was drunk with the blood of the holy ones and with the blood of the witnesses of Jesus.

Well, on seeing her I was greatly amazed. ^7 So the angel said to me: “Why is it that you were amazed? I will tell you the mystery of the woman and of the wild beast that is carrying her and that has the seven heads and the ten horns: ^8 The wild beast that you saw was, but is not, and yet is about to ascend out of the abyss, and it is to go off into destruction. And the inhabitants of the earth—those whose names have not been written in the scroll of life from the founding of the world—will be amazed when they see how the wild beast was, but is not, and yet will be present.

^9 “This calls for a mind[*] that has wisdom: The seven heads mean seven mountains, where the woman sits on top. ^10 And there are seven kings: Five have fallen, one is, and the other has not yet arrived; but when he does arrive, he must remain a short while. ^11 And the wild beast that was but is not, it is also an eighth king, but it springs from the seven, and it goes off into destruction.

^12 “The ten horns that you saw mean ten kings who have not yet received a kingdom, but they do receive authority as kings for one hour with the wild beast. ^13 These have one thought, so they give their power and authority to the wild beast. ^14 These will battle with the Lamb, but because he is Lord of lords and King of kings, the Lamb will conquer them. Also, those with him who are called and chosen and faithful will do so.”

^15 He said to me: “The waters that you saw, where the prostitute is sitting, mean peoples and crowds and nations and tongues.[*] ^16 And the ten horns that you saw and the wild beast, these will hate the prostitute and will make her devastated and naked, and they will eat up her flesh and completely burn her with fire. ^17 For God put it into their hearts to carry out his thought, yes, to carry out their one thought by giving their kingdom to the wild beast, until the words of God will have been accomplished. ^18 And the woman whom you saw means the great city that has a kingdom over the kings of the earth.”

^ Rev. 17:2 See Glossary.

^ Rev. 17:2 Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 17:4 Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 17:9 Or “for intelligence.”

^ Rev. 17:15 Or “languages.”

Revelation  18 : 1 - 24

18 After this I saw another angel descending from heaven with great authority, and the earth was illuminated by his glory. ^2 And he cried out with a strong voice, saying: “She has fallen! Babylon the Great has fallen, and she has become a dwelling place of demons and a place where every unclean spirit[*] and every unclean and hated bird lurks! ^3 For because of the wine of the passion[*] of her sexual immorality,[*] all the nations have fallen victim, and the kings of the earth committed sexual immorality with her, and the merchants[*] of the earth became rich owing to the power of her shameless luxury.”

^4 And I heard another voice out of heaven say: “Get out of her, my people, if you do not want to share with her in her sins, and if you do not want to receive part of her plagues. ^5 For her sins have massed together clear up to heaven, and God has called her acts of injustice[*] to mind. ^6 Repay her in the way she treated others, yes, pay her back double for the things she has done; in the cup she has mixed, mix a double portion for her. ^7 To the extent that she glorified herself and lived in shameless luxury, to that extent give her torment and mourning. For she keeps saying in her heart: ‘I sit as queen, and I am not a widow, and I will never see mourning.’ ^8 That is why in one day her plagues will come, death and mourning and famine, and she will be completely burned with fire, because Jehovah[*] God, who judged her, is strong.

^9 “And the kings of the earth who committed sexual immorality[*] with her and lived with her in shameless luxury will weep and beat themselves in grief over her when they see the smoke from her burning. ^10 They will stand at a distance because of their fear of her torment and say: ‘Too bad, too bad, you great city, Babylon you strong city, because in one hour your judgment has arrived!’

^11 “Also, the merchants of the earth are weeping and mourning over her, because there is no one to buy their full cargo anymore, ^12 a full cargo of gold, silver, precious stones, pearls, fine linen, purple cloth, silk, and scarlet cloth; and everything made from scented wood; and every sort of object made from ivory, and from precious wood, copper, iron, and marble; ^13 also cinnamon, Indian spice, incense, perfumed oil, frankincense, wine, olive oil, fine flour, wheat, cattle, sheep, horses, carriages, slaves, and human lives.[*] ^14 Yes, the fine fruit that you[*] desired has left you, and all the delicacies and the splendid things have vanished from you, never to be found again.

^15 “The merchants who sold these things, who became rich from her, will stand at a distance because of their fear of her torment and will weep and mourn, ^16 saying: ‘Too bad, too bad, the great city, clothed with fine linen, purple, and scarlet and richly adorned with gold ornaments, precious stones, and pearls, ^17 because in one hour such great riches have been devastated!’

“And every ship captain and every seafaring person and sailors and all those who make a living by the sea stood at a distance ^18 and cried out as they looked at the smoke from her burning and said: ‘What city is like the great city?’ ^19 They threw dust on their heads and cried out, weeping and mourning, and said: ‘Too bad, too bad, the great city, in which all those who had ships at sea became rich from her wealth, because in one hour she has been devastated!’

^20 “Be glad over her, O heaven, also you holy ones and apostles and prophets, because God has pronounced his judgment on her in your behalf!”

^21 And a strong angel lifted up a stone like a great millstone and hurled it into the sea, saying: “Thus with a swift pitch will Babylon the great city be hurled down, and she will never be found again. ^22 And the sound of singers who accompany themselves on the harp, of musicians, of flutists, and of trumpeters will never be heard in you again. And no craftsman who practices any trade will ever be found in you again, and no sound of a millstone will ever be heard in you again. ^23 No light of a lamp will ever shine in you again, and no voice of a bridegroom and of a bride will ever be heard in you again; for your merchants were the top-ranking men of the earth, and by your spiritistic practices all the nations were misled. ^24 Yes, in her was found the blood of prophets and of holy ones and of all those who have been slaughtered on the earth.”

^ Rev. 18:2 Or possibly, “breath; exhalation; inspired statement.”

^ Rev. 18:3 Or “anger.”

^ Rev. 18:3 Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 18:3 Or “traveling merchants.”

^ Rev. 18:5 Or “her crimes.”

^ Rev. 18:8 See App. A5.

^ Rev. 18:9 See Glossary.

^ Rev. 18:13 Or “souls.”

^ Rev. 18:14 Or “your soul.”

Revelation  19 : 1 - 21

19 After this I heard what seemed to be a loud voice of a great crowd in heaven. They said: “Praise Jah![*] The salvation and the glory and the power belong to our God, ^2 because his judgments are true and righteous. For he has executed judgment on the great prostitute who corrupted the earth with her sexual immorality,[*] and he has avenged the blood of his slaves that is on her hands.”[*] ^3 And right away for the second time they said: “Praise Jah![*] And the smoke from her goes on ascending forever and ever.”

^4 And the 24 elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshipped God who sits on the throne and said: “Amen! Praise Jah!”[*]

^5 Also, a voice came from the throne and said: “Be praising our God, all you his slaves, who fear him, the small ones and the great.”

^6 And I heard what sounded like a voice of a great crowd and like the sound of many waters and like the sound of heavy thunders. They said: “Praise Jah,[*] because Jehovah[*] our God, the Almighty, has begun to rule as king! ^7 Let us rejoice and be overjoyed and give him glory, because the marriage of the Lamb has arrived and his wife has prepared herself. ^8 Yes, it has been granted to her to be clothed with bright, clean, fine linen—for the fine linen stands for the righteous acts of the holy ones.”

^9 And he tells me, “Write: Happy are those invited to the evening meal of the Lamb’s marriage.” Also, he tells me: “These are the true sayings of God.” ^10 At that I fell down before his feet to worship him. But he tells me: “Be careful! Do not do that! I am only a fellow slave of you and of your brothers who have the work of witnessing concerning Jesus. Worship God! For the witness concerning Jesus is what inspires prophecy.”

^11 I saw heaven opened, and look! a white horse. And the one seated on it is called Faithful and True, and he judges and carries on war in righteousness. ^12 His eyes are a fiery flame, and on his head are many diadems.[*] He has a name written that no one knows but he himself, ^13 and he is clothed with an outer garment stained[*] with blood, and he is called by the name The Word of God. ^14 Also, the armies in heaven were following him on white horses, and they were clothed in white, clean, fine linen. ^15 And out of his mouth protrudes a sharp, long sword with which to strike the nations, and he will shepherd them with a rod of iron. Moreover, he treads the winepress of the fury of the wrath of God the Almighty. ^16 On his outer garment, yes, on his thigh, he has a name written, King of kings and Lord of lords.

^17 I saw also an angel standing in the sun, and he cried out with a loud voice and said to all the birds that fly in midheaven:[*] “Come here, be gathered together to the great evening meal of God, ^18 so that you may eat the flesh of kings and the flesh of military commanders and the flesh of strong men and the flesh of horses and of those seated on them, and the flesh of all, of freemen as well as of slaves and of small ones and great.”

^19 And I saw the wild beast and the kings of the earth and their armies gathered together to wage war against the one seated on the horse and against his army. ^20 And the wild beast was caught, and along with it the false prophet that performed in front of it the signs with which he misled those who received the mark of the wild beast and those who worship its image. While still alive, they both were hurled into the fiery lake that burns with sulfur. ^21 But the rest were killed off with the long sword that proceeded out of the mouth of the one seated on the horse. And all the birds were filled with their flesh.

^ Rev. 19:1 Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ Rev. 19:2 Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 19:2 Lit., “from her hand.”

^ Rev. 19:3 Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ Rev. 19:4 Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ Rev. 19:6 Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ Rev. 19:6 See App. A5.

^ Rev. 19:12 Or “royal headbands.”

^ Rev. 19:13 Or possibly, “sprinkled.”

^ Rev. 19:17 Or “in midair; overhead.”

Revelation  20 : 1 - 15

20 And I saw an angel coming down out of heaven with the key of the abyss and a great chain in his hand. ^2 He seized the dragon, the original serpent, who is the Devil and Satan, and bound him for 1,000 years. ^3 And he hurled him into the abyss and shut it and sealed it over him, so that he would not mislead the nations anymore until the 1,000 years were ended. After this he must be released for a little while.

^4 And I saw thrones, and those who sat on them were given authority to judge. Yes, I saw the souls[*] of those executed[*] for the witness they gave about Jesus and for speaking about God, and those who had not worshipped the wild beast or its image and had not received the mark on their forehead and on their hand. And they came to life and ruled as kings with the Christ for 1,000 years. ^5 (The rest of the dead did not come to life until the 1,000 years were ended.) This is the first resurrection. ^6 Happy and holy is anyone having part in the first resurrection; over these the second death has no authority, but they will be priests of God and of the Christ, and they will rule as kings with him for the 1,000 years.

^7 Now as soon as the 1,000 years have ended, Satan will be released from his prison, ^8 and he will go out to mislead those nations in the four corners of the earth, Gog and Maʹgog, to gather them together for the war. The number of these is as the sand of the sea. ^9 And they advanced over the whole earth and encircled the camp of the holy ones and the beloved city. But fire came down out of heaven and consumed them. ^10 And the Devil who was misleading them was hurled into the lake of fire and sulfur, where both the wild beast and the false prophet already were; and they will be tormented[*] day and night forever and ever.

^11 And I saw a great white throne and the One seated on it. From before him the earth and the heaven fled away, and no place was found for them. ^12 And I saw the dead, the great and the small, standing before the throne, and scrolls were opened. But another scroll was opened; it is the scroll of life. The dead were judged out of those things written in the scrolls according to their deeds. ^13 And the sea gave up the dead in it, and death and the Grave[*] gave up the dead in them, and they were judged individually according to their deeds. ^14 And death and the Grave[*] were hurled into the lake of fire. This means the second death, the lake of fire. ^15 Furthermore, whoever was not found written in the book of life was hurled into the lake of fire.

^ Rev. 20:4 See Glossary and Re 6:9 ftn.

^ Rev. 20:4 Lit., “executed with the ax.”

^ Rev. 20:10 Or “restrained; imprisoned.”

^ Rev. 20:13 Or “Hades,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ Rev. 20:14 Or “Hades,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Revelation  21 : 1 - 27

21 And I saw a new heaven and a new earth; for the former heaven and the former earth had passed away, and the sea is no more. ^2 I also saw the holy city, New Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God and prepared as a bride adorned for her husband. ^3 With that I heard a loud voice from the throne say: “Look! The tent of God is with mankind, and he will reside with them, and they will be his people. And God himself will be with them. ^4 And he will wipe out every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.”

^5 And the One seated on the throne said: “Look! I am making all things new.” Also he says: “Write, for these words are faithful[*] and true.” ^6 And he said to me: “They have come to pass! I am the Alʹpha and the O·meʹga,[*] the beginning and the end. To anyone thirsting I will give from the spring[*] of the water of life free.[*] ^7 Anyone conquering will inherit these things, and I will be his God and he will be my son. ^8 But as for the cowards and those without faith and those who are disgusting in their filth and murderers and the sexually immoral[*] and those practicing spiritism and idolaters and all the liars, their portion will be in the lake that burns with fire and sulfur. This means the second death.”

^9 One of the seven angels who had the seven bowls that were full of the seven last plagues came and said to me: “Come, and I will show you the bride, the Lamb’s wife.” ^10 So he carried me away in the power of the spirit to a great and lofty mountain, and he showed me the holy city Jerusalem coming down out of heaven from God ^11 and having the glory of God. Its radiance was like a most precious stone, like a jasper stone shining crystal clear. ^12 It had a great and lofty wall and had 12 gates with 12 angels at the gates, and on the gates were inscribed the names of the 12 tribes of the sons of Israel. ^13 On the east were three gates, and on the north three gates, and on the south three gates, and on the west three gates. ^14 The wall of the city also had 12 foundation stones, and on them were the 12 names of the 12 apostles of the Lamb.

^15 Now the one who was speaking with me was holding a golden reed as a measure in order to measure the city and its gates and its wall. ^16 And the city is laid out as a square, and its length is as great as its width. And he measured the city with the reed, 12,000 stadia;[*] its length and width and height are equal. ^17 He also measured its wall, 144 cubits[*] according to a man’s measure, at the same time an angel’s measure. ^18 Now the wall was made of jasper, and the city was pure gold like clear glass. ^19 The foundations of the city wall were adorned with every sort of precious stone: the first foundation was jasper, the second sapphire, the third chal·ceʹdo·ny, the fourth emerald, ^20 the fifth sar·donʹyx, the sixth sardius, the seventh chrysʹo·lite, the eighth beryl, the ninth topaz, the tenth chrysʹo·prase, the eleventh hyacinth, the twelfth amethyst. ^21 Also, the 12 gates were 12 pearls; each one of the gates was made of one pearl. And the main street of the city was pure gold, like transparent glass.

^22 I did not see a temple in it, for Jehovah[*] God the Almighty is its temple, also the Lamb is. ^23 And the city has no need of the sun nor of the moon to shine on it, for the glory of God illuminated it, and its lamp was the Lamb. ^24 And the nations will walk by means of its light, and the kings of the earth will bring their glory into it. ^25 Its gates will not be closed at all by day, for night will not exist there. ^26 And they will bring the glory and the honor of the nations into it. ^27 But anything defiled and anyone who does what is disgusting and deceitful will in no way enter into it; only those written in the Lamb’s scroll of life will enter.

^ Rev. 21:5 Or “trustworthy.”

^ Rev. 21:6 Or “the A and the Z.” Alpha and Omega are the first and last letters of the Greek alphabet.

^ Rev. 21:6 Or “fountain.”

^ Rev. 21:6 Or “without cost.”

^ Rev. 21:8 See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

^ Rev. 21:16 About 2,220 km (1,379 mi). A stadium equaled 185 m (606.95 ft). See App. B14.

^ Rev. 21:17 About 64 m (210 ft). See App. B14.

^ Rev. 21:22 See App. A5.

Revelation  22 : 1 - 21

22 And he showed me a river of water of life, clear as crystal, flowing out from the throne of God and of the Lamb ^2 down the middle of its main street. On both sides of the river were trees of life producing 12 crops of fruit, yielding their fruit each month. And the leaves of the trees were for the healing of the nations.

^3 And there will no longer be any curse. But the throne of God and of the Lamb will be in the city, and his slaves will offer him sacred service; ^4 and they will see his face, and his name will be on their foreheads. ^5 Also, night will be no more, and they have no need of lamplight or sunlight, for Jehovah[*] God will shed light upon them, and they will rule as kings forever and ever.

^6 He said to me: “These words are faithful[*] and true; yes, Jehovah,[*] the God who inspired the prophets, has sent his angel to show his slaves the things that must shortly take place. ^7 Look! I am coming quickly. Happy is anyone observing the words of the prophecy of this scroll.”

^8 Well I, John, was the one hearing and seeing these things. When I heard and saw them, I fell down to worship at the feet of the angel who had been showing me these things. ^9 But he tells me: “Be careful! Do not do that! I am only a fellow slave of you and of your brothers the prophets and of those observing the words of this scroll. Worship God.”

^10 He also tells me: “Do not seal up the words of the prophecy of this scroll, for the appointed time is near. ^11 Let the one who is unrighteous continue in unrighteousness, and let the filthy one continue in his filth; but let the righteous one continue in righteousness, and let the holy one continue in holiness.

^12 “‘Look! I am coming quickly, and the reward I give is with me, to repay each one according to his work. ^13 I am the Alʹpha and the O·meʹga,[*] the first and the last, the beginning and the end. ^14 Happy are those who wash their robes, so that they may have authority to go to the trees of life and that they may gain entrance into the city through its gates. ^15 Outside are the dogs[*] and those who practice spiritism and those who are sexually immoral[*] and the murderers and the idolaters and everyone who loves and practices lying.’

^16 “‘I, Jesus, sent my angel to bear witness to you about these things for the congregations. I am the root and the offspring of David and the bright morning star.’”

^17 And the spirit and the bride keep on saying, “Come!” and let anyone hearing say, “Come!” and let anyone thirsting come; let anyone who wishes take life’s water free.

^18 “I am bearing witness to everyone who hears the words of the prophecy of this scroll: If anyone makes an addition to these things, God will add to him the plagues that are written in this scroll; ^19 and if anyone takes anything away from the words of the scroll of this prophecy, God will take his portion away from the trees of life and out of the holy city, things that are written about in this scroll.

^20 “The one who bears witness of these things says, ‘Yes, I am coming quickly.’”

“Amen! Come, Lord Jesus.”

^21 May the undeserved kindness of the Lord Jesus be with the holy ones.

^ Rev. 22:5 See App. A5.

^ Rev. 22:6 Or “trustworthy.”

^ Rev. 22:6 See App. A5.

^ Rev. 22:13 Or “the A and the Z.” Alpha and Omega are the first and last letters of the Greek alphabet.

^ Rev. 22:15 That is, those whose practices are disgusting in God’s eyes.

^ Rev. 22:15 See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

Glossary of Bible Terms

A B C D E F G H I J L M N O P Q R S T U V W Y Z

A

Ab.

After the Babylonian exile, the name of the 5th month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the 11th month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-July to mid-August. It is not mentioned by name in the Bible; it is simply referred to as “the fifth month.” (Nu 33:38; Ezr 7:9)—See App. B15.

Abib.

The original name of the first month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the seventh month of the secular calendar. It means “Green Ears (of Grain)” and ran from mid-March to mid-April. After the Jews’ return from Babylon, it was called Nisan. (De 16:1)—See App. B15.

Abyss.

From the Greek word aʹbys·sos, meaning “exceedingly deep” or “unfathomable, boundless.” It is used in the Christian Greek Scriptures to refer to a place or condition of confinement. It includes the grave but is not limited to it.—Lu 8:31; Ro 10:7; Re 20:3.

Achaia.

In the Christian Greek Scriptures, the Roman province of southern Greece with its capital at Corinth. Achaia included all of the Peloponnese and the central part of continental Greece. (Ac 18:12)—See App. B13.

Adar.

After the Babylonian exile, the name of the 12th month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the 6th month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-February to mid-March. (Es 3:7)—See App. B15.

Adultery.

Voluntary sexual intercourse by a married man or woman with someone other than his or her mate.—Ex 20:14; Mt 5:27; 19:9.

Alabaster.

The name of small perfume jars originally made of a stone found near Alabastron, Egypt. Such containers were usually made with a narrow neck that could be sealed to prevent any of the precious perfume from leaking. The stone itself also came to be known by the same name.—Mr 14:3.

Alamoth.

A musical term meaning “Maidens; Young Women,” probably alluding to the soprano voices of young women. It was likely used to indicate that a musical piece or accompaniment was to be executed at a high register.—1Ch 15:20; Ps 46:Sup.

Alpha and Omega.

Names of the first and last letters of the Greek alphabet; they are used together three times in Revelation as a title for God. In these contexts this expression means the same as “the first and the last” and “the beginning and the end.”—Re 1:8; 21:6; 22:13.

Altar.

A raised structure or platform made of dirt, rocks, a block of stone, or wood covered with metal on which sacrifices or incense were offered in worship. In the first room of the tabernacle and of the temple, there was a small “altar of gold” for offering incense. It was made of wood covered with gold. A larger “altar of copper” for burnt sacrifices was located outside in the courtyard. (Ex 27:1; 39:38, 39; Ge 8:20; 1Ki 6:20; 2Ch 4:1; Lu 1:11)—See App. B5 and B8.

Amen.

“So be it,” or “surely.” The word comes from the Hebrew root word ʼa·manʹ, which means “to be faithful, trustworthy.” “Amen” was said in agreement to an oath, a prayer, or a statement. In Revelation, it is used as a title for Jesus.—De 27:26; 1Ch 16:36; Re 3:14.

Angels.

From the Hebrew mal·ʼakhʹ and the Greek agʹge·los. Both words literally mean “messenger” but are rendered “angel” when referring to spirit messengers. (Ge 16:7; 32:3; Jas 2:25; Re 22:8) Angels are powerful spirit creatures, created by God long before the creation of mankind. They are also referred to in the Bible as “holy myriads,” “sons of God,” and “morning stars.” (De 33:2; Job 1:6; 38:7) They were not made with the ability to reproduce their own kind but were created individually. They number well over a hundred million. (Da 7:10) The Bible indicates that they have personal names and distinct personalities, yet they humbly refuse to receive worship, and most even avoid disclosing their names. (Ge 32:29; Lu 1:26; Re 22:8, 9) They have different ranks and are assigned a variety of roles, including serving before Jehovah’s throne, conveying his messages, intervening in behalf of Jehovah’s earthly servants, executing God’s judgments, and supporting the preaching of the good news. (2Ki 19:35; Ps 34:7; Lu 1:30, 31; Re 5:11; 14:6) In the future they will support Jesus in fighting the battle of Armageddon.—Re 19:14, 15.

Anoint.

The Hebrew word basically means “to smear with liquid.” Oil was applied to a person or an object to symbolize dedication to a special service. In the Christian Greek Scriptures, the word is also used of the pouring out of holy spirit on those chosen for the heavenly hope.—Ex 28:41; 1Sa 16:13; 2Co 1:21.

Antichrist.

The Greek term has a twofold meaning. It refers to that which is anti, or opposed to, Christ. It may also refer to a false Christ, one in the place of Christ. All people, organizations, or groups that falsely claim to represent Christ or claim to be the Messiah or that oppose Christ and his disciples can properly be called antichrists.—1Jo 2:22.

Apostasy.

This term in Greek (a·po·sta·siʹa) comes from a verb literally meaning “to stand away from.” The noun has the sense of “desertion, abandonment, or rebellion.” In the Christian Greek Scriptures, “apostasy” is used primarily with regard to those who defect from true worship.—Pr 11:9; Ac 21:21; 2Th 2:3.

Apostle.

The basic sense of the word is “one sent forth,” and it is used of Jesus and certain ones who were sent to serve others. Most frequently, it is used with regard to the disciples whom Jesus personally selected as a group of 12 appointed representatives.—Mr 3:14; Ac 14:14.

Aram; Aramaeans.

Descendants of Shem’s son Aram who mainly lived in regions from the Lebanon Mountains across to Mesopotamia and from the Taurus Mountains in the north down to Damascus and beyond in the south. This area, called Aram in Hebrew, was later referred to as Syria, and its inhabitants were referred to as Syrians.—Ge 25:20; De 26:5; Ho 12:12.

Aramaic.

A Semitic language closely related to Hebrew, using the same alphabet. It was originally spoken by the Aramaeans but later became the international language of trade and communication in the Assyrian and Babylonian empires. It was also the official administrative language of the Persian Empire. (Ezr 4:7) Parts of the books of Ezra, Jeremiah, and Daniel were written in Aramaic.—Ezr 4:8–6:18; 7:12-26; Jer 10:11; Da 2:4b–7:28.

Archangel.

Meaning “chief of the angels.” The prefix “arch” means “chief” or “principal.” This definition, coupled with the fact that “archangel” in the Bible is used only in the singular, indicates that there is just one archangel. The Bible gives the name of the archangel, identifying him as Michael.—Da 12:1; Jude 9; Re 12:7.

Areopagus.

A high hill in Athens, north-west of the Acropolis. It was also the name of the council (court) that held meetings there. Paul was brought to the Areopagus by Stoic and Epicurean philosophers to explain his beliefs.—Ac 17:19.

Ark of the covenant.

The chest made of acacia wood and overlaid with gold, which was kept in the Most Holy of the tabernacle and later in the Most Holy of the temple built by Solomon. It had a solid gold cover with two cherubs facing each other. Its principal contents were the two tablets of the Ten Commandments. (De 31:26; 1Ki 6:19; Heb 9:4)—See App. B5 and B8.

Armageddon.

From the Hebrew Har Meghid·dohnʹ, meaning “Mountain of Megiddo.” The word is associated with “the war of the great day of God the Almighty” in which “the kings of the entire inhabited earth” gather to wage war against Jehovah. (Re 16:14, 16; 19:11-21)—See GREAT TRIBULATION.

Armor.

The protective clothing worn by soldiers, namely, helmet, coat of mail, belt, shin guards, and shield.—1Sa 31:9; Eph 6:13-17.

Aselgeia.—

See BRAZEN CONDUCT.

Ashtoreth.

A Canaanite goddess of war and fertility, the wife of Baal.—1Sa 7:3.

Asia.

In the Christian Greek Scriptures, the name of the Roman province that included what is today the western part of Turkey, as well as some coastal islands, such as Samos and Patmos. The capital was Ephesus. (Ac 20:16; Re 1:4)—See App. B13.

Assembly.

A group of people gathered by appointment. In the Hebrew Scriptures, this word often refers to gatherings of the people of Israel at religious festivals or at events of great national significance.—De 16:8; 1Ki 8:5.

Astrologer.

A person who studies the movements of the sun, moon, and stars in order to predict future events.—Da 2:27; Mt 2:1.

Atonement.

In the Hebrew Scriptures, the concept was connected with sacrifices that were made to allow people to approach God and worship him. Under the Mosaic Law, sacrifices were made, particularly on the annual Day of Atonement, in order to effect reconciliation with God despite the sins of individuals and of the whole nation. Those sacrifices pointed to Jesus’ sacrifice, which completely atoned for mankind’s sins once for all time, giving people the opportunity to be reconciled to Jehovah.—Le 5:10; 23:28; Col 1:20; Heb 9:12.

Azazel.

A Hebrew name that possibly means “Goat That Disappears.” On the Day of Atonement, the goat designated for Azazel was sent into the wilderness, symbolically carrying off the nation’s sins of the past year.—Le 16:8, 10.

B

Baal.

A Canaanite god regarded as the owner of the sky and giver of rains and fertility. “Baal” was also used as a designation for local lesser gods. The Hebrew word means “Owner; Master.”—1Ki 18:21; Ro 11:4.

Baptism; Baptize.

The verb means “to immerse,” or dip under water. Jesus made baptism a requirement for his followers. The Scriptures also refer to John’s baptism, baptism with holy spirit, and baptism with fire, among others.—Mt 3:11, 16; 28:19; Joh 3:23; 1Pe 3:21.

Bath.

A liquid measure that is estimated to equal about 22 L (5.81 gal), according to archaeological findings of jar fragments bearing this name. Most of the other dry and liquid measures in the Bible are calculated in relation to the estimated volume of the bath measure. (1Ki 7:38; Eze 45:14)—See App. B14.

Beelzebub.

A designation applied to Satan, the prince, or ruler, of the demons. It is possibly an alteration of Baal-zebub, the Baal worshipped by the Philistines at Ekron.—2Ki 1:3; Mt 12:24.

Brazen conduct.

From the Greek a·selʹgei·a, a phrase pertaining to acts that are serious violations of God’s laws and that reflect a brazen or boldly contemptuous attitude; a spirit that betrays disrespect or even contempt for authority, laws, and standards. The expression does not refer to wrong conduct of a minor nature.—Ga 5:19; 2Pe 2:7.

Breastpiece.

The jewel-studded pouch worn by Israel’s high priest over his heart whenever he entered the Holy. It was called “the breastpiece of judgment” because it contained the Urim and the Thummim, which were used in revealing Jehovah’s judgments. (Ex 28:15-30)—See App. B5.

Brother-in-law marriage.

A custom, later incorporated into the Mosaic Law, whereby a man would marry the sonless widow of his deceased brother in order to produce children to carry on his brother’s line. Also known as levirate marriage.—Ge 38:8; De 25:5.

Bul.

The name of the eighth month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the second month of the secular calendar. It comes from a root meaning “yield; produce” and ran from mid-October to mid-November. (1Ki 6:38)—See App. B15.

Burnt offering.

An animal sacrifice that was burned on the altar as a total offering to God; no part of the animal (bull, ram, male goat, turtledove, or young pigeon) was kept by the worshipper.—Ex 29:18; Le 6:9.

C

Cab.

A dry measure of 1.22 L (1.11 dry qt), based on the estimated volume of the bath measure. (2Ki 6:25)—See App. B14.

Caesar.

A Roman family name that became a title for the Roman emperors. Augustus, Tiberius, and Claudius are mentioned by name in the Bible, and though Nero is not mentioned by name, it applies to him as well. “Caesar” is also used in the Christian Greek Scriptures to represent civil authority, or the State.—Mr 12:17; Ac 25:12.

Canaan.

A grandson of Noah, and the fourth son of Ham. The 11 tribes that descended from Canaan eventually inhabited the region along the eastern Mediterranean between Egypt and Syria. That area was called “the land of Canaan.” (Le 18:3; Ge 9:18; Ac 13:19)—See App. B4.

Capital.

The ornamental top of a column. Massive capitals topped the twin columns Jachin and Boaz, which stood in front of Solomon’s temple. (1Ki 7:16)—See App. B8.

Cassia.

A product from the cassia bark tree (Cinnamomum cassia), which is of the same family as the cinnamon tree. Cassia was used as a perfume and as an ingredient of the holy anointing oil.—Ex 30:24; Ps 45:8; Eze 27:19.

Chaff.

The husks that are separated from the edible portion of grain during threshing and winnowing. Chaff is used in figures of speech as a symbol of something worthless and undesirable.—Ps 1:4; Mt 3:12.

Chaldea; Chaldeans.

Originally the land and people occupying the delta area of the Tigris and Euphrates rivers; in time the terms were used for all of Babylonia and its people. “Chaldeans” also referred to an educated class of people who studied science, history, languages, and astronomy but who practiced magic and astrology as well.—Ezr 5:12; Da 4:7; Ac 7:4.

Chariot.

A two-wheeled, horse-drawn vehicle used primarily in war.—Ex 14:23; Jg 4:13; Ac 8:28.

Chemosh.

The chief god of the Moabites.—1Ki 11:33.

Cherubs.

Angels of high rank having special duties. They are different from seraphs.—Ge 3:24; Ex 25:20; Isa 37:16; Heb 9:5.

Chief Agent.

The Greek term basically means “Chief Leader.” It refers to the essential role of Jesus Christ in freeing faithful humans from the deadly effects of sin and in leading them to everlasting life.—Ac 3:15; 5:31; Heb 2:10; 12:2.

Chief priest.

An alternate term for “high priest” in the Hebrew Scriptures. In the Christian Greek Scriptures, the expression “chief priests” evidently denoted the principal men of the priesthood, possibly including any deposed high priests and the heads of the 24 priestly divisions.—2Ch 26:20; Ezr 7:5; Mt 2:4; Mr 8:31.

Chislev.

After the Jews’ return from Babylon, the name of the ninth month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the third month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-November to mid-December. (Ne 1:1; Zec 7:1)—See App. B15.

Christ.

The title of Jesus, from the Greek word Khri·stosʹ, which is equivalent to the Hebrew word translated “Messiah,” or “Anointed One.”—Mt 1:16; Joh 1:41.

Christian.

A God-given name for the followers of Jesus Christ.—Ac 11:26; 26:28.

Circumcision.

The removal of the foreskin of the male genital organ. The procedure was made mandatory for Abraham and his descendants, but it is not a requirement for Christians. It is also used figuratively in a variety of contexts.—Ge 17:10; 1Co 7:19; Php 3:3.

Cities of refuge.

Levite cities where an unintentional manslayer could seek asylum from the avenger of blood. Six such cities, spread throughout the Promised Land, were appointed by Moses and later by Joshua, under Jehovah’s direction. Upon reaching a city of refuge, the fugitive stated his case to the elders at the city gate and was received hospitably. To prevent willful murderers from taking advantage of this provision, the asylum seeker had to stand trial in the city where the killing took place in order to prove his innocence. If proved innocent, he was returned to the city of refuge, where he had to stay within its boundaries for the rest of his life or until the death of the high priest.—Nu 35:6, 11-15, 22-29; Jos 20:2-8.

City of David.

The name given to the city of Jebus after David conquered it and built his royal residence there. It is also called Zion. It is the southeastern part as well as the oldest part of Jerusalem.—2Sa 5:7; 1Ch 11:4, 5.

Clean.

Biblically, this word refers not only to physical cleanliness but also to maintaining or restoring to a condition that is without blemish, spotless, and free from anything that soils, adulterates, or corrupts in a moral or spiritual way. Under the Mosaic Law, the word refers to being ceremonially clean.—Le 10:10; Ps 51:7; Mt 8:2; 1Co 6:11.

Communion offering.

A sacrifice presented to Jehovah as a request for peace with him. The worshipper and his household, the officiating priest, and the priests on duty all partook of it. Jehovah received, as it were, the pleasing smoke of the burning fat. The blood, representing the life, was also given to him. It was as if the priests and the worshippers sat at the meal together with Jehovah, signifying a peaceful relationship.—Le 7:29, 32; De 27:7.

Conclusion of the system of things.

The period of time leading up to the end of the system of things, or state of affairs, dominated by Satan. It runs concurrently with Christ’s presence. Under the direction of Jesus, angels will “separate the wicked from among the righteous” and destroy them. (Mt 13:40-42, 49) Jesus’ disciples were interested in the timing of that “conclusion.” (Mt 24:3) Before his return to heaven, he promised his followers that he would be with them until that time.—Mt 28:20.

Concubine.

A secondary wife who was often a slave girl.—Ex 21:8; 2Sa 5:13; 1Ki 11:3.

Congregation.

A group of people gathered together for a particular purpose or activity. In the Hebrew Scriptures, it generally refers to the nation of Israel. In the Christian Greek Scriptures, it refers to individual congregations of Christians but more often to the Christian congregation in general.—1Ki 8:22; Ac 9:31; Ro 16:5.

Cor.

A dry and a liquid measure. It equaled 220 L (58.1 gal/200 dry qt), based on the estimated volume of the bath measure. (1Ki 5:11)—See App. B14.

Coral.

A hard, stonelike substance that is formed from the skeletons of tiny sea animals. It is found in the ocean in a variety of colors, including red, white, and black. Corals were especially plentiful in the Red Sea. In Bible times, red coral was highly prized and was made into beads and other ornaments.—Pr 8:11.

Cornerstone.

A stone placed at the angle, or corner, of a building where two walls meet, important in joining and binding them together. The principal cornerstone was the foundation cornerstone; a particularly strong one was generally chosen for public buildings and city walls. The word is used in a figurative sense for the founding of the earth, and Jesus is spoken of as “the foundation cornerstone” of the Christian congregation, which is likened to a spiritual house.—Eph 2:20; Job 38:6.

Courtyard.

The fenced, open area surrounding the tabernacle, and later one of the walled, open-air yards around the main building of the temple. The altar of burnt offering was located in the courtyard of the tabernacle and in the inner courtyard of the temple. (See App. B5, B8, B11.) The Bible also mentions courtyards in connection with houses and palaces.—Ex 8:13; 27:9; 1Ki 7:12; Es 4:11; Mt 26:3.

Covenant.

A formal agreement, or contract, between God and humans or between two human parties to do or refrain from doing something. Sometimes only one party was responsible to carry out the terms (a unilateral covenant, which was essentially a promise). At other times both parties had terms to carry out (a bilateral covenant). Besides covenants made by God with humans, the Bible mentions covenants between men, tribes, nations, or groups of people. Among the covenants that have had a far-reaching effect are those that God made with Abraham, David, the nation of Israel (Law covenant), and the Israel of God (new covenant).—Ge 9:11; 15:18; 21:27; Ex 24:7; 2Ch 21:7.

Cubit.

A linear measure roughly the distance from the elbow to the tip of the middle finger. The Israelites commonly used a cubit of about 44.5 cm (17.5 in.), but they also used a larger cubit that was one handbreadth longer, about 51.8 cm (20.4 in.). (Ge 6:15; Lu 12:25)—See App. B14.

Curse.

To threaten or pronounce evil on someone or something. It is not to be confused with profanity or with violent anger. A curse is often a formal declaration of a pronouncement or prediction of evil, and when made by God or by an authorized person, it has a prophetic value and force.—Ge 12:3; Nu 22:12; Ga 3:10.

Curtain.

The beautifully woven piece of fabric embroidered with figures of cherubs that separated the Holy from the Most Holy in both the tabernacle and the temple. (Ex 26:31; 2Ch 3:14; Mt 27:51; Heb 9:3)—See App. B5.

D

Dagon.

A god of the Philistines. The etymology of the word is uncertain, but some scholars associate it with the Hebrew word dagh (fish).—Jg 16:23; 1Sa 5:4.

Daric.

A Persian gold coin weighing 8.4 g (0.27 oz t). (1Ch 29:7)—See App. B14.

Day of Atonement.

The most important holy day for the Israelites, also called Yom Kippur (from Hebrew yohm hak·kip·pu·rimʹ, “day of the coverings”), held on Ethanim 10. This was the only day of the year on which the high priest went into the Most Holy of the tabernacle and later of the temple. There he offered the blood of the sacrifices for his sins, the sins of the other Levites, and the sins of the people. It was a time of holy convention and fasting, and it was also a sabbath, a time to abstain from regular work.—Le 23:27, 28.

Daystar.

Similar in meaning to “morning star.” It is the last star to rise on the eastern horizon before the sun appears, thus heralding the dawn of a new day.—Re 22:16; 2Pe 1:19.

Decapolis.

A group of Greek cities, originally made up of ten cities (from Greek deʹka, meaning “ten,” and poʹlis, “city”). It was also the name for the region east of the Sea of Galilee and the Jordan River, where most of these cities were located. They were centers of Hellenistic culture and trade. Jesus passed through this region, but there is no record of his having visited any of the cities. (Mt 4:25; Mr 5:20)—See App. A7 and B10.

Dedication, holy sign of.

A shining plate of pure gold engraved with the words, in Hebrew, “Holiness belongs to Jehovah.” It was put on the front of the turban of the high priest. (Ex 39:30)—See App. B5.

Demons.

Invisible, wicked spirit creatures having superhuman powers. Called “the sons of the true God” at Genesis 6:2 and “angels” at Jude 6, they were not created wicked; rather, they were angels who made themselves enemies of God by disobeying him in Noah’s day and joining in Satan’s rebellion against Jehovah.—De 32:17; Lu 8:30; Ac 16:16; Jas 2:19.

Denarius.

A Roman silver coin that weighed about 3.85 g (0.124 oz t) and bore an image of Caesar on one side. It was the daily wage of a laborer and was the “head tax” coin exacted by the Romans from the Jews. (Mt 22:17; Lu 20:24)—See App. B14.

Devil.

The descriptive name of Satan in the Christian Greek Scriptures, which means “Slanderer.” Satan was given the name Devil because he is the chief and foremost slanderer and false accuser of Jehovah, His good word, and His holy name.—Mt 4:1; Joh 8:44; Re 12:9.

Director.

As used in the Psalms, the Hebrew term seems to refer to one who in some way arranged songs and directed the singing of them, rehearsed and trained the Levite singers, and even led official performances. Other translations render this term “chief musician” or “musical director.”—Ps 4:Sup; 5:Sup.

Dirge.

A composition, lyrical or musical, expressing deep sorrow, such as the grief expressed because of the death of a friend or a loved one; a lamentation.—2Sa 1:17; Ps 7:Sup.

Drachma.

In the Christian Greek Scriptures, this word refers to a Greek silver coin, which at that time weighed 3.4 g (0.109 oz t). In the Hebrew Scriptures, there is reference to a gold drachma from the Persian period that is equated with the daric. (Ne 7:70; Mt 17:24)—See App. B14.

Drink offering.

An offering of wine that was poured out on the altar and presented along with most other offerings. Used figuratively by Paul to express his willingness to expend himself for fellow Christians.—Nu 15:5, 7; Php 2:17.

E

Edom.

Another name given to Esau, son of Isaac. The descendants of Esau (Edom) took over the area of Seir, the mountainous region between the Dead Sea and the Gulf of ‘Aqaba. It became known as Edom. (Ge 25:30; 36:8)—See App. B3 and B4.

Elder; Older man.

A man of mature age, but in the Scriptures, one who primarily holds a position of authority and responsibility in a community or a nation. The word is also used of heavenly creatures in the book of Revelation. The Greek word pre·sbyʹte·ros is translated “elder” when it refers to those responsible for taking the lead in the congregation.—Ex 4:29; Pr 31:23; 1Ti 5:17; Re 4:4.

Elul.

After the Babylonian exile, the name of the 6th month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the 12th month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-August to mid-September. (Ne 6:15)—See App. B15.

Ephah.

A dry measure capacity and the container itself, used for measuring grains. It was equal to a liquid bath measure, so it amounted to 22 L (20 dry qt). (Ex 16:36; Eze 45:10)—See App. B14.

Ephod.

An apronlike garment worn by priests. The high priest wore a special ephod, on the front of which was mounted the breastpiece with 12 precious stones. (Ex 28:4, 6)—See App. B5.

Ephraim.

The name of Joseph’s second son; this name was subsequently applied to one of the tribes of Israel. After Israel was divided, Ephraim, as the most prominent tribe, came to represent the entire ten-tribe kingdom.—Ge 41:52; Jer 7:15.

Epicurean philosophers.

Followers of the Greek philosopher Epicurus (341-270 B.C.E.). Their philosophy centered on the idea that the pleasure of the individual was the ultimate goal in life.—Ac 17:18.

Ethanim.

The name of the seventh month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the first month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-September to mid-October. After the Jews’ return from Babylon, it was called Tishri. (1Ki 8:2)—See App. B15.

Ethiopia.

An ancient nation south of Egypt. It included the southernmost part of modern-day Egypt and the northern half of modern-day Sudan. The expression is sometimes used for the Hebrew “Cush.”—Es 1:1.

Eunuch.

In a literal sense, a castrated male. Such men were often appointed in royal courts as attendants or caretakers of the queen and the concubines. The term also refers to a man who was, not a literal eunuch, but an official assigned to duties in the court of the king. It is used figuratively for a ‘eunuch for the Kingdom,’ one who exercises self-control so as to apply himself more fully to the service of God.—Mt 19:12; Es 2:15; Ac 8:27.

Euphrates.

The longest and most important river of southwest Asia, and one of the two major rivers in Mesopotamia. It is first mentioned at Genesis 2:14 as one of the four rivers of Eden. It is often called “the River.” (Ge 31:21) It was the northern boundary of Israel’s assigned territory. (Ge 15:18; Re 16:12)—See App. B2.

Exile.

Expulsion from one’s native land or home, often decreed by conquerors. The Hebrew word means “a departing.” The Israelites experienced two major exiles. The northern ten-tribe kingdom was taken into exile by the Assyrians, and later the southern two-tribe kingdom was taken into exile by the Babylonians. Remnants of both exiles were returned to their land under Cyrus, the Persian ruler.—2Ki 17:6; 24:16; Ezr 6:21.

Extinguishers.

Tools used in the tabernacle and temple, made of gold or copper. They may have been like scissors for trimming the lampwicks.—2Ki 25:14.

F

Fast.

Abstinence from all food for a limited period. The Israelites practiced fasting on the Day of Atonement, in times of distress, and when in need of divine guidance. The Jews established four annual fasts to mark calamitous events in their history. Fasting is not a requirement for Christians.—Ezr 8:21; Isa 58:6; Lu 18:12.

Fathom.

A linear unit for measuring the depth of water, equal to 1.8 m (6 ft). (Ac 27:28)—See App. B14.

Festival of Booths.

Also called the Festival of Tabernacles, or the Festival of Ingathering. It was held on Ethanim 15-21. It celebrated the harvest at the end of the agricultural year for Israel and was a time of rejoicing and thanksgiving for Jehovah’s blessings on their crops. During the days of the festival, people lived in booths, or rooflike shelters, to remind them of the Exodus from Egypt. It was one of the three festivals that males were required to go to Jerusalem to observe.—Le 23:34; Ezr 3:4.

Festival of Dedication.

The annual day of remembrance for the cleansing of the temple after its defilement by Antiochus Epiphanes. The celebration began on Chislev 25 and lasted for eight days.—Joh 10:22.

Festival of Harvest; Festival of Weeks.—

See PENTECOST.

Festival of Unleavened Bread.

The first of the three major annual festivals of the Israelites. It began on Nisan 15, the day after Passover, and continued for seven days. Only unleavened bread could be eaten, in remembrance of the Exodus from Egypt.—Ex 23:15; Mr 14:1.

Fire holders.

Utensils made of gold, silver, or copper, used at the tabernacle and the temple for burning incense and for removing coals from the sacrificial altar and burnt lampwicks from the golden lampstand. They were also called censers.—Ex 37:23; 2Ch 26:19; Heb 9:4.

Firstborn.

Primarily, the oldest son of a father (rather than the firstborn of the mother). In Bible times, the firstborn son held an honored position in the family and was given the headship of the household when the father died. The term also refers to the first male offspring of animals, at times called “firstlings.”—Ex 11:5; 13:12; Ge 25:33; Col 1:15.

Firstfruits.

The earliest fruits of a harvest season; the first results or products of anything. Jehovah required the nation of Israel to offer their firstfruits to him, whether it be of man, animal, or the fruitage of the ground. As a nation, the Israelites offered firstfruits to God at the Festival of Unleavened Bread and at Pentecost. The term “firstfruits” was also used figuratively of Christ and his anointed followers.—1Co 15:23; Nu 15:21; Pr 3:9; Re 14:4.

Fornication.—

See SEXUAL IMMORALITY.

Fortune-teller.

An individual claiming ability to foretell future events. Magic-practicing priests, spiritistic diviners, astrologers, and others are listed in the Bible as such.—Le 19:31; De 18:11; Ac 16:16.

Frankincense.

Dried sap (gum resin) from trees and bushes of certain species of the genus Boswellia. When burned, it gave off a sweet-smelling fragrance. It was an ingredient of the holy incense used at the tabernacle and the temple. It also accompanied grain offerings and was placed on each row of the showbread inside the Holy.—Ex 30:34-36; Le 2:1; 24:7; Mt 2:11.

Freeman; Freedman.

During Roman rule, a “freeman” was one who was born free, possessing full rights of citizenship. In contrast, a “freedman” was one emancipated from slavery. Formal emancipation granted the freedman Roman citizenship, but he was not eligible for political office. Informal emancipation freed the individual from slavery but did not give full civil rights.—1Co 7:22.

Furnace.

A structure for smelting ore or melting metal; also used to fire pottery and other ceramic items. In Bible times, furnaces were made of brick or stone. A furnace for firing pottery and ceramics and for burning lime is also called a kiln.—Ge 15:17; Da 3:17; Re 9:2.

G

Gehenna.

The Greek name for the Valley of Hinnom, south and southwest of ancient Jerusalem. (Jer 7:31) It was prophetically spoken of as a place where dead bodies would be strewn. (Jer 7:32; 19:6) There is no evidence that animals or humans were thrown into Gehenna to be burned alive or tormented. So the place could not symbolize an invisible region where human souls are tormented eternally in literal fire. Rather, Gehenna was used by Jesus and his disciples to symbolize the eternal punishment of “second death,” that is, everlasting destruction, annihilation.—Re 20:14; Mt 5:22; 10:28.

Gerah.

A weight equivalent to 0.57 g (0.01835 oz t). It corresponded to 1/20 shekel. (Le 27:25)—See App. B14.

Gifts of mercy.

Gifts given to help someone in need. These are not directly mentioned in the Hebrew Scriptures, but the Law gave specific directions to the Israelites about their obligations toward the poor.—Mt 6:2.

Gilead.

In a strict sense, the fertile area east of the Jordan River that extended north and south of the Valley of Jabbok. At times used for the entire Israelite territory east of the Jordan, where the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and the half tribe of Manasseh lived. (Nu 32:1; Jos 12:2; 2Ki 10:33)—See App. B4.

Gittith.

A musical term of uncertain meaning, though it seems to be derived from the Hebrew word gath. Some believe that it may be a melody associated with songs related to wine making, since gath refers to a winepress.—Ps 81:Sup.

Glean.

To gather whatever portion of a crop the harvesters had intentionally or unintentionally left behind. The Mosaic Law directed the people not to reap the edges of their fields completely nor to take all the olives or grapes. It was the God-given right of the poor, the afflicted, the foreign resident, the fatherless child, and the widow to glean what was left after harvest.—Ru 2:7.

Goad.

A long rod with a sharp metal point, used by farmers to prod an animal. The goad is compared to the words of a wise person that move the listener to heed wise counsel. “Kicking against the goads” is drawn from the action of a stubborn bull that resists the prodding of the goad by kicking against it, resulting in injury to itself.—Ac 26:14; Jg 3:31.

Godly devotion.

Reverence, worship, and service to Jehovah God, with loyalty to his universal sovereignty.—1Ti 4:8; 2Ti 3:12.

God’s Kingdom.

The phrase used particularly of God’s sovereignty represented by the royal government of his Son, Christ Jesus.—Mt 12:28; Lu 4:43; 1Co 15:50.

Good news, the.

In the Christian Greek Scriptures, the good news of the Kingdom of God and of salvation by faith in Jesus Christ.—Lu 4:18, 43; Ac 5:42; Re 14:6.

Grave.

When lowercased, referring to an individual grave; when capitalized, the common grave of mankind, equivalent to the Hebrew “Sheol” and the Greek “Hades.” It is described in the Bible as a symbolic place or condition wherein all activity and consciousness cease.—Ge 47:30; Ec 9:10; Ac 2:31.

Great tribulation.

The Greek word for “tribulation” conveys the idea of distress or suffering resulting from the pressures of circumstances. Jesus spoke of an unprecedented “great tribulation” that would come upon Jerusalem and especially of one that would later befall mankind in connection with his future ‘coming with glory.’ (Mt 24:21, 29-31) Paul described this tribulation as a righteous act of God against “those who do not know God and those who do not obey the good news” about Jesus Christ. Revelation chapter 19 shows Jesus as the one leading heavenly armies against “the wild beast and the kings of the earth and their armies.” (2Th 1:6-8; Re 19:11-21) “A great crowd” is shown as surviving that tribulation. (Re 7:9, 14)—See ARMAGEDDON.

Greek.

The language spoken by the people of Greece; also, a native of Greece or one whose family originated there. In the Christian Greek Scriptures, the word also has a broader usage, referring to all non-Jewish peoples or to those who were influenced by Greek language and culture.—Joe 3:6; Joh 12:20.

Guilt offering.

A sacrifice for personal sins. It differed slightly from other sin offerings in that it was to satisfy or restore certain covenant rights that the repentant wrongdoer had lost because of a sin and to give him relief from the penalty.—Le 7:37; 19:22; Isa 53:10.

H

Hades.

A Greek word corresponding to the Hebrew word “Sheol.” It is translated “Grave” (capitalized), to distinguish it as the common grave of mankind.—See GRAVE.

Hebrew.

A designation first used for Abram (Abraham), distinguishing him from his Amorite neighbors. It was used thereafter to refer to Abraham’s descendants through his grandson Jacob as well as to their language. By the time of Jesus, the Hebrew language had come to include many Aramaic expressions and was the language spoken by Christ and his disciples.—Ge 14:13; Ex 5:3; Ac 26:14.

Hermes.

A Greek god, son of Zeus. In Lystra, Paul was mistakenly called Hermes in reference to that god’s supposed role as messenger of the gods and the god of skillful speech.—Ac 14:12.

Herod.

The family name of a dynasty that ruled over the Jews by appointment from Rome. Herod the Great was famous for rebuilding the temple in Jerusalem and for ordering the slaughter of children in an attempt to destroy Jesus. (Mt 2:16; Lu 1:5) Herod Archelaus and Herod Antipas, sons of Herod the Great, were appointed over sections of their father’s domain. (Mt 2:22) Antipas was a tetrarch, popularly referred to as “king,” who ruled during Christ’s three-and-a-half-year ministry and through the period up to Acts chapter 12. (Mr 6:14-17; Lu 3:1, 19, 20; 13:31, 32; 23:6-15; Ac 4:27; 13:1) After that, Herod Agrippa I, grandson of Herod the Great, was executed by God’s angel after ruling for a short time. (Ac 12:1-6, 18-23) His son, Herod Agrippa II, became ruler and reigned up to the time of the Jewish revolt against Rome.—Ac 23:35; 25:13, 22-27; 26:1, 2, 19-32.

Herod, party followers of.

Also known as Herodians. They were a party of nationalists who supported the political aims of the Herods in their rule under the Romans. Some of the Sadducees probably belonged to this party. The Herodians joined with the Pharisees to oppose Jesus.—Mr 3:6.

Higgaion.

A technical term of musical direction. As used at Psalm 9:16, the word may signify either a solemn, deep-toned harp interlude or a solemn pause conducive to meditation.

High place.

A place of worship usually on top of a hill, a mountain, or a man-made platform. Although high places were sometimes used for the worship of God, they are most often associated with pagan worship of false gods.—Nu 33:52; 1Ki 3:2; Jer 19:5.

High priest.

Under the Mosaic Law, the principal priest who represented the people before God and supervised the other priests. Also called “the chief priest.” (2Ch 26:20; Ezr 7:5) He alone was allowed to enter the Most Holy, the innermost compartment of the tabernacle and later of the temple. He did so only on the annual Day of Atonement. The term “high priest” is also applied to Jesus Christ.—Le 16:2, 17; 21:10; Mt 26:3; Heb 4:14.

Hin.

A liquid measure and the container for that measure. It is equivalent to 3.67 L (7.75 pt), based on a statement by the historian Josephus that a hin equaled two Athenian choes. (Ex 29:40)—See App. B14.

Holy; Holiness.

A quality possessed inherently by Jehovah; a state of absolute moral purity and sacredness. (Ex 28:36; 1Sa 2:2; Pr 9:10; Isa 6:3) When referring to humans (Ex 19:6; 2Ki 4:9), animals (Nu 18:17), things (Ex 28:38; 30:25; Le 27:14), places (Ex 3:5; Isa 27:13), time periods (Ex 16:23; Le 25:12), and activities (Ex 36:4), the original Hebrew word conveys the thought of separateness, exclusiveness, or sanctification to the holy God; a state of being set aside for Jehovah’s service. In the Christian Greek Scriptures, the words rendered “holy” and “holiness” likewise denote separation to God. The words are also used to refer to purity in one’s personal conduct.—Mr 6:20; 2Co 7:1; 1Pe 1:15, 16.

Holy, the.

The first and larger compartment of the tabernacle or of the temple, as distinguished from the innermost compartment, the Most Holy. In the tabernacle, the Holy contained the golden lampstand, golden altar of incense, table of showbread, and golden utensils; in the temple, it contained the golden altar, ten golden lampstands, and ten tables of showbread. (Ex 26:33; Heb 9:2)—See App. B5 and B8.

Holy spirit.

The invisible energizing force that God puts into action to accomplish his will. It is holy because it comes from Jehovah, who is clean and righteous to the highest degree, and because it is God’s means to accomplish what is holy.—Lu 1:35; Ac 1:8.

Homer.

A dry measure corresponding to the cor. Based on the estimated volume of the bath measure, it equaled 220 L (200 dry qt). (Le 27:16)—See App. B14.

Horeb; Mount Horeb.

The mountainous region surrounding Mount Sinai. Another name for Mount Sinai. (Ex 3:1; De 5:2)—See App. B3.

Horn.

Referring to animal horns, which were used as drinking vessels, as vessels for oil, as containers for ink and cosmetics, and as musical or signaling instruments. (1Sa 16:1, 13; 1Ki 1:39; Eze 9:2) “Horn” is often used figuratively for strength, conquest, and victory.—De 33:17; Mic 4:13; Zec 1:19.

Horns of the altar.

Hornlike projections extending outward from the four corners of certain altars. (Le 8:15; 1Ki 2:28)—See App. B5 and B8.

Hyssop.

A plant with fine branches and leaves, used for sprinkling blood or water in cleansing ceremonies. It was possibly marjoram (Origanum maru; Origanum syriacum). As used at John 19:29, it may have been marjoram attached to a branch or durra, a variety of common sorghum (Sorghum vulgare), since this plant could have provided a stalk long enough to carry the sponge of sour wine to Jesus’ mouth.—Ex 12:22; Ps 51:7.

I

Idol; Idolatry.

An idol is an image, a representation of anything, real or imagined, that people may use in worship. Idolatry is the veneration, love, worship, or adoration of an idol.—Ps 115:4; Ac 17:16; 1Co 10:14.

Illyricum.

A Roman province northwest of Greece. Paul traveled this far in his ministry, but it is not stated whether he preached in Illyricum or merely up to it. (Ro 15:19)—See App. B13.

Incense.

A compound of aromatic gums and balsams that burns slowly, giving off a fragrant aroma. A special four-ingredient incense was made for use at the tabernacle and the temple. It was burned morning and night on the altar of incense in the Holy compartment, and on the Day of Atonement, it was burned inside the Most Holy compartment. It was symbolic of the acceptable prayers of God’s faithful servants. Its use was not required of Christians.—Ex 30:34, 35; Le 16:13; Re 5:8.

Israel.

The name God gave to Jacob. It came to refer to all his descendants collectively, at any one time. The descendants of Jacob’s 12 sons were often called the sons of Israel, the house of Israel, the people (men) of Israel, or the Israelites. Israel was also used as the name for the ten-tribe northern kingdom that broke away from the southern kingdom, and later as a term for anointed Christians, “the Israel of God.”—Ga 6:16; Ge 32:28; 2Sa 7:23; Ro 9:6.

J

Jacob.

A son of Isaac and Rebekah. God later gave him the name Israel, and he became the patriarch of the people of Israel (also called Israelites and later, Jews). He was the father of the 12 sons who, along with their descendants, made up the 12 tribes of the nation of Israel. The name Jacob continued to be used for the nation or people of Israel.—Ge 32:28; Mt 22:32.

Jeduthun.

A term of uncertain meaning appearing in the superscriptions of Psalms 39, 62, and 77. These superscriptions appear to be instructions for the performance of the psalm, perhaps identifying a style or a musical instrument. There was a Levitical musician named Jeduthun, so this performance style or instrument may have been associated with him or his sons.

Jehovah.

The common English rendering of the Tetragrammaton (the four Hebrew letters for the personal name of God), which appears over 7,000 times in this translation.—See App. A4 and A5.

Jew.

A term used for a person of the tribe of Judah after the fall of the ten-tribe kingdom of Israel. (2Ki 16:6) After the Babylonian exile, it was used with regard to Israelites from various tribes who returned to Israel. (Ezr 4:12) Later, it was used throughout the world to distinguish Israelites from those of the Gentile nations. (Es 3:6) The term is also used figuratively by the apostle Paul when reasoning that nationality is of no consequence in the Christian congregation.—Ro 2:28, 29; Ga 3:28.

Jubilee.

Every 50th year, counting from Israel’s entry into the Promised Land. The land was to lie fallow during the Jubilee year, and Hebrew slaves were to be set free. Hereditary lands that had been sold were returned. The Jubilee was, in a sense, an entire year of festival, a year of liberty that restored the nation to the state it had enjoyed when God first established it.—Le 25:10.

Judah.

Jacob’s fourth son by his wife Leah. In his deathbed prophecy, Jacob foretold that a great and lasting ruler would come from Judah’s family line. Jesus, in his human existence, descended from Judah. The name Judah also refers to the tribe and later to the kingdom named after Judah. Described as the southern kingdom, Judah was made up of the Israelite tribes of Judah and Benjamin and included the priests and Levites. Judah occupied the southern part of the country that included Jerusalem and the temple.—Ge 29:35; 49:10; 1Ki 4:20; Heb 7:14.

Judges.

Men raised up by Jehovah to save his people prior to the period of Israel’s human kings.—Jg 2:16.

Judgment Day.

A specific day, or period, when particular groups, nations, or mankind in general are called to account by God. It may be a time when those judged to be deserving of death are executed, or the judgment may afford opportunity for some to be saved and gain everlasting life. Jesus Christ and his apostles pointed to a future “Judgment Day” involving not only the living but also those who died in the past.—Mt 12:36.

Judgment seat.

Usually a raised outdoor platform, approached by steps, from which seated officials could address the crowds and announce their decisions. The expressions “judgment seat of God” and “judgment seat of the Christ” are symbolic of Jehovah’s arrangement for judging mankind.—Ro 14:10; 2Co 5:10; Joh 19:13.

L

Lake of fire.

A symbolic place that “burns with fire and sulfur,” also described as “the second death.” Unrepentant sinners, the Devil, and even death and the Grave (or, Hades) are thrown into it. The inclusion of a spirit creature and also of death and Hades, all of which cannot be affected by fire, indicates that this lake is a symbol, not of everlasting torment, but of everlasting destruction.—Re 19:20; 20:14, 15; 21:8.

Last days.

This and similar expressions, such as “the final part of the days,” are used in Bible prophecy to refer to the time when historical events would reach a final climax. (Eze 38:16; Da 10:14; Ac 2:17) Depending on the nature of the prophecy, this may be a period covering just a few years or many. Most notably, the Bible uses this term regarding “the last days” of the present system of things, during Jesus’ invisible presence.—2Ti 3:1; Jas 5:3; 2Pe 3:3.

Law.

When it is capitalized, this word often refers either to the Mosaic Law or to the first five books of the Bible. When it is lowercased, it may refer to individual laws of the Mosaic Law or a principle of law.—Nu 15:16; De 4:8; Mt 7:12; Ga 3:24.

Lay hands on.

Hands were laid on a person to appoint him to a special work or to designate him for a blessing, a healing, or a gift of the holy spirit. Sometimes hands were laid on animals before they were sacrificed.—Ex 29:15; Nu 27:18; Ac 19:6; 1Ti 5:22.

Leaven.

A substance added to dough or to liquids to cause fermentation; especially a portion of fermented dough preserved from a previous batch. Often used in the Bible as a symbol of sin and corruption, it is also used to indicate hidden, pervasive growth.—Ex 12:20; Mt 13:33; Ga 5:9.

Lebanon Mountain range.

One of the two mountain ranges forming the mountain system of the land of Lebanon. The Lebanon range is on the west, and the Anti-Lebanon range is on the east. A long, fertile valley separates the two ranges. The Lebanon range rises up almost directly from the Mediterranean coast, and its summits average between 1,800 and 2,100 m (6,000 and 7,000 ft) in elevation. In ancient times, Lebanon was covered with majestic cedars, which were highly prized by the surrounding nations. (De 1:7; Ps 29:6; 92:12)—See App. B7.

Leprosy; Leper.

A serious skin disease. In the Scriptures, leprosy is not restricted to the disease known by that name today, for it could affect not only humans but also clothing and houses. A person afflicted with leprosy is called a leper.—Le 14:54, 55; Lu 5:12.

Lepton.

In the Christian Greek Scripture period, the smallest Jewish copper or bronze coin. Translated as “mite” in some Bible versions. (Mr 12:42; Lu 21:2; ftns.)—See App. B14.

Levi; Levite.

Jacob’s third son by his wife Leah; also the tribe named after him. His three sons became the founders of the three principal divisions of the Levites. At times, the term “Levites” applies to the whole tribe, but usually it excludes the priestly family of Aaron. The tribe of Levi did not receive an allotment of land in the Promised Land but was given 48 cities within the boundaries of land apportioned to the other tribes.—De 10:8; 1Ch 6:1; Heb 7:11.

Leviathan.

An animal usually associated with water, apparently some form of aquatic creature. At Job 3:8 and 41:1, it seems to refer to the crocodile or some other aquatic creature of great proportions and strength. At Psalm 104:26, it may be some type of whale. Elsewhere it is used figuratively and is not identifiable with any one animal.—Ps 74:14; Isa 27:1.

Loaves of presentation.—

See SHOWBREAD.

Locusts.

A variety of grasshoppers that migrate in great swarms. They were considered clean for food in the Mosaic Law. Large swarms that consume everything in their path, causing massive destruction, were regarded as a plague.—Ex 10:14; Mt 3:4.

Log.

The smallest liquid measure mentioned in the Bible. In the Jewish Talmud, it is described as 1/12 of a hin, so using that as a basis, the log would have a capacity of 0.31 L (0.66 pt). (Le 14:10)—See App. B14.

Loom.

A frame used for weaving threads or yarns into cloth.—Ex 39:27.

Lord’s Evening Meal.

A literal meal consisting of unleavened bread and wine as symbols of Christ’s body and blood; a memorial of Jesus’ death. Since this is an observance that Christians are Scripturally required to keep, it is also appropriately termed “the Memorial.”—1Co 11:20, 23-26.

Lots.

Pebbles or small bits of wood or stone that were used in making decisions. These were gathered into the folds of a garment or into a vessel and then shaken. The lot that fell out or was drawn out was the one chosen. This was often done prayerfully. The term “lot” is used both literally and figuratively with the meaning “share” or “portion.”—Jos 14:2; Ps 16:5; Pr 16:33; Mt 27:35.

Loyal love.

Most frequently rendered from the Hebrew word cheʹsedh, referring to love motivated by commitment, integrity, loyalty, and deep attachment. It is often used in connection with God’s love for humans, but it is also love shown between humans.—Ex 34:6; Ru 3:10.

M

Macedonia.

A region north of Greece that gained prominence under Alexander the Great and remained independent until conquered by the Romans. Macedonia was a Roman province when the apostle Paul made his first visit to Europe. Paul visited the area three times. (Ac 16:9)—See App. B13.

Magistrates.

Under the government of Babylon, magistrates were civil officers in the jurisdictional districts who knew the law and had limited judicial authority. In Roman colonies, the civil magistrates were administrators of the government. Their duties included maintaining order, controlling finances, judging violators of the law, and ordering the carrying out of punishment.—Da 3:2; Ac 16:20.

Mahalath.

A term, evidently musical, found in the superscriptions of Psalms 53 and 88. It may be related to a Hebrew root verb meaning “grow weak; fall sick,” thereby suggesting a gloomy and sad tone, which would harmonize with the somber content of the two songs.

Malcam.

Probably the same as Molech, the chief god of the Ammonites. (Zep 1:5)—See MOLECH.

Manna.

The main food of the Israelites during their 40 years in the wilderness. It was provided by Jehovah. It miraculously appeared on the ground under a layer of dew every morning except on the Sabbath. When the Israelites first saw it, they said, “What is it?” or, in Hebrew, “man huʼ?” (Ex 16:13-15, 35) In other contexts, it is referred to as “the grain of heaven” (Ps 78:24), “bread from heaven” (Ps 105:40), and “the bread of mighty ones” (Ps 78:25). Jesus also referred to manna in a figurative sense.—Joh 6:49, 50.

Maskil.

A Hebrew term of uncertain meaning in the superscriptions of 13 psalms. It possibly means “contemplative poem.” Some think that a word similar in form, translated ‘serve with discretion,’ may be related in meaning.—2Ch 30:22; Ps 32:Sup.

Measuring reed.

A measuring reed was six cubits long. Based on the common cubit, it measured 2.67 m (8.75 ft); based on the long cubit, it measured 3.11 m (10.2 ft). (Eze 40:3, 5; Re 11:1)—See App. B14.

Medes; Media.

A people descended from Japheth’s son Madai; they settled in the mountainous Iranian plateau that became the country of Media. The Medes joined with Babylon to defeat Assyria. At that time, Persia was a province under Media, but Cyrus revolted and Media was merged with Persia to form the Medo-Persian Empire that defeated the Neo-Babylonian Empire in 539 B.C.E. Medes were present in Jerusalem at Pentecost in 33 C.E. (Da 5:28, 31; Ac 2:9)—See App. B9.

Mediator.

One who intercedes between two parties in order to reconcile them. In the Scriptures, Moses and Jesus are the mediators of the Law covenant and the new covenant respectively.—Ga 3:19; 1Ti 2:5.

Memorial tomb.

A burial place in which the remains of a deceased person were placed. This term renders the Greek word mne·meiʹon, which comes from the verb “to remind,” suggesting that the person who has died is remembered.—Joh 5:28, 29.

Merodach.

The chief god of the city of Babylon. After the Babylonian king and lawmaker Hammurabi made Babylon the capital of Babylonia, Merodach (or, Marduk) grew in importance, finally displacing a number of the earlier gods and becoming the chief god of the Babylonian pantheon. In later periods, the name Merodach (or, Marduk) was replaced by the title “Belu” (“Owner”), and Merodach was commonly spoken of as Bel.—Jer 50:2.

Messiah.

A word derived from the Hebrew word for “anointed” or “anointed one.” “Christ” is the equivalent derived from the Greek.—Da 9:25; Joh 1:41.

Miktam.

A Hebrew word used in the superscriptions of six psalms (Ps 16, 56-60). It is a technical term of uncertain meaning, though it may be related to the word “inscription.”

Milcom.

A god worshipped by the Ammonites, probably the same as the god Molech. (1Ki 11:5, 7) Near the close of his reign, Solomon built high places to this false god.—See MOLECH.

Mildew.

Any of many parasitic plant diseases caused by fungi. It has been suggested that the mildew mentioned in the Bible is black stem rust (Puccinia graminis).—1Ki 8:37.

Mile.

A measure of distance occurring only once in the original text of the Christian Greek Scriptures at Matthew 5:41, probably referring to the Roman mile that was equal to 1,479.5 m (4,854 ft). The three other occurrences of “mile” at Luke 24:13, John 6:19, and John 11:18 refer to statute miles converted from the ancient stadia of the original text.—See App. B14.

Millstone.

A round stone placed on top of a similar stone and used to grind grain into flour. A peg that was fitted into the center of the lower stone served as a pivot for the upper stone. In Bible times, hand mills operated by the women were used in most homes. Since a family’s daily bread depended on the hand mill, the Mosaic Law forbade confiscating it or its upper grindstone as security. Larger mills of a similar construction were turned by animals.—De 24:6; Mr 9:42.

Mina.

Also called maneh in Ezekiel. A unit both of weight and of monetary value. Based on archaeological evidence that a mina equaled 50 shekels, and a shekel weighed 11.4 g, the mina of the Hebrew Scriptures weighed 570 g (18.35 oz t). There may also have been a royal mina, as in the case of the cubit. In the Christian Greek Scriptures, a mina was equivalent to 100 drachmas. It weighed 340 g (10.9 oz t). Sixty minas equaled a talent. (Ezr 2:69; Lu 19:13)—See App. B14.

Ministerial servant.

A rendering of the Greek word di·aʹko·nos, which is often translated “minister” or “servant.” “Ministerial servant” refers to one who serves as an assistant to the body of elders in the congregation. He must meet Bible standards to qualify for this privilege of service.—1Ti 3:8-10, 12.

Miracles; Powerful works.

Actions or phenomena that surpass all powers known to humans and are attributed to a supernatural agency. Such expressions as “sign,” “portent,” and “wonder” are sometimes used synonymously in the Bible.—Ex 4:21; Ac 4:22; Heb 2:4.

Molech.

A god of the Ammonites; possibly the same as Malcam, Milcom, and Moloch. It may be a title rather than the name of a specific god. The Mosaic Law demanded the death penalty for anyone who sacrificed his children to Molech.—Le 20:2; Jer 32:35; Ac 7:43.

Moloch.—

See MOLECH.

Morning star.—

See DAYSTAR.

Moses, Law of.

The Law that Jehovah gave Israel through Moses in the wilderness of Sinai in 1513 B.C.E. The first five books of the Bible are often referred to as the Law.—Jos 23:6; Lu 24:44.

Most Holy, the.

The innermost room of the tabernacle and of the temple, where the ark of the covenant was kept; also called the Holy of Holies. According to the Mosaic Law, the only person allowed to enter the Most Holy was the high priest, and he could enter only on the annual Day of Atonement.—Ex 26:33; Le 16:2, 17; 1Ki 6:16; Heb 9:3.

Mound.

In Hebrew, “Millo,” from a root word meaning “fill.” The Septuagint translates it “citadel.” It was apparently a geographic or structural feature of the City of David, but its exact nature remains unknown.—2Sa 5:9; 1Ki 11:27.

Mourning.

The outward expression of grief over a death or some other calamity. In Bible times, it was customary to mourn for a period of time. In addition to weeping loudly, mourners wore special clothes, put ashes on their head, ripped their garments, and beat their chest. Professional mourners were sometimes invited to funerals.—Ge 23:2; Es 4:3; Re 21:4.

Muth-labben.

A term in the superscription of Psalm 9. Traditionally, it meant “concerning the death of the son.” Some suggest that it was the name or perhaps the opening words of a familiar melody to be used when singing this psalm.

Myrrh.

An aromatic gum resin obtained from a variety of thorny shrubs or small trees of the genus Commiphora. Myrrh was one of the ingredients of the holy anointing oil. It was used to scent such things as garments or beds, and it was added to oil for massages and body lotions. Myrrh was also used to prepare bodies for burial.—Ex 30:23; Pr 7:17; Joh 19:39.

N

Nard.

A costly fragrant oil of light-reddish color, derived from the spikenard plant (Nardostachys jatamansi). Because it was expensive, nard was often mixed with inferior oils, and it was sometimes counterfeited. Notably, both Mark and John state that “genuine nard” was used on Jesus.—Mr 14:3; Joh 12:3.

Nazarene.

A name for Jesus, as one from the town of Nazareth. It is probably related to the Hebrew word used at Isaiah 11:1 for “sprout.” It was later applied to Jesus’ followers as well.—Mt 2:23; Ac 24:5.

Nazirite.

A word taken from the Hebrew for “One Singled Out,” “Dedicated One,” “Separated One.” There were two classes of Nazirites: those who volunteered and those who were appointed as such by God. A man or a woman could take a special vow to Jehovah to live as a Nazirite for a period of time. Those voluntarily taking the vow had three principal restrictions: they were to drink no alcohol nor eat any product of the grapevine, they were not to cut their hair, and they were not to touch a dead body. Those appointed by God as Nazirites remained such for life, and Jehovah specified the requirements for them.—Nu 6:2-7; Jg 13:5.

Nehiloth.

A term of uncertain meaning, occurring in the superscription of Psalm 5. Some believe that it refers to a wind instrument, linking it with a Hebrew root word related to cha·lilʹ (flute). However, it may designate a melody.

Nephilim.

The violent hybrid sons who were the children of materialized angels and the daughters of men before the Flood.—Ge 6:4.

Nethinim.

Non-Israelite temple servants, or ministers. The Hebrew term literally means “Given Ones,” implying that they were given for temple service. Likely, many of the Nethinim were descendants of the Gibeonites, whom Joshua had constituted “gatherers of wood and drawers of water for the assembly and for Jehovah’s altar.”—Jos 9:23, 27; 1Ch 9:2; Ezr 8:17.

New moon.

The first day of each month of the Jewish calendar, which was observed as a day for gathering together, feasting, and offering special sacrifices. In later periods, the day became an important national festival, and people abstained from work.—Nu 10:10; 2Ch 8:13; Col 2:16.

Nisan.

After the Babylonian exile, the new name for Abib, the first month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the seventh month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-March to mid-April. (Ne 2:1)—See App. B15.

O

Oath.

A sworn statement to certify that something is true, or a solemn promise that a person will or will not do a certain thing. It is frequently a vow made to a superior, especially to God. Jehovah reinforced his covenant with Abraham by a sworn oath.—Ge 14:22; Heb 6:16, 17.

Omer.

A dry measure equaling 2.2 L (2 dry qt), or a tenth of an ephah. (Ex 16:16, 18)—See App. B14.

Onyx.

A semiprecious stone, a hard variety of agate, or a banded form of chalcedony. The onyx has white layers alternating with black, brown, red, gray, or green layers. It was used in the special garments of the high priest.—Ex 28:9, 12; 1Ch 29:2; Job 28:16.

Overseer.

A man whose primary responsibility is to watch over and shepherd the congregation. The basic idea inherent in the Greek term e·piʹsko·pos is that of protective supervision. The terms “overseer” and “elder” (pre·sbyʹte·ros) refer to the same position in the Christian congregation, with “elder” indicating the mature qualities of the one so appointed, and “overseer” emphasizing the duties inherent in this appointment.—Ac 20:28; 1Ti 3:2-7; 1Pe 5:2.

P

Papyrus.

A reedlike aquatic plant used in making such things as baskets, containers, and boats. It was also used to make a writing material similar to paper and was used in many scrolls.—Ex 2:3.

Paradise.

A beautiful park, or parklike garden. The first such place was Eden, made by Jehovah for the first human pair. When speaking to one of the criminals next to him on the torture stake, Jesus indicated that the earth would become a paradise. At 2 Corinthians 12:4, the word evidently refers to a future paradise, and at Revelation 2:7, to a heavenly paradise.—Ca 4:13; Lu 23:43.

Parchment.

The skin of a sheep, goat, or calf prepared for use as writing material. It was more durable than papyrus and was used for scrolls of the Bible. The parchments that Paul requested Timothy to bring were possibly portions of the Hebrew Scriptures. Some of the Dead Sea Scrolls were written on parchment.—2Ti 4:13.

Party followers of Herod.—

See HEROD; PARTY FOLLOWERS OF.

Passover.

An annual festival observed on the 14th day of Abib (later called Nisan) to commemorate the deliverance of the Israelites from Egypt. It was observed by slaughtering and roasting a lamb (or goat), which was then eaten with bitter greens and unleavened bread.—Ex 12:27; Joh 6:4; 1Co 5:7.

Pentecost.

The second of the three major festivals that all Jewish males were required to celebrate in Jerusalem. Pentecost, meaning “Fiftieth (Day),” is the name used in the Christian Greek Scriptures for what is called the Festival of Harvest or Festival of Weeks in the Hebrew Scriptures. It was celebrated on the 50th day counted from Nisan 16.—Ex 23:16; 34:22; Ac 2:1.

Persia; Persians.

A land and a people regularly mentioned along with, and evidently related to, the Medes. In their early history, the Persians held only the southwestern part of the Iranian plateau. Under Cyrus the Great (who according to some ancient historians was born of a Persian father and a Median mother), the Persians became dominant over the Medes, though the empire continued to be dual. Cyrus conquered the Babylonian Empire in 539 B.C.E. and allowed the Jews in captivity to return to their homeland. The Persian Empire extended from the Indus River on the east to the Aegean Sea on the west. The Jews were under Persian rule until Alexander the Great defeated the Persians in 331 B.C.E. The Persian Empire was foreseen in a vision by Daniel, and it figures in the Bible books of Ezra, Nehemiah, and Esther. (Ezr 1:1; Da 5:28; 8:20)—See App. B9.

Pestilence.

Any rapidly spreading infectious disease capable of attaining epidemic proportions and of causing death. It is often related to the execution of divine judgment.—Nu 14:12; Eze 38:22, 23; Am 4:10.

Pharaoh.

A title given to the kings of Egypt. Five pharaohs are named in the Bible (Shishak, So, Tirhakah, Nechoh, and Hophra), but others are left anonymous, including those who had extensive dealings with Abraham, Moses, and Joseph.—Ex 15:4; Ro 9:17.

Pharisees.

A prominent religious sect of Judaism in the first century C.E. They were not of priestly descent, but they were strict observers of the Law in its smallest detail, and they elevated oral traditions to the same level. (Mt 23:23) They opposed any Greek cultural influence, and as scholars of the Law and the traditions, they had great authority over the people. (Mt 23:2-6) Some were also members of the Sanhedrin. They often opposed Jesus regarding Sabbath observance, traditions, and association with sinners and tax collectors. Some became Christians, including Saul of Tarsus.—Mt 9:11; 12:14; Mr 7:5; Lu 6:2; Ac 26:5.

Philistia; Philistines.

The land on the southern coast of Israel that came to be called Philistia. The immigrants from Crete who settled there were called Philistines. David subdued them, but they remained independent and were constant enemies of Israel. (Ex 13:17; 1Sa 17:4; Am 9:7)—See App. B4.

Pillar.

An upright structural support or column, or something resembling such a column. Some were set up to commemorate historic acts or events. Structural pillars were used in the temple and the royal structures built by Solomon. Pagan peoples set up sacred pillars in connection with their false religion, and the Israelites at times took up this practice. (Jg 16:29; 1Ki 7:21; 14:23)—See CAPITAL.

Pim.

A weight as well as the price charged by the Philistines for sharpening various metal implements. Several stone weights found in archaeological excavations in Israel bear the ancient Hebrew consonants of “pim”; their average weight is 7.8 g (0.2508 oz t), which would be approximately two thirds of a shekel.—1Sa 13:20, 21.

Pledge.

An object of personal property given by a debtor to his creditor as a guarantee of the future repayment of a loan. It was also called security. The Mosaic Law contained stipulations concerning pledges in order to protect the interests of poor and defenseless members of the nation.—Ex 22:26; Eze 18:7.

Pomegranate.

A fruit that is shaped like an apple, with a rosette or crown at one end. Crowded within the hard rind are small capsules full of juice, each containing a tiny pink or red seed. Pomegranate-shaped ornaments adorned the hem of the high priest’s blue sleeveless coat as well as the capitals of the pillars Jachin and Boaz in front of the temple.—Ex 28:34; Nu 13:23; 1Ki 7:18.

Porneia.—

See SEXUAL IMMORALITY.

Potter.

A maker of earthenware pots, dishes, and other vessels. The Hebrew word for potter literally means “former.” The potter’s authority over the clay is often used to illustrate Jehovah’s sovereignty over individuals and nations.—Isa 64:8; Ro 9:21.

Praetorian Guard.

A group of Roman soldiers established as a bodyguard for the Roman emperor. The guard came to be a powerful political force in supporting or overthrowing an emperor.—Php 1:13.

Prefect.

An official lower in rank than a satrap in the Babylonian government. In the Bible, prefects were in a position of authority over the wise men in the Babylonian court. Prefects are also mentioned during the rule of King Darius the Mede.—Da 2:48; 6:7.

Preparation.

A name for the day before the Sabbath, during which the Jews made the necessary preparations. The day ended at sundown of what is today called Friday, at which time the Sabbath would begin. The Jewish day ran from evening to evening.—Mr 15:42; Lu 23:54.

Presence.

In some contexts in the Christian Greek Scriptures, this word describes the royal presence of Jesus Christ from the time of his invisible enthronement as Messianic King onward in the last days of this system of things. Christ’s presence is not simply a coming followed by a quick departure; rather, it covers a marked period of time.—Mt 24:3.

Priest.

A man who officially represented God to the people he served, instructing them about God and his laws. Priests also represented the people before God, offering sacrifices as well as interceding and pleading for the people. Before the Mosaic Law was instituted, the family head served as priest for his family. Under the Mosaic Law, the male members of the family of Aaron of the tribe of Levi made up the priesthood. The rest of the male Levites were their assistants. At the inauguration of the new covenant, spiritual Israel became a nation of priests, with Jesus Christ as High Priest.—Ex 28:41; Heb 9:24; Re 5:10.

Proconsul.

The principal governor of a province administered by the Roman Senate. He had judicial and military power, and although his actions were subject to review by the Senate, he wielded supreme authority in the province.—Ac 13:7; 18:12.

Prophecy.

An inspired message, whether a revelation of divine will or the proclamation of it. Prophecy may be an inspired moral teaching, an expression of a divine command or judgment, or a declaration of something to come.—Eze 37:9, 10; Da 9:24; Mt 13:14; 2Pe 1:20, 21.

Prophet.

One through whom divine purposes are made known. Prophets acted as spokesmen for God, conveying not only predictions but also Jehovah’s teachings, commands, and judgments.—Am 3:7; 2Pe 1:21.

Propitiation.—

See ATONEMENT.

Propitiatory cover.

The cover of the ark of the covenant, before which the high priest spattered the blood of sin offerings on Atonement Day. The Hebrew term comes from a root verb meaning “to cover over (sin)” or perhaps “to wipe away (sin).” It was made of solid gold, with two cherubs, one mounted at each end. It is sometimes referred to simply as “the cover.” (Ex 25:17-22; 1Ch 28:11; Heb 9:5)—See App. B5.

Proselyte.

A convert. In the Scriptures, this refers to one who embraced Judaism, which in the case of a male involved getting circumcised.—Mt 23:15; Ac 13:43.

Prostitute.

A person who engages in sexual relations outside the marriage bond, especially for money. (The Greek word for “prostitute,” porʹne, comes from a root meaning “to sell.”) The term usually refers to a woman, although male prostitutes are also mentioned in the Bible. Prostitution was condemned in the Mosaic Law, and a prostitute’s wages were unacceptable as a contribution to Jehovah’s sanctuary, in contrast with the pagan practice of using temple prostitutes as a source of revenue. (De 23:17, 18; 1Ki 14:24) The Bible also uses the term figuratively, referring to people, nations, or organizations that engage in some form of idolatry while claiming to be worshippers of God. For example, the religious entity called “Babylon the Great” is described in Revelation as a prostitute because she has consorted with the rulers of this world for power and material gain.—Re 17:1-5; 18:3; 1Ch 5:25.

Proverb.

A wise saying or short story that teaches a lesson or expresses a profound truth in very few words. A Biblical proverb may take the form of a puzzling saying or a riddle. A proverb embodies a truth in expressive language, often metaphorically. Some sayings became common expressions of ridicule or contempt for certain people.—Ec 12:9; 2Pe 2:22.

Psalm.

A song of praise to God. Psalms were set to music and sung by worshippers, including in public worship of Jehovah God at his temple in Jerusalem.—Lu 20:42; Ac 13:33; Jas 5:13.

Purim.

The annual festival celebrated on the 14th and 15th of Adar. It commemorates the Jews’ deliverance from destruction in Queen Esther’s time. The non-Hebrew word pu·rimʹ means “lots.” The Festival of Purim, or Festival of Lots, was so named from the act of Haman in casting Pur (the Lot) to determine the day to carry out his extermination plot against the Jews.—Es 3:7; 9:26.

Q

Queen of Heaven.

The title of a goddess worshipped by apostate Israelites in the days of Jeremiah. Some suggest that it refers to the Babylonian goddess Ishtar (Astarte). The name of her earlier Sumerian counterpart, Inanna, means “Queen of Heaven.” Besides being associated with the heavens, she was a fertility goddess. Astarte is also called “Lady of Heaven” in an Egyptian inscription.—Jer 44:19.

R

Rahab.

An expression used symbolically in the books of Job, Psalms, and Isaiah (not to be confused with the woman Rahab in the book of Joshua). In the book of Job, the context helps to identify Rahab as a sea monster; in other contexts this sea monster is used as a symbol for Egypt.—Job 9:13; Ps 87:4; Isa 30:7; 51:9, 10.

Ransom.

A price paid to provide a release from captivity, punishment, suffering, sin, or even an obligation. The price was not always monetary. (Isa 43:3) A ransom was required in a number of different situations. For example, all firstborn boys or male animals in Israel belonged to Jehovah, and a ransom, or redemption price, needed to be paid to release them from exclusive use in Jehovah’s service. (Nu 3:45, 46; 18:15, 16) If an unguarded, dangerous bull killed someone, a ransom was imposed on its owner in order to release him from the prescribed death sentence. (Ex 21:29, 30) However, no ransom was accepted for a willful murderer. (Nu 35:31) Most important, the Bible highlights the ransom that Christ paid by his sacrificial death in order to release obedient humankind from sin and death.—Ps 49:7, 8; Mt 20:28; Eph 1:7.

Reed.

A term used for numerous plants commonly growing in wet places. The plant intended in many cases is Arundo donax. (Job 8:11; Isa 42:3; Mt 27:29; Re 11:1)—See MEASURING REED.

Repentance.

In Biblical usage, a change of mind accompanied by heartfelt regret over a former way of life, wrong actions, or what one has failed to do. Genuine repentance produces fruitage, a changed course of action.—Mt 3:8; Ac 3:19; 2Pe 3:9.

Resurrection.

A rising up from death. The Greek word a·naʹsta·sis literally means “raising up; standing up.” Nine resurrections are mentioned in the Bible, including the resurrection of Jesus by Jehovah God. Although other resurrections were performed through Elijah, Elisha, Jesus, Peter, and Paul, these miracles are clearly attributed to God’s power. The earthly resurrection of “both the righteous and the unrighteous” is essential to God’s purpose. (Ac 24:15) The Bible also mentions a heavenly resurrection, termed “the earlier” or “the first” resurrection, involving the spirit-anointed brothers of Jesus.—Php 3:11; Re 20:5, 6; Joh 5:28, 29; 11:25.

Righteousness.

In the Scriptures, what is right according to God’s standard of right and wrong.—Ge 15:6; De 6:25; Pr 11:4; Zep 2:3; Mt 6:33.

S

Sabbath.

From a Hebrew word meaning “to rest; to cease.” It is the seventh day of the Jewish week (sunset Friday to sunset Saturday). Some other festive days in the year, as well as the 7th and 50th years, were also called sabbaths. On the Sabbath day, no work except priestly service in the sanctuary was to be done. In Sabbath years, the land was to lie uncultivated and fellow Hebrews were not pressed for repayment of debts. In the Mosaic Law, the restrictions for the Sabbath were reasonable, but religious leaders gradually added to them, so that by Jesus’ day they were hard for people to observe.—Ex 20:8; Le 25:4; Lu 13:14-16; Col 2:16.

Sackcloth.

A coarse cloth used in making sacks, or bags, such as those for containing grain. It was usually woven from dark-colored goat’s hair and was the traditional garment of mourning.—Ge 37:34; Lu 10:13.

Sacred pillar.

An upright pillar, usually of stone, and evidently a phallic symbol of Baal or of other false gods.—Ex 23:24.

Sacred pole.

The Hebrew word (ʼashe·rahʹ) refers to (1) a sacred pole representing Asherah, a Canaanite goddess of fertility, or (2) an image of the goddess Asherah herself. The poles apparently stood upright and were made, at least in part, of wood. They may have been uncarved poles, or even trees.—De 16:21; Jg 6:26; 1Ki 15:13.

Sacred secret.

An aspect of God’s purpose that originates with God, is withheld until his own time, and is revealed only to those whom he chooses to make it known.—Mr 4:11; Col 1:26.

Sacred service.

Ministry, or work, that is sacred, being directly related to one’s worship of God.—Ro 12:1; Re 7:15.

Sacrifice.

An offering presented to God as a token to express thanksgiving, to acknowledge guilt, and to restore good relations with him. Starting with Abel, humans offered various voluntary sacrifices, including animals, until the Mosaic Law covenant made them a requirement. Animal sacrifices were no longer needed after Jesus gave his own life as a perfect sacrifice, though Christians continue to offer spiritual sacrifices to God.—Ge 4:4; Heb 13:15, 16; 1Jo 4:10.

Sadducees.

A prominent religious sect of Judaism made up of wealthy aristocrats and priests who wielded great authority over the activities at the temple. They rejected the many oral traditions observed by the Pharisees as well as other Pharisaic beliefs. They did not believe in the resurrection or in the existence of angels. They opposed Jesus.—Mt 16:1; Ac 23:8.

Samaria.

The capital city of the northern ten-tribe kingdom of Israel for some 200 years, as well as the name of its entire territory. The city was built on a mountain of the same name. In Jesus’ time, Samaria was the name of a district that lay between Galilee in the north and Judea in the south. Jesus usually refrained from preaching in the region in his travels, but at times he passed through it and spoke to the inhabitants. Peter used the second figurative key of the Kingdom when the Samaritans received the holy spirit. (1Ki 16:24; Joh 4:7; Ac 8:14)—See App. B10.

Samaritans.

The term initially referred to the Israelites of the northern ten-tribe kingdom, but after the conquest of Samaria by the Assyrians in 740 B.C.E., it included the foreigners brought in by the Assyrians. In Jesus’ day, rather than having a racial or political connotation, the name usually referred to those who belonged to the religious sect that was located in the vicinity of ancient Shechem and Samaria. The sect’s adherents held certain beliefs that were distinctly different from those of Judaism.—Joh 8:48.

Sanctuary.

Generally, a place set apart for worship, a holy place. Most often, though, it designates either the tabernacle or the temple in Jerusalem. The term is also used of God’s dwelling place in the heavens.—Ex 25:8, 9; 2Ki 10:25; 1Ch 28:10; Re 11:19.

Sanhedrin.

The Jewish high court in Jerusalem. In Jesus’ day, it was made up of 71 members, including the high priest and others who had held the office of high priest, members of the high priestly families, elders, tribal and family heads, and scribes.—Mr 15:1; Ac 5:34; 23:1, 6.

Satan.

A Hebrew word meaning “Resister.” When used with the definite article in the original languages, it refers to Satan the Devil, God’s chief Adversary.—Job 1:6; Mt 4:10; Re 12:9.

Satrap.

A viceroy, or governor of a province, in the Babylonian and Persian empires. A satrap was appointed by the king as a chief ruler.—Ezr 8:36; Da 6:1.

Scepter.

A baton or rod carried by a ruler as an emblem of royal authority.—Ge 49:10; Heb 1:8.

Scourge.

In the Hebrew Scriptures, this term usually refers to a plague, a disease, or a calamity sent from Jehovah as punishment. In the Christian Greek Scriptures, it refers to beating or flogging with a whip that had knots or barbed ends.—Nu 16:49; Joh 19:1.

Scribe.

A copyist of the Hebrew Scriptures. By the time Jesus came to earth, it designated a class of men learned in the Law. They opposed Jesus.—Ezr 7:6, ftn.; Mr 12:38, 39; 14:1.

Scripture(s).

The sacred writings of God’s Word. This expression occurs only in the Christian Greek Scriptures.—Lu 24:27; 2Ti 3:16.

Scroll.

A long sheet of parchment or papyrus, with writing on one side, which was usually rolled around a stick. The Scriptures were written and copied on scrolls, the common book form during the period of Bible writing.—Jer 36:4, 18, 23; Lu 4:17-20; 2Ti 4:13.

Seah.

A dry measure. Basing the capacity on the corresponding liquid bath measure, it would equal 7.33 L (6.66 dry qt). (2Ki 7:1)—See App. B14.

Seal.

A device used to make an impression (usually on clay or wax) that showed ownership, authenticity, or agreement. Ancient seals consisted of a piece of hard material (stone, ivory, or wood) having engraved letters or designs in reverse. A seal is used figuratively for something stamped as authentic, or as a mark of possession, or as something that is hidden or secret.—Ex 28:11; Ne 9:38; Re 5:1; 9:4.

Seal ring.

A type of seal that was worn on the finger or on a cord, probably around the neck. Also called a signet ring, it was the symbol of authority of a ruler or an official. (Ge 41:42)—See SEAL.

Sect.

A body of people adhering to a doctrine or to a leader and following their own beliefs. It is used of the two prominent branches of Judaism, the Pharisees and the Sadducees. Non-Christians also called Christianity a “sect” or “the sect of the Nazarenes,” possibly viewing it as a breakaway from Judaism. Sects eventually developed in the Christian congregation; “the sect of Nicolaus” is mentioned specifically in Revelation.—Ac 5:17; 15:5; 24:5; 28:22; Re 2:6; 2Pe 2:1.

Seer.

A person enabled by God to discern the divine will, one whose eyes had been opened to see or understand things that were not evident to humans in general. The Hebrew word is drawn from a root word meaning “to see,” either literally or figuratively. A seer was a person consulted by others for wise counsel on problems encountered.—1Sa 9:9.

Selah.

A technical term for music or recitation found in Psalms and Habakkuk. It may mean a pause in the singing or in the music, or in both, for the purpose of silent meditation or to make the sentiment just expressed stand out. The Greek Septuagint rendering is di·aʹpsal·ma, defined as “a musical interlude.”—Ps 3:4; Hab 3:3.

Seraphs.

Spirit creatures stationed around Jehovah’s throne in the heavens. The Hebrew term sera·phimʹ literally means “burning ones.”—Isa 6:2, 6.

Sexual immorality.

From the Greek por·neiʹa, a term used in the Scriptures to refer to certain sexual activities forbidden by God. It includes adultery, prostitution, sexual relations between unmarried individuals, homosexuality, and bestiality. It is used figuratively in Revelation with regard to a religious prostitute called “Babylon the Great” to describe her consorting with the rulers of this world for power and material gain. (Re 14:8; 17:2; 18:3; Mt 5:32; Ac 15:29; Ga 5:19)—See PROSTITUTE.

Shebat.

After the Babylonian exile, the name of the 11th month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the 5th month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-January to mid-February. (Zec 1:7)—See App. B15.

Shekel.

The basic Hebrew unit of weight and of monetary value. The weight equaled 11.4 g (0.403 oz; 0.367 oz t). The “shekel of the holy place” may have been an expression used to emphasize that the weight should be precise or that it should conform to a standard weight kept at the tabernacle. There may have been a royal shekel (different from the common shekel) or a standard weight kept at the royal palace.—Ex 30:13.

Sheminith.

A musical term literally meaning “the eighth” that may refer to a lower musical register, or mode. For instruments, the word probably pointed to those that produced the bass tones of the musical scale. For songs, it likely referred to musical accompaniment in a lower range and sung accordingly.—1Ch 15:21; Ps 6:Sup; 12:Sup.

Sheol.

A Hebrew word corresponding to the Greek word “Hades.” It is translated “Grave” (capitalized), to distinguish it as the common grave of mankind rather than an individual grave.—Ge 37:35; Ps 16:10; Ac 2:31 (ftns.).

Showbread.

Twelve loaves of bread that were placed in two stacks of six each on the table in the Holy compartment of the tabernacle and of the temple. Also called “layer bread” and “loaves of presentation.” This offering to God was replaced with fresh bread on each Sabbath. The bread that was removed was normally eaten only by the priests. (2Ch 2:4; Mt 12:4; Ex 25:30; Le 24:5-9; Heb 9:2)—See App. B5.

Sign.

An object, act, situation, or unusual display that has significance as an indicator of something else, present or future.—Ge 9:12, 13; 2Ki 20:9; Mt 24:3; Re 1:1.

Sin offering.

A sacrifice offered for unintentional sin committed because of weakness of the imperfect flesh. Various animal sacrifices, from bull to pigeon, were used, according to the position and circumstances of the one whose sin was being atoned for.—Le 4:27, 29; Heb 10:8.

Sivan.

After the Babylonian exile, the name of the third month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the ninth month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-May to mid-June. (Es 8:9)—See App. B15.

Sling.

A leather strip or a woven band of such materials as animal sinews, rushes, or hair. The wide center part held the projectile, often a stone. One end of the sling was tied to the hand or wrist, while the other was held in the hand and released when the sling was swung. Ancient nations employed slingers in their armies.—Jg 20:16; 1Sa 17:50.

Snuffers.

Tools made of gold, possibly similar to tongs, that were used in the tabernacle and the temple to put out the flame on lamps.—Ex 37:23.

Solomon’s Colonnade.

In the temple in Jesus’ day, a covered passageway on the east of the outer courtyard, popularly believed to be a remnant from Solomon’s temple. There Jesus walked ‘in the wintertime,’ and there early Christians met for worship. (Joh 10:22, 23; Ac 5:12)—See App. B11.

Song of the Ascents.

The superscription of Psalms 120-134. Although there are various ideas on the meaning of the phrase, many believe that these 15 psalms were sung by joyful Israelite worshippers as they ‘ascended’ to Jerusalem, which was situated high in the mountains of Judah, in order to attend the three great annual festivals there.

Son of David.

A phrase often applied to Jesus, emphasizing that he is the Heir of the Kingdom covenant that was to be fulfilled by someone in David’s lineage.—Mt 12:23; 21:9.

Son of man.

An expression found about 80 times in the Gospels. It applies to Jesus Christ and shows that by means of his fleshly birth, he became a human and was not simply a spirit creature with a materialized body. The phrase also indicates that Jesus would fulfill the prophecy recorded at Daniel 7:13, 14. In the Hebrew Scriptures, this expression was used for Ezekiel and Daniel, highlighting the difference between these mortal spokesmen and the divine Originator of their message.—Eze 3:17; Da 8:17; Mt 19:28; 20:28.

Sons of Aaron.

Descendants of Levi’s grandson Aaron, who was chosen as the first high priest under the Mosaic Law. The sons of Aaron performed the priestly duties at the tabernacle and at the temple.—1Ch 23:28.

Sorcery.

The use of power that is acknowledged to be from wicked spirits.—2Ch 33:6.

Soul.

The traditional rendering of the Hebrew word neʹphesh and the Greek word psy·kheʹ. In examining the way these terms are used in the Bible, it becomes evident that they basically refer to (1) people, (2) animals, or (3) the life that a person or an animal has. (Ge 1:20; 2:7; Nu 31:28; 1Pe 3:20; also ftns.) In contrast to the way that the term “soul” is used in many religious contexts, the Bible shows that both neʹphesh and psy·kheʹ, in connection with earthly creatures, refer to that which is material, tangible, visible, and mortal. In this translation, these original-language words have most often been rendered according to their meaning in each context, using such terms as “life,” “creature,” “person,” “one’s whole being,” or simply as a personal pronoun (for example, “I” for “my soul”). In most cases, footnotes give the alternative rendering “soul.” When the term “soul” is used, either in the main text or in footnotes, it should be understood in line with the above explanation. When referring to doing something with one’s whole soul, it means to do it with one’s whole being, wholeheartedly, or with one’s whole life. (De 6:5; Mt 22:37) In some contexts, these original-language words can be used to refer to the desire or appetite of a living creature. They can also refer to a dead person or a dead body.—Nu 6:6; Pr 23:2; Isa 56:11; Hag 2:13.

Span.

A linear measure approximately equal to the distance between the end of the thumb and the end of the little finger when the hand is spread out. Based on the cubit of 44.5 cm (17.5 in.), a span would be 22.2 cm (8.75 in.) in length. (Ex 28:16; 1Sa 17:4)—See App. B14.

Spelt.

An inferior kind of wheat (Triticum spelta), the kernels of which are not readily separated from the chaff.—Ex 9:32.

Spirit.

The Hebrew word ruʹach and the Greek word pneuʹma, often translated “spirit,” have a number of meanings. All of them refer to that which is invisible to human sight and gives evidence of force in motion. The Hebrew and Greek words are used with reference to (1) wind, (2) the active life-force in earthly creatures, (3) the impelling force that issues from a person’s figurative heart and causes him to say and do things in a certain way, (4) inspired expressions originating from an invisible source, (5) spirit persons, and (6) God’s active force, or holy spirit.—Ex 35:21; Ps 104:29; Mt 12:43; Lu 11:13.

Spiritism.

The belief that the spirits of dead humans survive the death of the physical body and that they can and do communicate with the living, especially through a person (a medium) particularly susceptible to their influence. The Greek word for “practice of spiritism” is phar·ma·kiʹa, which literally means “druggery.” This term came to be connected with spiritism because in ancient times, drugs were used when invoking the power of the demons in order to practice sorcery.—Ga 5:20; Re 21:8.

Spirit medium.

Someone who claims to talk with the dead.—Le 20:27; De 18:10-12; 2Ki 21:6.

Spoil.

Personal or household effects, livestock, or other items of value that are taken as plunder from a defeated enemy.—Jos 7:21; 22:8; Heb 7:4.

Stake.

An upright pole to which a victim was fastened. It was used in some nations for execution and/or for exposing a dead body as a warning to others or for public humiliation. The Assyrians, noted for their savage warfare, impaled captives by hanging their bodies atop pointed stakes that had been run up through the abdomen into the chest cavity of the victim. In Jewish law, though, those guilty of such heinous crimes as blasphemy or idolatry were first killed by stoning or by some other method, and then their dead bodies were hung on stakes, or trees, as warning examples to others. (De 21:22, 23; 2Sa 21:6, 9) The Romans sometimes simply tied a victim to the stake, in which case he might live for several days before he died from pain, thirst, hunger, and exposure to the sun. In other cases, such as the execution of Jesus, they nailed the hands and feet of the accused to a stake. (Lu 24:20; Joh 19:14-16; 20:25; Ac 2:23, 36)—See TORTURE STAKE.

Stocks.

An instrument of confinement for punishment. Some devices confined only the feet, while others kept the body in a distorted position, perhaps confining feet, hands, and neck.—Jer 20:2; Ac 16:24.

Stoic philosophers.

A Greek school of philosophers who believed that happiness consists of living in accord with reason and nature. The truly wise man, in their estimation, was indifferent to pain or pleasure.—Ac 17:18.

Superscription.

The heading at the beginning of a psalm that identifies the writer, gives background information, provides musical instructions, or indicates the use or purpose of the psalm.—See the superscriptions of Psalms 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 30, 38, 60, 92, 102.

Synagogue.

A word meaning “a bringing together; an assembly,” but in most scriptures, the building or place where Jews assembled for Scripture reading, instruction, preaching, and prayer. In Jesus’ day, each sizable town in Israel had a synagogue, and the larger cities had more than one.—Lu 4:16; Ac 13:14, 15.

Syria; Syrians.—

See ARAM; ARAMAEANS.

Syrtis.

Two large shallow gulfs on the coast of Libya, North Africa, feared by ancient sailors because of the treacherous sandbanks that were constantly shifting as a result of the tides. (Ac 27:17)—See App. B13.

System(s) of things.

Rendering of the Greek word ai·onʹ when it refers to the current state of affairs or features that distinguish a certain period of time, epoch, or age. The Bible speaks of “the present system of things,” referring to the prevailing state of affairs in the world in general and the worldly way of life. (2Ti 4:10) By means of the Law covenant, God introduced a system of things that some might call the Israelite or Jewish epoch. By means of his ransom sacrifice, Jesus Christ was used by God to introduce a different system of things, one primarily involving the congregation of anointed Christians. This marked the beginning of a new epoch, characterized by the realities foreshadowed by the Law covenant. When in the plural, this phrase refers to the various systems of things, or prevailing states of affairs, that have existed or will exist.—Mt 24:3; Mr 4:19; Ro 12:2; 1Co 10:11.

T

Tabernacle.

A transportable tent of worship used by Israel after the Exodus from Egypt. It housed the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, which was representative of God’s presence, and served as a place of sacrifice and worship. It is also sometimes called “the tent of meeting.” It was a framework of wooden panels enclosed by linen coverings embroidered with cherubs. It was divided into two rooms, the first called the Holy, and the second, the Most Holy. (Jos 18:1; Ex 25:9)—See App. B5.

Talent.

The largest of the Hebrew units of weight and of monetary value. It weighed 34.2 kg (75.5 lb; 91.75 lb t; 1,101 oz t). A Greek talent was smaller, weighing about 20.4 kg (44.8 lb; 54.5 lb t; 654 oz t). (1Ch 22:14; Mt 18:24)—See App. B14.

Tammuz.

(1) The name of a deity over whom apostate Hebrew women in Jerusalem wept. It has been suggested that Tammuz was originally a king who was deified after his death. In Sumerian text, Tammuz is called Dumuzi and is identified as the consort or lover of the fertility goddess Inanna (the Babylonian Ishtar). (Eze 8:14) (2) After the Babylonian exile, the name of the fourth Jewish lunar month of the sacred calendar and the tenth month of the secular calendar. This month ran from mid-June to mid-July.—See App. B15.

Tarshish, ships of.

Initially a term used for ships that made trips to ancient Tarshish (modern-day Spain). It seems that the term eventually came to stand for large ships capable of long-distance travel. Solomon and Jehoshaphat utilized such ships for trade purposes.—1Ki 9:26; 10:22; 22:48.

Tartarus.

In the Christian Greek Scriptures, a prisonlike abased condition into which the disobedient angels of Noah’s day were cast. At 2 Peter 2:4, the use of the verb tar·ta·roʹo (to “cast into Tartarus”) does not signify that “the angels who sinned” were cast into the pagan mythological Tartarus (that is, an underground prison and place of darkness for the lesser gods). Rather, it indicates that they were abased by God from their heavenly place and privileges and were delivered over to a condition of deepest mental darkness respecting God’s bright purposes. Darkness also marks their own eventuality, which the Scriptures show is everlasting destruction along with their ruler, Satan the Devil. Therefore, Tartarus denotes the lowest condition of abasement for those rebellious angels. It is not the same as “the abyss” spoken of at Revelation 20:1-3.

Tebeth.

After the Babylonian exile, the name of the tenth month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the fourth month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-December to mid-January. It is generally referred to simply as “the tenth month.” (Es 2:16)—See App. B15.

Temple.

The permanent building in Jerusalem that replaced the portable tabernacle as the center of Israelite worship. The first temple was built by Solomon and was destroyed by the Babylonians. The second one was built by Zerubbabel after the return from Babylonian exile and was later rebuilt by Herod the Great. In the Scriptures, the temple was often simply called “the house of Jehovah.” (Ezr 1:3; 6:14, 15; 1Ch 29:1; 2Ch 2:4; Mt 24:1)—See App. B8 and B11.

Tenth (tithe).

A tenth part, or 10 percent, given or paid as a tribute, especially for religious purposes. It is also called a “tithe,” and giving it is called “tithing.” (Mal 3:10; De 26:12; Mt 23:23) Under the Mosaic Law, a tenth of the produce of the land and a tenth of the increase of the herds and flocks were given to the Levites yearly to support them. The Levites gave a tenth of this tenth to the Aaronic priesthood to support them. There were some additional tithes as well. Tithing is not required of Christians.

Tent of meeting.

An expression applied both to the tent of Moses and to the sacred tabernacle originally erected in the wilderness.—Ex 33:7; 39:32.

Teraphim.

Family gods or idols, at times consulted for omens. (Eze 21:21) Some were the size and shape of a man, while others were much smaller. (Ge 31:34; 1Sa 19:13, 16) Archaeological findings in Mesopotamia indicate that possessing the teraphim images had a bearing on who would receive the family inheritance. (This may explain why Rachel took her father’s teraphim.) This does not seem to have been the case in Israel, although the idolatrous use of teraphim existed in the days of the judges as well as the kings, and they were included among the items destroyed by faithful King Josiah.—Jg 17:5; 2Ki 23:24; Ho 3:4.

Testimony.

“The Testimony” usually refers to the Ten Commandments as written on the two stone tablets given to Moses.—Ex 31:18.

Thanksgiving offering.

A communion offering intended to praise God for his provisions and loyal love. The flesh of the animal offering and both leavened and unleavened bread were eaten. The flesh had to be eaten the same day.—2Ch 29:31.

Thresh; Threshing floor.

The process of releasing grain from its stalk and chaff; the place where this work was done. Threshing was done by hand with a rod, or for larger quantities, with special equipment, such as threshing sledges or rollers, pulled by animals. The equipment ran over the grain that was spread on the threshing floor, a flat circular area usually at a high elevation exposed to wind.—Le 26:5; Isa 41:15; Mt 3:12.

Tishri.—

See ETHANIM and App. B15.

Torture stake.

The rendering of the Greek word stau·rosʹ, meaning an upright stake or pole, such as the one on which Jesus was executed. There is no evidence that the Greek word meant a cross, such as the pagans used as a religious symbol for many centuries before Christ. “Torture stake” conveys the full intent of the original word, since the word stau·rosʹ is also used to indicate the torture, suffering, and shame that Jesus’ followers would face. (Mt 16:24; Heb 12:2)—See STAKE.

Transgress; Transgression.

To overstep a stated law; the act of overstepping a law. It is synonymous with “sin” in the Bible.—Ps 51:3; Ro 5:14.

Tree of life.

A tree in the garden of Eden. The Bible does not indicate that it had inherent life-giving qualities in its fruit; instead, it represented God’s guarantee of everlasting life to those he would allow to eat of its fruit.—Ge 2:9; 3:22.

Tree of the knowledge of good and bad.

A tree in the garden of Eden that God used as a symbol of his right to set the standards for mankind as to what is “good” and what is “bad.”—Ge 2:9, 17.

Tribute.

Payment by one State or ruler to another as a mark of submission, in order to maintain peace or to gain protection. (2Ki 3:4; 18:14-16; 2Ch 17:11) The word is also used for a personal tax on individuals.—Ne 5:4; Ro 13:7.

True God, the.

A rendering of the Hebrew expression for “the God.” In many cases, this use of the definite article in Hebrew serves to distinguish Jehovah as the only true God in contrast to false gods. The rendering “the true God” carefully preserves the full meaning of the Hebrew expression in such contexts.—Ge 5:22, 24; 46:3; De 4:39.

Trumpet.

A wind instrument made of metal, used for signaling and for music. According to Numbers 10:2, Jehovah gave instructions for making two silver trumpets that would be used to sound specific signals for summoning the assembly, for breaking camp, or for proclaiming war. These likely were straight trumpets, unlike the curved “horns” that were actually made from animal horns. Trumpets of unspecified construction were also included among the musical instruments at the temple. The sound of trumpets often symbolically accompanies the proclamation of Jehovah’s judgments or other significant events of divine origin.—2Ch 29:26; Ezr 3:10; 1Co 15:52; Re 8:7–11:15.

Turban.

A cloth wrapped around the head and worn as a headdress. The high priest wore a turban of fine linen, with a gold plate tied to its front with a blue cord. The king wore a turban under his crown. Job used the expression figuratively when he likened his justice to a turban.—Ex 28:36, 37; Job 29:14; Eze 21:26.

U

Unclean.

May refer to being physically dirty or to breaking moral laws. In the Bible, though, the word often refers to what is not acceptable, or not clean, according to the Mosaic Law. (Le 5:2; 13:45; Mt 10:1; Ac 10:14; Eph 5:5)—See CLEAN.

Undeserved kindness.

A Greek word with the central idea of that which is agreeable and winsome. The word is often used to refer to a kind gift or a kind manner of giving. When referring to the undeserved kindness of God, the word describes a free gift given generously by God, with no expectation of repayment. Thus, it is an expression of God’s bounteous giving and generous love and kindness toward humans. The Greek term is also rendered by such expressions as “favor” and “kind gift.” It is given unearned and unmerited, motivated solely by the generosity of the giver.—2Co 6:1; Eph 1:7.

Unleavened.

Referring to bread that is made without leaven.—De 16:3; Mr 14:12; 1Co 5:8.

Urim and Thummim.

Objects used by the high priest in a manner similar to the use of lots to determine the divine will when questions of national importance needed an answer from Jehovah. The Urim and Thummim were put inside the high priest’s breastpiece when he entered the tabernacle. Their use seems to have ceased when the Babylonians destroyed Jerusalem.—Ex 28:30; Ne 7:65.

V

Vow.

A solemn promise made to God to perform some act, make some offering or gift, enter some service, or abstain from certain things not unlawful in themselves. It carried the force of an oath.—Nu 6:2; Ec 5:4; Mt 5:33.

Vow offering.

A voluntary offering that accompanied certain vows.—Le 23:38; 1Sa 1:21.

W

Wadi.

The valley or bed of a stream that is usually dry except during the rainy season; the word may also refer to the stream itself. Some streams were fed by springs and were therefore perennial. The wadi is referred to as “valley” in some contexts.—Ge 26:19; Nu 34:5; De 8:7; 1Ki 18:5; Job 6:15.

Warp.

In weaving, the group of threads running the length of the fabric. The set of threads woven alternately over and under these at right angles across the cloth are the woof.—Jg 16:13.

Watchman.

One who guards against possible harm to people or property, often during the night, and who may sound an alarm in the face of threatened danger. Watchmen were often stationed on the city walls and towers to observe those approaching before they got close. A watchman in the military is usually called a guard or a sentry. Figuratively, prophets served as watchmen to the nation of Israel, warning of impending destruction.—2Ki 9:20; Eze 3:17.

Wave offering.

An offering in which the priest evidently placed his hands under the hands of the worshipper who was holding the sacrifice to be presented and waved them back and forth; or the priest himself waved the offering. This action represented a presenting of the sacrificial offerings to Jehovah.—Le 7:30.

Way, the.

An expression used figuratively in the Scriptures to refer to a mode of action or conduct that is either approved or disapproved by Jehovah. Those who became followers of Jesus Christ were spoken of as belonging to “The Way,” that is, they kept a way of life centered on faith in Jesus Christ, following his example.—Ac 19:9.

Wicked one, the.

A designation for Satan the Devil, who stands in opposition to God and his righteous standards.—Mt 6:13; 1Jo 5:19.

Winepress.

Usually two pits (vats) cut out of natural limestone, one higher than the other, and connected by a small channel. As the grapes were crushed in the upper pit, the juice flowed into the lower pit. The word is used figuratively for God’s judgment.—Isa 5:2; Re 19:15.

Wineskin.

A skin bottle made of the complete hide of an animal, such as a goat or a sheep, and used for holding wine. Wine was put into new wineskins, because as it ferments, it generates carbon dioxide gas that exerts pressure on the skin bottles. New skins expand; old, inflexible ones burst under the pressure.—Jos 9:4; Mt 9:17.

Woof.

In weaving, the set of threads running the width of the fabric. These were woven alternately over and under the warp, that is, the group of threads running the length of the fabric.—Le 13:59.

Wormwood.

Various woody plants having an intensely bitter taste and a strong aromatic odor. Wormwood is used figuratively in the Bible to describe the bitter effects of immorality, enslavement, injustice, and apostasy. At Revelation 8:11, “wormwood” denotes a bitter and poisonous substance, also called absinthe.—De 29:18; Pr 5:4; Jer 9:15; Am 5:7.

Y

Yoke.

A bar borne upon a person’s shoulders, from each side of which loads were suspended, or a wooden bar or frame placed over the necks of two draft animals (usually cattle) when pulling a farm implement or a wagon. Because slaves often used yokes to carry heavy burdens, the yoke was used figuratively to represent enslavement or subjection to another person, as well as oppression and suffering. Removing or breaking the yoke signified liberation from bondage, oppression, and exploitation.—Le 26:13; Mt 11:29, 30.

Z

Zeus.

The supreme god of the polytheistic Greeks. In Lystra, Barnabas was mistakenly identified as Zeus. Ancient inscriptions found near Lystra refer to “priests of Zeus” and “Zeus the sun-god.” The ship Paul traveled on from the island of Malta had the figurehead “Sons of Zeus,” that is, the twin brothers Castor and Pollux.—Ac 14:12; 28:11.

Zion; Mount Zion.

The name of the Jebusite fortress city of Jebus that was on the southeast hill of Jerusalem. After David captured it, he built his royal residence there, and it came to be called “the City of David.” (2Sa 5:7, 9) Zion became a mountain especially holy to Jehovah when David had the Ark transferred there. Later, the name included the temple area on Mount Moriah, and at times the entire city of Jerusalem. It is often used symbolically in the Christian Greek Scriptures.—Ps 2:6; 1Pe 2:6; Re 14:1.

Ziv.

The original name of the second month of the Jewish sacred calendar and the eighth month of the secular calendar. It ran from mid-April to mid-May. It is named Iyyar in the Jewish Talmud and other works dated after the Babylonian exile. (1Ki 6:37)—See App. B15.

A2

Features of This Revision

The New World Translation of the Christian Greek Scriptures was released in English in 1950, and the complete New World Translation of the Holy Scriptures was published in 1961. Since then, tens of millions of readers in well over 210 languages have benefited from this accurate yet readable rendering of the Holy Scriptures from the original languages.

Over the past half century, however, languages have changed. The current New World Bible Translation Committee recognized the need to respond to those changes in order to touch the heart of today’s reader. For this reason, a number of style and vocabulary changes have been made in this revision, with the following objectives in mind:

Use of modern, understandable language. For example, the expression “long-suffering” can be misunderstood to mean “someone who suffers for a long time.” However, the intended idea is that of deliberate restraint, which is better expressed by the term “patience.” (Galatians 5:22) The now obsolete meaning of “dumb” was replaced with “speechless.” (Matthew 9:32, 33) The term “harlot” was changed to “prostitute.” (Genesis 38:15) In this revision, “fornication” is usually rendered as “sexual immorality”; “loose conduct” as “brazen conduct”; and “revelries” as “wild parties.” (Galatians 5:19-21) The expression “time indefinite” was replaced with such terms as “forever,” “lasting,” “everlasting,” or “long ago,” to convey the intended meaning in each context.—Genesis 3:22; Exodus 31:16; Psalm 90:2; Ecclesiastes 1:4; Micah 5:2.

The term “seed” in ancient Hebrew and Greek could refer to plant seed as well as to human offspring, or descendants, or to semen. Because it is no longer common in English to use the term “seed” when referring to humans, it was replaced with expressions that convey the intended idea according to the context. (Genesis 1:11; 22:17; 48:4; Matthew 22:24; John 8:37) In most cases, the term “offspring” is now used when referring to the Edenic promise, found at Genesis 3:15.

The English verb “impale” was used in previous versions of this Bible in connection with the execution of Jesus. While this term could refer to the way that Jesus was nailed to the torture stake, it is more often used in reference to the ancient method of execution by running a sharp stake through the body and fixing the victim on it. Since Jesus was not impaled with the torture stake, this revision uses such expressions as “executed on a stake” and “nailed to the stake” with regard to the manner in which Jesus was fastened to the torture stake.—Matthew 20:19; 27:31, 35.

Biblical expressions clarified. Some terms used in previous editions of the English New World Translation often needed to be explained in order to be properly understood. For example, the Hebrew term “Sheol” and the Greek term “Hades” are used in the Bible to refer to the common grave of mankind. Those terms are unknown to many, and “Hades” has a dual meaning as a result of its usage in Greek mythology. Therefore, both terms were replaced with what was meant by the Bible writers, “the Grave.” The terms “Sheol” and “Hades” are now given in footnotes.—Psalm 16:10; Acts 2:27.

In past editions, the Hebrew word neʹphesh and the Greek word psy·kheʹ were consistently rendered “soul.” In view of the many misconceptions regarding the meaning of the word “soul,” this approach helped the reader to see how the inspired Bible writers used these original-language terms. Depending on the context, those words may refer (1) to a person, (2) to the life of a person, (3) to living creatures, (4) to the desires and appetite of a person or, in some cases, (5) even to dead individuals. However, since such use of the word “soul” is not common in English, the decision was made to render these original-language words according to their intended meaning, usually with a footnote that reads “Or ‘soul.’” (See, for example, Genesis 1:20; 2:7; Leviticus 19:28; Psalm 3:2; Proverbs 16:26; Matthew 6:25.) However, in some poetic or well-known contexts, the word “soul” was retained in the main text, along with a footnote referring to the Glossary or showing another possible rendering.—Deuteronomy 6:5; Psalm 131:2; Proverbs 2:10; Matthew 22:37.

Similarly, the word “kidney” was retained when it refers to the literal organ. However, when it is used figuratively in such verses as Psalm 7:9 and 26:2 and Revelation 2:23, the intended idea of “deepest emotions” or “innermost thoughts” is conveyed in the main text, and the literal idea is given in a footnote.

Like its Hebrew and Greek equivalents, the English expression “heart” has both a literal and a figurative meaning, so it was usually retained in the main text. However, in a few contexts where the sense was not clear, a more explicit rendering was used. For example, in the book of Proverbs, “in want of heart” now reads “lacking good sense,” and the literal idea is given in a footnote. (Proverbs 6:32; 7:7) Other expressions, for instance, “fat,” “flesh,” and “horn,” were handled similarly, according to the context. (Genesis 45:18; Ecclesiastes 5:6; Job 16:15) Some of these expressions are discussed in the “Glossary of Bible Terms.”

Enhanced readability. In previous editions of the English New World Translation, auxiliary expressions were used to indicate whether the Hebrew verb is in the imperfect or the perfect state. For example, the continuous action often expressed by imperfect verbs was indicated by means of the expressions “proceeded to,” “went on to,” “came to be,” and so forth. The emphasis often conveyed by the Hebrew perfect verb was denoted by the added expressions “certainly,” “must,” “actually,” and similar ones. As a result, these terms were used thousands of times in the text. In this revision, auxiliary terms were retained in certain contexts by using such expressions as “kept,” “keep on,” and “used to” when there was a valid reason to express continuous action. (Genesis 3:9; 34:1; Proverbs 2:4) However, they were omitted to enhance readability when the auxiliary expressions were not critical for conveying the original meaning.

Conveying the correct idea of words involving gender. Hebrew and Greek nouns indicate male or female gender, and in Greek, also neuter. At times, though, reflecting the gender of the original-language term may obscure the intended meaning. In both Hebrew and Greek, plural nouns are generally masculine, not only when referring exclusively to males but also when referring to both males and females. For example, though the expression “the sons of Israel” may refer to the 12 sons of Jacob, it more often refers to the entire nation of Israel, both men and women. (Genesis 46:5; Exodus 35:29) So in the revision, this phrase was often rendered “Israelites” to show that it refers to the entire nation. Similarly, the expression “fatherless boy” was rendered “fatherless child” or “orphan” to show that it may refer to a boy or a girl. On the other hand, since the Bible uses the male gender in reference to God and to his Son, as well as to various angels and demons, there is no basis for using genderless terms as is done in some modern translations.

Omission of indicators for second person plural. Past editions also indicated whether the pronouns “you” and “your” and second person verbs were singular or plural by using small capital letters to show plurality. This feature was not retained in this revision, but readers may consult earlier editions of this translation for this information.

All adjustments in the Bible text were made prayerfully, carefully, and with deep respect for the fine work of the original New World Bible Translation Committee.

Other features of this revision:

This Bible edition contains a limited number of footnotes. The footnotes generally fall into the following categories:

“Or” Alternative ways the text could be rendered from Hebrew, Aramaic, or Greek that would give the same overall idea.—Genesis 1:2, footnote on “active force”; Joshua 1:8, “undertone.”

“Or possibly” Alternative ways the text could be rendered that would convey a valid yet different overall idea.—Genesis 21:6, “laugh with me”; Zechariah 14:21, “Canaanite.”

“Lit.” A word-for-word translation from the Hebrew, Aramaic, or Greek or the basic meaning of an original-language expression.—Genesis 30:22, “pregnant”; Exodus 32:9, “obstinate.”

Meaning and background information Meaning of names (Genesis 3:17, “Adam”; Exodus 15:23, “Marah”); details about weights and measures (Genesis 6:15, “cubits”); the antecedent of a pronoun (Genesis 38:5, “He”); helpful information in the Appendix and the Glossary.—Genesis 37:35, “Grave”; Matthew 5:22, “Gehenna.”

The front section, entitled “An Introduction to God’s Word,” contains an outline of basic teachings found in the Bible. Immediately following the Bible text is the “Table of the Books of the Bible,” the “Bible Words Index,” and the “Glossary of Bible Terms.” The Glossary helps the reader understand selected expressions according to their Bible-specific usage. Appendix A contains the following sections: “Principles of Bible Translation,” “Features of This Revision,” “How the Bible Came to Us,” “The Divine Name in the Hebrew Scriptures,” “The Divine Name in the Christian Greek Scriptures,” “Chart: Prophets and Kings of Judah and of Israel,” and “Main Events of Jesus’ Earthly Life.” Appendix B contains maps, charts, and other information useful to diligent Bible students.

In the main text of the Bible, each book features an outline of its chapter contents, along with the related verses, giving the reader an overview of the entire book. The center column of each page contains the most relevant marginal references from previous editions, pointing to related Bible verses.